<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>SCOTUS (CourtListener) + Full Text</title>
    <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/court/scotus/</link>
    <description>Latest SCOTUS items with extracted PDF text.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 15:22:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Ellingburg v. United States</title>
      <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776751/ellingburg-v-united-states/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776751/ellingburg-v-united-states/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/pdf/2026/01/20/ellingburg_v._united_states.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;(Slip Opinion)

OCTOBER  TERM,  2025

1

Syllabus

NOTE:  Where  it  is  feasible,  a  syllabus  (headnote)  will  be  released,  as  is
being  done  in  connection  with  this  case,  at  the  time  the  opinion  is  issued.
The  syllabus  constitutes  no  part  of  the  opinion  of  the  Court  but  has  been
prepared  by  the  Reporter  of  Decisions  for  the  convenience  of  the  reader.
See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

Syllabus

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR
THE EIGHTH CIRCUIT

No. 24–482.  Argued October 14, 2025—Decided  January 20, 2026

The  Mandatory  Victims  Restitution  Act  of  1996  requires  defendants
convicted  of  certain  federal  crimes  to  pay  monetary  restitution  to
victims.  Although  petitioner  Ellingburg  committed  his  crime  before
the  MVRA’s  enactment,  he  was  sentenced  under  the  MRVA  and
ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution.  Ellingburg raised an Ex Post
Facto  Clause  challenge  to  his  continued  restitution  obligation.    The
Eighth  Circuit  concluded  that  restitution  under  the  MVRA  is  not
criminal punishment subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause.

Held: Restitution  under  the  MVRA  is  plainly  criminal  punishment  for
purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.  Whether a law violates the Ex
Post  Facto  Clause  requires  evaluating  whether  the  law  imposes  a
criminal or penal sanction as opposed to a civil remedy.  That question
is one “of statutory construction” that requires the Court to “consider
the  statute’s  text  and  its  structure.”    Smith  v.  Doe,  538  U. S.  84,  92
(quotation marks omitted).  When viewed as a whole, the MVRA makes
abundantly clear that restitution is criminal punishment.  The MVRA
labels  restitution  as  a  “penalty”  for  a  criminal  “offense.”   18  U. S. C.
§3663A(a)(1).    Only  a  criminal  defendant  convicted  of  a  qualifying
crime  may  be  ordered  to  pay  restitution.  Restitution  is  imposed  at
sentencing for that offense together with other criminal punishments
such  as  imprisonment  and  fines.  And  at  the  sentencing  proceeding
where restitution is imposed, the Government, not the victim, is the
party adverse to the defendant.  Further, the federal MVRA restitution
regime is codified in Title 18, “Crimes and Criminal Procedure,” and
the statutory provisions authorizing restitution orders are contained
in  Chapter  232  of  that  Title,  entitled  “Miscellaneous  Sentencing
Provisions.”  A  district  court  imposing  restitution  must  follow  the


2

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

procedures applicable to other criminal penalties.

Syllabus

The  Court’s  precedents  have  understood  restitution  under  the
MVRA to be criminal punishment.  See Manrique v. United States, 581
U. S. 116, 118.  And the Court’s precedents on related issues further
buttress
is  criminal
punishment.    See  United  States  v.  Bajakajian,  524  U. S.  321,  328;
United States v. One Assortment of 89 Firearms, 465 U. S. 354, 363–
366.

that  MVRA  restitution

the  conclusion

Finally,  while  Congress  intended  restitution  under  the  MVRA  to
both punish offenders and compensate victims, victims cannot initiate
or  settle  the  restitution  process  as  they  would  if  it  were  a  civil
proceeding.  The  text  and  structure  of  the  Act  demonstrate  that
Congress  intended  restitution  under  the  Act  to  impose  criminal
punishment.  Pp. 2–5.

113 F. 4th 839, reversed and remanded.

KAVANAUGH, J., delivered the opinion for a unanimous Court.  THOMAS,

J., filed a concurring opinion, in which GORSUCH, J., joined.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

Opinion of the Court

NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the
United  States  Reports.  Readers  are  requested  to  notify  the  Reporter  of
Decisions,  Supreme  Court  of  the  United  States,  Washington,  D.  C.  20543,
pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–482
_________________

HOLSEY ELLINGBURG, JR., PETITIONER
v. UNITED STATES

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE EIGHTH CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE KAVANAUGH delivered the opinion of the Court.
Under  the  Mandatory  Victims  Restitution  Act  of  1996,
defendants  convicted  of  certain  federal  crimes  must  pay
monetary restitution to the victims.  That Act, known as the
MVRA,  became  law  on  April  24,  1996.
Petitioner
Ellingburg was sentenced later in 1996 and ordered to pay
restitution  in  the  amount  of  $7,567.25.  He  has  not  yet
satisfied that obligation.

Ellingburg  has  now  raised  an  Ex  Post  Facto  Clause
challenge to his continued restitution obligation because he
committed  his  crime  before  the  enactment  of  the  MVRA.
The  Ex  Post  Facto  Clause  issue  turns  in  part  on  the
threshold question of whether restitution under the MVRA
is  criminal  punishment.    Applying  Circuit  precedent,  the
U. S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit concluded that
restitution  under  the  MVRA  is  not  criminal  punishment.
113 F. 4th 839, 841–842 (2024).  We now reverse.

In  this  Court,  Ellingburg  and  the  United  States  agree
that the Eighth Circuit erred and that MVRA restitution is
criminal punishment.  The Court therefore appointed John
F.  Bash  as  amicus  curiae  to  defend  the  judgment  of  the


2

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

Opinion of the Court

Eighth  Circuit.  605  U. S.  908  (2025).    He  has  ably
discharged his responsibilities.

When  determining  whether  a  law  violates  the  Ex  Post
Facto  Clause,  the  Court  must  evaluate  whether  the  law
imposes a criminal or penal sanction as opposed to a civil
remedy.  Assessing whether “a statutory scheme is civil or
criminal is first of all a question of statutory construction”
that requires the Court to “consider the statute’s text and
its  structure.”    Smith  v.  Doe,  538  U. S.  84,  92  (2003)
(quotation marks omitted).1

Here,

the  statutory  analysis

is  straightforward:
is  plainly  criminal

Restitution  under
punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.2

the  MVRA

Numerous features of the MVRA lead to that conclusion.
The MVRA labels restitution as a “penalty” for a criminal
“offense.”  18  U.  S. C.  §3663A(a)(1).  A  court  may  order
restitution only with respect to a criminal “defendant” and
only after that defendant’s conviction of a qualifying crime.
Ibid.  Restitution  is  imposed  during  “sentencing”  for  the
offense.
Ibid.  At  the  sentencing  proceeding  where
restitution  is  ordered,  the  Government,  not  the  victim,  is
the party adverse to the defendant.

At sentencing, restitution is imposed together with other
criminal  punishments  such  as  imprisonment  and  fines.
Indeed,  for  misdemeanors,  restitution  may  be  “in  lieu  of ”
sole
those  punishments,  making

restitution

the

——————

1 If  the  text  and  structure  of  a  statute  do  not  demonstrate  that
Congress intended criminal punishment, the statute may still be deemed
criminal  or  penal  if  the  “party  challenging  the  statute  provides  ‘the
clearest  proof’  that  ‘the  statutory  scheme  [is]  so  punitive  either  in
purpose or effect as to negate [the Government’s] intention’ to deem it
‘civil.’ ”  Kansas v. Hendricks, 521 U. S. 346, 361 (1997) (quoting United
States v. Ward, 448 U. S. 242, 248–249 (1980)).

2 Amicus contends that Ellingburg’s restitution was not imposed under
the MVRA even though Ellingburg was sentenced after the MVRA took
effect  in  1996.    But  the  Eighth  Circuit  decided  this  case  on  the
understanding that the MVRA was applied to Ellingburg.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

Opinion of the Court

punishment for a federal offense in certain circumstances.
Ibid.  In  addition,  when  a  defendant  does  not  make  the
required  restitution  payments,  the  court  may  modify  the
terms  of  his  supervised  release  or  probation  and  impose
imprisonment if the court determines that “alternatives to
imprisonment  are  not  adequate  to  serve  the  purposes  of
punishment and deterrence.”  §§3614(b)(2), 3613A(a)(1).

As  a  further  sign  that  MVRA  restitution  is  criminal
punishment,  the  federal  MVRA  restitution  regime  is
codified in Title 18, “Crimes and Criminal Procedure.”  The
main  statutory  provisions  authorizing  restitution  orders,
§3663 and §3663A, are contained in Chapter 232 of Title 18,
entitled  “Miscellaneous  Sentencing  Provisions.”  Another
statutory provision, §3556, states that a court “shall order
restitution”  in  “imposing  a  sentence”  for  covered  offenses.
That provision is housed in Chapter 227 of Title 18, entitled
“Sentences.”  The  statute  also  refers  to  a  “sentence  that
imposes an order of restitution.”  §3664(o).  When imposing
restitution,  a  district  court  must  follow  the  procedures
applicable  to  other  criminal  penalties,  including  the
Federal  Rules  of  Criminal  Procedure.    See  §3664(c).  And
§3663(c)  directs  the  U. S.  Sentencing  Commission  to
promulgate criminal sentencing guidelines for restitution.
§208, 110 Stat. 1240; §3663(c)(7).

When  viewed  as  a  whole,  then,  the  MVRA  makes
abundantly clear that  restitution is criminal punishment.
We are not saying that all of the statutory features present
here are necessary to constitute criminal punishment, but
they are sufficient.

Given  the  statutory  text  and  structure,  it  comes  as  no
surprise  that  this  Court’s  precedents  have  understood
restitution under the MVRA to be criminal punishment.  In
Manrique v. United States, the Court stated that the MVRA
requires  courts  “to  impose  restitution  as  part  of  the
sentence.”  581  U. S.  116,  118  (2017).    In  Pasquantino  v.
United  States,  the  Court  explained  that  restitution  under


4

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

Opinion of the Court

the  MVRA  is  designed  “to  mete  out  appropriate  criminal
punishment.”  544 U. S. 349, 365 (2005).  And in Paroline v.
United  States,  the  Court  repeated  that  description.    572
U. S. 434, 456 (2014).

This Court’s precedents on related issues further buttress
is  criminal
the  conclusion  that  MVRA  restitution
punishment.  For  example,  forfeiture  under  18  U. S. C.
§982(a)(1)—like restitution under the MVRA—occurs at the
culmination  of  a  criminal  proceeding  and  requires
conviction  of  an  underlying  crime.    That  forfeiture,  the
Court  concluded,  is  criminal  punishment.  See  United
States v. Bajakajian, 524 U. S. 321, 328 (1998).  By contrast,
the Court determined that the forfeiture of firearms under
18 U. S. C. §924(d) ordered during an in rem proceeding is
a  civil  sanction.  United  States  v.  One  Assortment  of  89
Firearms, 465 U. S. 354, 363–366 (1984).

As the Government cautions, not everything that occurs
at criminal sentencing or even that appears in a criminal
judgment may necessarily be part of the punishment.  See
Tr. of Oral Arg. 22–23.  But we need not explore that point
further  here  because,  for  the  reasons  we  have  explained,
MVRA restitution is criminal punishment.

Amicus  relies  heavily  on  Smith  v.  Doe,  538  U. S.  84.
There,  this  Court  considered  a  law  requiring  a  defendant
convicted of certain crimes to register as a sex offender.  The
Court  held  that  the  registration  mandate  was  civil.    The
legislature  adopted  “distinctly  civil  procedures”  for  the
imposition  of  registration  requirements.
  Id.,  at  96
(quotation marks omitted).  By  contrast,  to  reiterate  what
we said above, MVRA restitution is labeled as a penalty, is
codified  in  the  criminal  code,  is  predicated  on  a  criminal
conviction,  is  imposed  against  a  criminal  defendant,  is
sometimes imposed in lieu of other penalties, is ordered at
sentencing  where  the  United  States  is  the  adverse  party,
and can result in resentencing when the defendant refuses
to pay.  So Smith v. Doe does not control.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

Opinion of the Court

It is true, as amicus thoroughly explains, that the MVRA
seeks  to  compensate  crime  victims,  a  nonpunitive  goal.
Several provisions of the MVRA reflect that objective, such
as a provision requiring that restitution amounts be based
on  a  victim’s  loss.  §3664(f )(1)(A);  see  also,  e.g.,  §3664(j).
But  those  provisions  show  only  that  Congress  intended
restitution  under  the  MVRA  to  both  punish  and
compensate.  And so long as the text and structure of the
Act demonstrate that Congress intended at least “to impose
punishment,” that “ends the inquiry.”  Smith, 538 U. S., at
92; see Paroline, 572 U. S., at 456; Pasquantino, 544 U. S.,
at 365.

To be sure, as amicus points out, victims receive notice of
sentencing  proceedings  and  are  consulted  by  prosecutors.
But outreach to victims and some participation by victims
in criminal proceedings are not unusual.  See, e.g., §3771(a).
With respect to restitution, the key point is that victims do
not  have  the  power  to  initiate  or  settle  the  restitution
process as they would if it were a civil proceeding.

Our ruling today does not mean that a restitution statute
can never be civil.  But the statutory text and structure of
the MVRA demonstrate that restitution under that Act is
criminal punishment.

For those reasons, we reverse the judgment of the U. S.
Court  of  Appeals  for  the  Eighth  Circuit  and  remand  the
case  for  further  proceedings  consistent  with  this  opinion.
On  remand,  the  Court  of  Appeals  may  consider  the
Government’s  separate  arguments  for  affirmance  of  the
District Court’s judgment.

It is so ordered.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

THOMAS, J., concurring

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–482
_________________

HOLSEY ELLINGBURG, JR., PETITIONER
v. UNITED STATES

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE EIGHTH CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE  THOMAS,  with  whom  JUSTICE  GORSUCH  joins,

concurring.

I join the Court’s opinion in full because it correctly ap-
plies our precedent.  I write separately to clarify the foun-
dation of that precedent.  This Court’s 1798 decision in Cal-
der v. Bull, 3 Dall. 386, established that the Ex Post Facto
Clauses  forbid  only  those  retroactive  laws  that  impose
“punishment” for a “crime.”  Id., at 386, 389–391 (opinion of
Chase, J.).  Over the 228 years since Calder, the Court has
struggled  to articulate what it means for a law to impose
punishment  for  a  crime,  and  thus  to  be  subject  to  the  Ex
Post  Facto  Clauses.  The  Court’s  more  recent  precedents
have  implemented  Calder  through  two  multifactor  tests
that turn largely on whether the legislature labels the law
as criminal or civil.  But in 1798, “punishment” for a “crime”
would have been understood to refer to any coercive penalty
for a public wrong.  Many laws that are nominally civil to-
day would therefore have been subject to the Ex Post Facto
Clauses under Calder.  I would restore Calder’s approach to
the Ex Post Facto Clauses.

I
The Constitution twice prohibits ex post facto laws.  As to
the Federal Government, it provides that “No Bill of Attain-
der or ex post facto Law shall be passed.”  Art. I, §9, cl. 3.


2

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

As to the States, it provides that “No State shall . . . pass
any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing
the Obligation of Contracts.”  Art. I, §10, cl. 1.  In its general
sense,  a  law  is  ex  post  facto—meaning  “after  the  fact”—
when  it  applies  retroactively  to  conduct  that  occurred  be-
fore the law was enacted.
  The two Ex Post Facto Clauses reflected the importance
of  the  protection  to  the  Founding  Fathers.  James  Iredell
believed that the protection against ex post facto laws was
“the most essential right of all,” which was worth “ten thou-
sand declarations of rights” without it.  Answers to Mr. Ma-
son’s Objections to the New Constitution, in Pamphlets on
the Constitution of the United States 334, 368 (P. Ford ed.
1888)  (reprint  1968).  “A  man  may  feel  some  pride  in  his
security,” Iredell wrote, “when he knows that what he does
innocently and safely to-day in accordance with the laws of
his  country,  cannot  be  tortured  into  guilt  and  danger  to-
morrow.”  Ibid.  In the Federalist Papers, Alexander Ham-
ilton placed “the prohibition of ex post facto laws” among the
greatest “securities to liberty and republicanism.”  The Fed-
eralist No. 84, p. 571 (P. Ford ed. 1898).  James Madison
argued that ex post facto laws are “contrary to the first prin-
ciples of the social compact.”  Id., No. 44, at 296.

Ex post facto laws lack legitimacy because laws must pre-
cede the actions that they govern.  Laws regulating actions
after  the  fact  “deprive  citizens  of  notice  and  fair  warning
and  are,  therefore,  an  affront  to  man’s  ‘reason  and
freewill.’ ”  Peugh v. United States, 569 U. S. 530, 561 (2013)
(THOMAS,  J.,  dissenting)  (quoting  1  W.  Blackstone,  Com-
mentaries on the Laws of England 39 (1765) (Blackstone)).
As  Blackstone  explained,  “it  is  impossible  that  the  party
could  foresee”  that  his  actions  would  become  unlawful  if
they were lawful when he took them.  Id., at 46.  When a
man had no notice that his actions were unlawful, “all pun-
ishment  for  not  abstaining  must  of  consequence  be  cruel
and  unjust.”  Ibid.    An  ex  post  facto  law  is  even  “more


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

THOMAS, J., concurring

unreasonable,” Blackstone thought, than the reviled prac-
tice of the Roman emperor “Caligula, who . . . wrote his laws
in a very small character, and hung them up upon high pil-
lars, the more effectually to ensnare the people.”  Ibid.

Many believed that no constitutional prohibition was nec-
essary because an ex post facto law would be invalid as con-
trary to natural law.  At the Constitutional Convention, Ol-
iver Ellsworth argued that “[i]t cannot . . . be necessary to
prohibit” ex post facto laws because “no lawyer, no civilian
. . . would not say that ex post facto laws were void of them-
selves.”  2 M. Farrand, Records of the Federal Convention
of  1787,  p.  376  (1966)  (Farrand).    James  Wilson  thought
that a constitutional prohibition on ex post facto laws would
suggest that the Convention denied that such laws were al-
ready forbidden by natural law, to its embarrassment.  “It
will  bring  reflexions  on  the  Constitution—and  proclaim
that we are ignorant of the first principles of Legislation.”
Ibid.  In fact, “[a]ll the delegates who spoke explicitly or im-
plicitly regarded an ex post facto law as a violation of natu-
ral law, and most of them therefore thought it unnecessary
to include such a basic natural law principle in the written
constitution.”  S. Sherry, The Founders’ Unwritten Consti-
tution, 54 U. Chi. L. Rev. 1127, 1157 (1987).  The Conven-
tion nonetheless adopted the Ex Post Facto Clauses after it
was urged that “the Judges can take hold of ” them if a leg-
islature ever enacts such a law.  2 Farrand 376 (William-
son).

II

The lodestar of this Court’s ex post facto jurisprudence is
Calder  v.  Bull,  which  established  that  the  Ex  Post  Facto
Clauses  apply  only  to  laws  that  impose  “punishment”  for
“crime[s].”  3 Dall., at 389–391.  Calder—and especially Jus-
tice Chase’s lead seriatim opinion—has since provided the
definitive  gloss  on  the  Ex  Post  Facto  Clauses.  Justice
Chase’s  definition  of  “ex post  facto  laws”  continues  to


4

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

“provid[e]  an  authoritative  account  of  the  scope  of  the  Ex
Post  Facto  Clause.”  Stogner  v.  California,  539  U. S.  607,
611 (2003); accord, e.g., Peugh, 569 U. S., at 532–533.  This
Court’s  modern  precedents,  including  today’s  opinion,  de-
cide whether a law is subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses
based on whether it satisfies Calder’s requirement that it
be “criminal or penal.”  Weaver v. Graham, 450 U. S. 24, 29
(1981); see also ante, at 2.  But this Court’s implementation
of Calder seems to have lost sight of how Calder would have
been understood when it was decided.

Calder  concerned  a  state  legislature’s  intervention  in  a
traditional private-law dispute.  The case arose out of the
probate  proceedings  for  the  estate  of  a  Connecticut  man
named  Normand  Morison.  In  1779,  Morison  wrote  a  will
leaving his property to his wife Abigail and her heirs.  See
8  The  Documentary  History  of  the  Supreme  Court  of  the
United States, 1789–1800, p. 89 (M. Marcus ed. 2007).  Soon
after Morison wrote his will, he and Abigail had a son.  Ibid.
When  the  son  was  young,  Morison  died.  Ibid.  Abigail
started the probate process so that she could inherit Mori-
son’s property as his will promised.  Ibid.  But the probate
judge  held  up  the  process  because  he  wanted  to  check
whether  the  birth  of  their  son  affected  the  will’s  validity.
Ibid.  At the time, Abigail did not mind the delay because
the default intestacy rules would have given the property
to her and her son anyway.  Id., at 89–90.

But later events jeopardized Abigail’s right to inherit Mo-
rison’s property.  First, Connecticut changed the default in-
testacy rules so that, absent a valid will, property like Mo-
rison’s  would  pass  to  his  nearest  blood  relative,  not  to  a
surviving spouse like Abigail.  Id., at 90, and n. 9.  Second,
the probate court, without telling Abigail, disapproved Mo-
rison’s original will.  Id., at 90.  And third, a few years later,
Abigail and Morison’s son died.  Ibid.  After her son died,
Abigail and her new husband Caleb Bull returned to pro-
bate court.  Ibid.  The Bulls were surprised to learn that the


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

THOMAS, J., concurring

probate court had disapproved Morison’s will years earlier
without telling Abigail—apparently on the theory that he
would  have  wanted  to  change  it  after  his  son  was  born.
Ibid.  And, since Connecticut had enacted new default in-
testacy rules in the meantime, the absence of a valid will
meant that Morison’s estate would pass on to his blood rel-
atives rather than to Abigail.  Ibid.  Morison’s blood rela-
tives,  the  Calders,  were  suddenly  the  lawful  heirs  of  his
property.  Id., at 90–91.

Abigail and Caleb Bull petitioned the Connecticut Legis-
lature for relief.  They convinced the legislature that Mori-
son did not intend to revoke his will after his son died, so
the legislature issued a decree in 1795 granting them a re-
hearing on the validity of Morison’s original will.  Id., at 91.
The legislature’s 1795 decree effectively vacated the origi-
nal  probate-court  decision  deeming  the  will  void  and
granted a new hearing at which the probate court could ad-
judicate  the  will’s  validity.  Id.,  at  91,  107.  The  probate
court held a new hearing pursuant to the decree and con-
cluded that Morison’s original will was valid after all.  Id.,
at  91.  Having  now  lost  in  probate  court,  the  Calders  ap-
pealed  this  new  decision  and  challenged  the  legislature’s
decree  that  had  granted  the  Bulls  a  new  hearing.    Id.,  at
91–92.  The Calders argued, eventually to this Court, that
the  legislature’s  decree  was  an  unconstitutional  ex  post
facto law because it retroactively voided the probate court’s
original decision, which caused them to lose an inheritance
that would otherwise have been theirs.  Id., at 92.

In  Calder  v. Bull, this  Court  gave  two reasons why the
legislature’s decree granting a new trial did not violate the
State Ex Post Facto Clause.  See Art. I, §10, cl. 1.  The first
reason was that the legislature’s decree operated on a legal
decision by a court, not a past action by the Calders.  There
was nothing that the parties had done in the past that was
“in any manner affected by the law or resolution of Connect-
icut.”  3  Dall.,  at  392  (opinion  of  Chase,  J.).    “It  does  not


6

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

concern, or relate to, any act done by them.”  Ibid.  Instead,
the decree effectively vacated a probate decision and gave
the court an opportunity to correct its decision, just like ap-
pellate courts do every day.  Ibid.  The new hearing, after
all, was conducted under the same substantive laws as were
in force at the original hearing.  In fact, the Justices seemed
to believe that the Connecticut Legislature’s “resolution or
law,” id., at 387, was not a legislative but a judicial act, con-
sistent with state legislatures’ traditional judicial power to
review state-court decisions—and thus could  not be an  ex
post facto “law” at all.  See id., at 395–396 (opinion of Pat-
erson, J.) (“[W]e may, in the present instance, consider the
Legislature of the State, as having acted in their customary
judicial capacity”); id., at 398 (opinion of Iredell, J.) (“an ex-
ercise of judicial, not of legislative, authority”); id., at 400
(opinion of Cushing, J.) (“If the act is a judicial act, it is not
touched by the Federal Constitution”).

The more lasting legacy of Calder, however, was its sec-
ond reason.  Three of the four seriatim opinions in Calder
limited the Ex Post Facto Clauses to laws imposing criminal
punishment.  On  their  view,  the  Clauses  did  not  forbid
other kinds of retroactive laws.  Justice Chase, in what has
proved  to  be  the  most  influential  opinion,  gave  a  compre-
hensive account of the scope of the Ex Post Facto Clauses.
He understood the Clauses to be limited to retroactive laws
imposing  criminal  punishment.  He  explained  that  the
Ex Post Facto Clauses covered only those laws that “create”
a “crime,” “aggravate” a crime, “encrease the punishment”
for a crime, or “change the rules of evidence, for the purpose
of conviction.” Id., at 391.

Justice Chase’s account implied that the Clauses did not
apply to other kinds of retroactive laws.  First, on his view,
the Clauses did not touch private law.  Justice Chase did
“not think” that the Ex Post Facto Clause “was inserted to
Secure the citizen in his private rights, of either property, or
contracts.”  Id., at 390.  Accordingly, the Clauses would not


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

7

THOMAS, J., concurring

prohibit a law that retroactively paused a debtor’s obliga-
tions to a creditor or voided a contract.  Such laws, in Jus-
tice Chase’s view, were governed by separate constitutional
prohibitions on impairing the obligations of contracts and
making anything but gold or silver a tender in payments of
debts.  Ibid.;  see  Art.  I,  §10,  cl.  1.    Second,  because  the
Clauses were meant as protections against the government,
they  did  not  apply  to  laws  that  retroactively  made  a  law
more  lenient.  They  would  not,  for  example,  forbid  a  law
that retroactively “mollifies the rigor of the criminal law.”
Calder, 3 Dall., at 391 (opinion of Chase, J.).

The other two seriatim opinions in Calder that addressed
the question agreed.  Justice Paterson explained that “the
meaning, annexed to the terms ex post facto laws, unques-
tionably  refers  to  crimes,  and  nothing  else.”    Id.,  at  396.
Justice Iredell—an adamant proponent of the Ex Post Facto
Clauses, see supra, at 2—likewise thought that they did not
“extend to civil cases, to cases that merely affect the private
property of citizens.”  Calder, 3 Dall., at 400.  Instead, the
Clauses  applied  only  to  laws  that  retroactively  “inflict  a
punishment” for an “offence.”  Ibid.

Some, myself included, have questioned whether Calder
was right to limit the Ex Post Facto Clauses to laws impos-
ing  criminal  punishment.  See,  e.g.,  Satterlee  v.  Matthew-
son, 2 Pet. 380, 416, and n. (a) (1829) (opinion of Johnson,
J.) (arguing that the Ex Post Facto Clauses protect more);
O. Field, Ex Post Facto in the Constitution, 20 Mich. L. Rev.
315, 331 (1922) (“[T]here have been reputable authorities,
both past and present, who incline to the view that the ex
post facto provisions of the Constitution prohibited civil as
well as criminal legislation”); Eastern Enterprises v. Apfel,
524  U. S.  498,  538–539  (1998)  (THOMAS,  J.,  concurring).
Others  have  defended  Calder’s  limitation.  See,  e.g.,  R.
Natelson, Statutory Retroactivity: The Founders’ View, 39
Idaho L. Rev. 489, 493–494 (2003); C. Nelson, Originalism
and Interpretive Conventions, 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 519, 578–


8

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

582 (2003).  But often lost in that debate has been the ques-
tion of what Calder meant when it limited the Clauses to
laws imposing criminal punishment.

III
This Court’s recent precedents have attempted to imple-
ment Calder’s limitation of the Clauses to criminal punish-
ment.  But, in doing so, they have adopted a framework that
turns largely on legislative labeling, has little basis in his-
tory, and is unnecessarily convoluted.

A

The modern precedents follow Calder’s limitation of the
Ex Post Facto Clauses to laws that impose criminal punish-
ment.  Based  on  “Justice  Chase’s  now  familiar  opinion  in
Calder,”  this  Court  has  repeatedly  held  that  the  Clauses
apply exclusively to laws that “retroactively alter the defi-
nition  of  crimes  or  increase  the  punishment  for  criminal
acts,” but not to other kinds of retroactive laws.  Collins v.
Youngblood, 497 U. S. 37, 41–43 (1990); see also, e.g., Kan-
sas v. Hendricks, 521 U. S. 346, 370 (1997); Smith v. Doe,
538 U. S. 84, 92 (2003).

But in defining criminal punishment—and thus the scope
of Calder’s limitation—the Court’s modern framework ap-
plies  two  multifactor  tests  developed  in  the  20th  century.
The first multifactor test asks whether the legislature “in-
tended” the law to be viewed as criminal or penal.  Smith,
538 U. S., at 92–93; see also ante, at 2, n. 1.  Under this test,
a law is subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses “[i]f the inten-
tion of the legislature was to impose punishment.”  Smith,
538 U. S., at 92.  But if “the intention was to enact a regu-
latory scheme that is civil and nonpunitive,” then a law is
presumptively  not  subject  to  the  Ex  Post  Facto  Clauses.
Ibid.  This test has included up to five factors, most of which
allow a legislature to avoid the Clauses through labeling or
semantics.  Those five factors are whether the legislature


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

9

THOMAS, J., concurring

had a “ ‘preference’ ” for “ ‘one label or the other,’ ” id., at 93
(quoting Hudson v. United States, 522 U. S. 93, 99 (1997));
whether the “codification” was in the criminal or civil code,
Smith, 538 U. S., at 94; whether legislative history or simi-
lar indicators suggested nonpunitive goals, United States v.
One Assortment of 89 Firearms, 465 U. S. 354, 364 (1984);
whether  the  legislature  provided  traditional  “safeguards
associated with the criminal process,” Smith, 538 U. S., at
96; and whether the legislature gave enforcement power to
an agency with power to enforce civil laws, ibid.

The second multifactor test, which applies only if the law
survives the first test, asks whether the law’s other features
render it criminal or penal.  See id., at 92.  Under this sec-
ond test, a law is subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses if it
is “so punitive either in purpose or effect as to negate [the
legislature’s] intention to deem it civil.”  Ibid. (internal quo-
tation  marks  omitted).  The  Court  has  at  times  said  that
this second test is a function of up to seven factors: whether
the law involves an affirmative disability or restraint, im-
poses what has historically been regarded as a punishment,
requires a finding of scienter, promotes the traditional aims
of punishment, applies to behavior which is already a crime,
lacks a rational alternative purpose, or is excessive in rela-
tion  to  that  purpose.  Kennedy  v.  Mendoza-Martinez,  372
U. S. 144, 168–169 (1963); see Smith, 538 U. S., at 97 (ex-
plaining  that  Mendoza-Martinez  factors  “migrated”  to  ex
post facto jurisprudence).  So long as a law survives the first
test,  “ ‘only  the  clearest  proof ’ ”  under  the  second  test  can
make it subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses.  Smith, 538
U. S., at 92 (quoting Hudson, 522 U. S., at 100).

B
This modern framework is incongruous with the histori-
cal purpose of Ex Post Facto Clauses.  The modern frame-
work, because of how much it turns on legislative labeling
and semantics, allows a legislature to manipulate when the


10

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

protection will apply.  Under the first test, for example, a
legislature  might  be  able  to  impose  a  retroactive  $10,000
fine on some previously innocent conduct—such as drinking
coffee  or  going  to  the  gym—if  it  labeled  the  law  “civil,”
placed it in the civil code, expressed a nonpunitive purpose,
omitted protections for the accused, and let non-traditional
prosecutors (such as a health agency) enforce it.  See supra,
at 2–3.  Under the second test, the legislature might be able
to prevail by aggravating the fair-notice problems that mo-
tivate the Clauses, such as by having its retroactive law im-
pose strict liability and then applying it only to previously
innocent  conduct.  See  Mendoza-Martinez,  372  U. S.,  at
168–169.  It is unlikely that a constitutional prohibition de-
signed to curb a “cruel and unjust” legislature, 1 Blackstone
46, can be  so easily manipulated by the same legislature.
See  United  States  v.  Rahimi,  602  U. S.  680,  776  (2024)
(THOMAS, J., dissenting) (explaining that the Constitution
does not “allow . . . majoritarian interests to determine” the
scope of “constitutional rights”).

The modern framework is also convoluted.  It is difficult
for  courts,  let  alone  ordinary  citizens,  to  predict  how  this
Court will weigh the modern framework’s combined twelve
factors spread over two tests.  This Court’s own precedents
admit  that  the  twelve  factors  are  “neither  exhaustive  nor
dispositive,”  United  States  v.  Ward,  448  U. S.  242,  249
(1980),  and  need  not  be  given  equal  weights,  Smith,  538
U. S.,  at  105.  Such  “multifactor  balancing  test[s]”  invite
“policy-driven,  ‘arbitrary  discretion.’ ”    Gamble  v.  United
States, 587 U. S. 678, 724 (2019) (THOMAS, J., concurring).
We should strive to avoid such unclear rules in any context,
but especially when interpreting a constitutional guarantee
of clear notice.

IV
When Calder said that the Ex Post Facto Clauses apply
only  to  laws  imposing  punishment  for  crimes,  it  was


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

11

THOMAS, J., concurring

referring to an established category of laws.  A crime meant
a “public wrong,” which is an injury to the sovereign in its
sovereign capacity.  Calder therefore encompassed offenses
against the sovereign regardless of whether they were nom-
inally criminal or civil.  And punishment simply referred to
the law’s coercive sanction—meaning a traditional depriva-
tion  of  life,  liberty,  or  property—redressing  that  public
wrong.  Applying  this  understanding  would  restore  the
Clauses to their proper role without the problems attendant
to the more recent precedents.

A
The English common law divided  all unlawful acts into
“private wrongs” and “public wrongs.”  See 3 Blackstone 2.
Blackstone titled the third and fourth volumes of his Com-
mentaries, respectively, “Of Private Wrongs” and “Of Public
Wrongs.”  This dichotomy was fundamental to English and
American law.

Public  wrongs  were  injuries  to  the  sovereign.    A  public
wrong was “a breach and violation of public rights and du-
ties,  which  affect  the  whole  community,  considered  as  a
community.”  Ibid.  Because a public wrong injured the com-
munity, it was deemed an injury to the sovereign in his sov-
ereign capacity.  4 Blackstone 2–7.  It followed that an ac-
tion to redress a public wrong was brought on behalf of the
sovereign, not the victim.  J. Locke, Second Treatise of Civil
Government  7  (J.  Gough  ed.  1948)  (Locke).  In  concrete
terms, actions for public wrongs were brought in England
on behalf of the King, and here on behalf of the State or the
United States—typically by public prosecutors, rather than
privately by the victims.  The sovereign “is supposed by the
law to be the person injured by every infraction of the public
rights belonging to that community, and is therefore in all
cases  the  proper  prosecutor  for  every  public  offense.”    4
Blackstone  2;  see  also  Robertson  v.  United  States  ex  rel.
Watson,  560  U. S.  272,  279  (2010)  (ROBERTS,  C. J.,


12

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

dissenting) (a criminal prosecution is an action “on behalf
of the sovereign, seeking to vindicate a public wrong”).  Pub-
lic wrongs included all wrongs deemed injuries to the sov-
ereign  and  redressable  by  the  sovereign,  from  murder  to
mayhem to public nuisance.  4 Blackstone 5–6.

Private wrongs, in contrast, were injuries to individuals
in  their  private  capacity.    An  action  inflicted  a  private
wrong insofar as it infringed “the private or civil rights be-
longing to individuals, considered as individuals.”  3 Black-
stone 2.  For example, a dispute with a fellow citizen over a
land  claim  or  a  failure  to  pay  a  debt  concerned  a  private
wrong.  “[I]f I detain a field from another man, to which the
law has given him a right, this is a civil injury, and not a
crime,” Blackstone explained, because “only the right of an
individual is concerned, and it is immaterial to the public,
which of us is in possession of the land.”  4 Blackstone 5.
Private wrongs were redressable by the individuals whose
rights were violated, not the sovereign.

A single act could be both a private wrong and a public
wrong.  Id., at 5–6.  “The same acts will generally constitute
a private injury, as well as a public crime.  A public punish-
ment is inflicted on the part of the state, to restrain such
conduct, and the party injured is entitled to a compensation
for the injury he has sustained.”  2 Z. Swift, System of the
Laws  of  the  State  of  Connecticut  292  (1796);  accord  ibid.
(“If one man assaults and beats another, he is punished by
a fine for disturbing the peace, and compelled to compen-
sate  in  money  the  person  he  has  abused  and  wounded.”).
The  private  suit  brought  by  the  individual  vindicated  the
private  wrong,  and  the  public  prosecution  brought  by  the
sovereign vindicated the public wrong.  This overlap carries
forward to  modern law: Theft can be redressed through  a
tort suit brought by the victim and a criminal prosecution
brought by the state.

When  the  opinions  in  Calder  spoke  of  “crimes,”  they
meant public wrongs.  The prevailing definition of a “crime”


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

13

THOMAS, J., concurring

around the time of Calder was “a violation of law to the in-
jury of the public, a public offense.”  N. Webster, A Compen-
dious Dictionary of the English Language 72 (1806) (Web-
ster).  Blackstone  used  the  terms  “crimes”  and  “public
wrongs” interchangeably.  See 4 Blackstone 1–5.  His fourth
volume covered “public wrongs, or crimes and misdemean-
ors.”  Id., at 1.1  The “common-law conception of crime,” this
Court has long recognized, was an “offense against the sov-
ereignty of the government.”  Heath v. Alabama, 474 U. S.
82, 88 (1985).  So Calder’s limitation of the Ex Post Facto
Clauses to crimes would have originally been understood to
include all public wrongs.

Calder itself confirms this understanding.  Justice Chase
distinguished crimes not with nominally civil laws enforced
by the sovereign, but with laws that merely “secure[d] pri-
vate  rights,”  like  contract  laws.  3  Dall.,  at  390.  Justices
Chase  and  Iredell  used  “crime”  interchangeably  with  “of-
fence.”  Ibid.;  id.,  at  400  (opinion  of  Iredell,  J.).    Justices
Chase  and  Paterson  said  that  their  definitions  tracked
Blackstone’s.  See id., at 391 (opinion of Chase, J.) (“Sir Wil-
liam Blackstone, in his commentaries, considers an ex post
facto law precisely in the same light I have done.”); id., at
396  (opinion  of  Paterson,  J.)  (similar).    Justice  Iredell  ex-
plained  in  a  contemporaneous  opinion  that  the  Ex  Post
Facto Clauses could be limited to crimes because “there . . .
is  little  reason  to  apprehend  a  legislative  interference  for
the sake of unjustly transferring property from one man to
another.”  Minge v. Gilmour, 17 F. Cas. 440, 443, No. 9,631
(CC NC 1798).  And, of course, the occasion for Calder’s dis-
tinction  was  a  probate  dispute,  where  only  private  rights
are implicated.2

——————

1 Crimes and misdemeanors were for these purposes “syn-

onymous.”  4 Blackstone 5.

2 Professor Caleb Nelson has read Calder along the same
lines: “By ‘criminal’ laws,” he has explained, “Justice Iredell


14

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

In turn, when Calder referred to criminal “punishment,”
it simply meant whatever coercive sanction—or deprivation
of life, liberty, or property—the law imposed as redress for
committing  those  crimes.  Blackstone  understood  punish-
ment to include the traditional “coercive penalties” that the
law  imposed  as  redress  for  a  public  wrong.    See  4  Black-
stone  7–8.    Dictionaries  defined  “punishment”  broadly  as
“[a]ny infliction or pain imposed in vengeance of a crime,”
S. Johnson, A Dictionary of the English Language (6th ed.
1785), or “any thing inflicted for a crime,” Webster 241.  The
power of punishing an offender was the power to harm the
offender in a way that was otherwise forbidden: “[N]o one
ought to harm another in his life, health, liberty, or posses-
sions”—“unless it be to do justice on an offender.”  Locke 5
(emphasis added); see also id., at 6 (describing when “one
man may lawfully do harm to another, which is that we call
punishment”).

The Ex Post Facto Clauses therefore prohibit retroactive
laws that impose coercive penalties for public wrongs.  Con-
trary to the modern framework, it does not matter what the
legislature  labels  the  law,  where  it  places  the  law,  which
agency  it  vests  enforcement  with,  what  its  stated  goals
were,  whether  it  provides  safeguards  for  the  accused,
whether  it  requires  a showing  of  scienter,  or  whether  the
conduct  to  which  it  applies  is  already  a  crime.    Contra,
Smith,  538  U. S.,  at  96;  Martinez-Mendoza,  372  U. S.,  at
168–169.  What matters is what the law does.  If it punishes
a public wrong—or an injury to the sovereign in its sover-
eign  capacity—then  it  is  subject  to  the  Ex  Post  Facto

——————
and  his  colleagues  may  simply  have  meant  laws  that  de-
fined offenses and imposed punishments for them,” even if
“the  penalties  that  they  prescribed  could  be  collected
through civil suits.”  C. Nelson, Originalism and Interpre-
tive Conventions, 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 519, 582, n. 255 (2003).


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

15

THOMAS, J., concurring

Clauses.  If it changes merely private relations, such as the
rules of contract or property or probate, then it is not.

Whether a law is subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses will
therefore typically depend on how it is enforced.  If it is en-
forced on behalf of the sovereign to redress a sovereign in-
jury, then it is subject to the Clauses.  See 4 Blackstone 2.
If instead it is enforced by a private person to vindicate his
own private rights, then it is not.  In this case, for example,
the law was subject to the Ex Post Facto Clauses because it
was enforced against Ellingburg by the United States, not
by the First Union National Bank, whose private rights El-
lingburg  violated  when  he  robbed  it.    And  the  United
States’s  action  was  redressing  a  sovereign  injury  to  the
community as a whole, not a private wrong.  Cf. 3 Black-
stone 257 (explaining that the King can bring “common law
actions”  to  redress  private  wrongs  to  himself,  such  as  an
“action for trespass for taking away his goods”).3
  Calder’s understanding secures Ex Post Facto Clause pro-
tection in a wide range of contexts involving nominally civil
laws.  Those contexts include civil proceedings seeking fines
for  public  offenses.  See,  e.g.,  Army  Corps  of  Engineers  v.
Hawkes Co., 578 U. S. 590, 600 (2016) (describing “civil pen-
alties of up to $37,500 for each day [the challenger] violated
the  Act”).  They  include  enforcement  proceedings  brought
by  administrative  agencies.    See  Axon  Enterprise,  Inc.  v.
FTC,  598  U. S.  175,  196  (2023)  (THOMAS,  J.,  concurring)
(describing the 20th-century rise of such proceedings).  And
they include municipal sanctions like speeding tickets.  “If

——————

3 Sovereigns  sometimes  delegated  enforcement  of  public
wrongs to private persons.  But, unlike in actions redress-
ing  private  wrongs,  the  private  persons  in  those  circum-
stances acted “on behalf of the sovereign” and were subject
to the sovereign’s control.  Robertson v. United States ex rel.
Watson, 560 U. S. 272, 279 (2010) (ROBERTS, C. J., dissent-
ing); see ibid. (collecting authorities).


16

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

one were to commit a minor traffic offense at a time the of-
fense was to be punished by a $25 fine, and the government
were  to  then  amend  the  statute  and  impose  a  fine  of
$1,000,000 dollars, it would be nonsensical to treat that fine
as non-punitive simply because the offense was processed
civilly.”  Brief for Professor Beth Colgan as Amicus Curiae
8, n. 3.  Because all of these offenses impose punishments
for public wrongs, Calder would treat them all as subject to
the Ex Post Facto Clauses.

B
This understanding of Calder long prevailed.  Courts took
the position that “the relevant line for the Clause’s scope”
lay between “punishments imposed in response to public of-
fenses whether prosecuted criminally or civilly on the one
hand, and purely private disputes on the other.”  Brief for
Professor Beth Colgan as Amicus Curiae 5.  This Court con-
firmed, contrary to the modern precedents, that “the ex post
facto effect of a law cannot be evaded by giving a civil form
to that which is essentially criminal.”  Burgess v. Salmon,
97  U. S.  381,  385  (1878).    The  influential  commentator
Thomas  Cooley  likewise  explained  that  a  “law  will  be  ex
post facto in the constitutional sense” if it “subject[s] an in-
dividual to a pecuniary penalty” or “deprives a party of any
valuable  right”  retroactively,  even  if  “it  does not  in  terms
declare the acts to which the penalty is attached criminal.”
Constitutional Limitations 321 (6th ed. 1890).

In a similar context, when a State sought nominally civil
fines against a company for doing business without proper
forms,  this  Court  explained  that  the  statute  “was  in  the
strictest sense a penal statute.”  Wisconsin v. Pelican Ins.
Co.,  127  U. S.  265,  299  (1888).  The  Court  held  that  the
nominally civil statute was penal because “[t]he cause of ac-
tion was not any private injury, but solely the offence com-
mitted against the State by violating her law.”  Ibid.  Like-
wise, “[t]he prosecution was in the name of the State.”  Ibid.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

17

THOMAS, J., concurring

The  Court  explained  that  “[t]he  real  nature of  the  case is
not affected by the forms provided by the law of the State”;
these  forms  were  “immaterial”  to  whether  the  law  was
criminal or penal in a constitutional sense.  Ibid.  Thus, the
Court concluded, “[i]n whatever form the State pursues her
right to punish the offence against her sovereignty,” an ac-
tion is criminal or penal in substance whenever it seeks to
“compe[l ]  the  offender  to  pay  a  pecuniary  fine  by  way  of
punishment for the offence.”  Ibid.

Other decisions followed the same reasoning.  For exam-
ple, when the United States brought a nominally civil ac-
tion for damages based on a public offense, the defendants
were  entitled  to  other  criminal-procedure  protections  be-
cause the action “was in its nature and essence, though not
its  form,  a  penal  or  criminal  action.”  United  States  v.
Poyllon,  27  F. Cas.  608,  611,  No.  16,081  (NY  1812).    And
when a statute forbade “any fine or forfeiture under any pe-
nal statute,” the statute applied to a nominally civil action
for  debt  on  behalf  of  the  sovereign  against  someone  who
committed a public offense.  Adams v. Woods, 2 Cranch 336,
337,  340–341  (1805)  (emphases  deleted).    Chief  Justice
Marshall explained that the category of penal laws referred
“not to any particular mode of proceeding, but generally to
any prosecution, trial, or punishment for the offence.”  Ibid.
This  understanding  of  Calder  harmonizes  the  Ex  Post
Facto Clauses with their historical purpose.  It means that
the Clauses ensure fair notice against government enforce-
ment  actions,  regardless  of  whether  the  legislature  labels
them  civil.  As  JUSTICE  GORSUCH  has  explained,  today’s
“civil”  laws  “regularly  impose  penalties  far  more  severe
than  those  found  in  many  criminal  statutes.”    Sessions  v.
Dimaya,  584  U.  S.  148,  184  (2018)  (opinion  concurring  in
part and concurring in the judgment).  “Today’s ‘civil’ pen-
alties include confiscatory rather than compensatory fines,
forfeiture provisions that allow homes to be taken, remedies
that  strip  persons  of  their  professional  licenses  and


18

ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES

THOMAS, J., concurring

livelihoods, and the power to commit persons against their
will indefinitely.’ ”  Ibid.  This understanding also helps rec-
oncile Calder with its critics, many of whom have focused
on the injustice of allowing the government to retroactively
impose sanctions for public offenses that it deems civil.  See,
e.g., Brief for Professor Wayne A. Logan as Amicus Curiae
31–32; cf. D. Troy, Retroactive Legislation 49–55 (1998).

This understanding of Calder also simplifies the law.  Ra-
ther than making the Ex Post Facto Clauses’ application de-
pend on twelve factors with indeterminate weights, this un-
derstanding makes it depend on a simple legal inquiry with
a long pedigree in our legal tradition—whether the law im-
poses a coercive penalty to redress a public wrong.  See, e.g.,
Pelican Ins. Co., 127 U. S., at 299; Robertson, 560 U. S., at
278–279 (ROBERTS, C. J., dissenting).  In most cases, that
inquiry  will  just  come  down  to  who  enforces  the  law,  the
sovereign or the injured private party.

*

*

*

In Collins v. Youngblood, this Court explained that any
“departure from Calder’s explanation of the original under-
standing of the Ex Post Facto Clause[s] was . . . unjustified.”
497 U. S., at 49.  The Court understood itself to be bound by
what  Calder  meant  rather  than  by  its  intervening  prece-
dents that misunderstood Calder.  497 U. S., at 49–50.  To-
day,  this  Court’s  precedents  concerning  the  scope  of  laws
imposing criminal punishment have departed from Calder’s
understanding of that category.  In a future case, the Court
should consider returning to Calder’s understanding.&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776751/ellingburg-v-united-states/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc. v. Burton</title>
      <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776752/coney-island-auto-parts-unlimited-inc-v-burton/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776752/coney-island-auto-parts-unlimited-inc-v-burton/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/pdf/2026/01/20/coney_island_auto_parts_unlimited_inc._v._burton.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;(Slip Opinion)

OCTOBER  TERM,  2025

1

Syllabus

NOTE:  Where  it  is  feasible,  a  syllabus  (headnote)  will  be  released,  as  is
being  done  in  connection  with  this  case,  at  the  time  the  opinion  is  issued.
The  syllabus  constitutes  no  part  of  the  opinion  of  the  Court  but  has  been
prepared  by  the  Reporter  of  Decisions  for  the  convenience  of  the  reader.
See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

Syllabus

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v.
BURTON, CHAPTER 7 TRUSTEE FOR VISTA-PRO
AUTOMOTIVE, LLC

CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR
THE SIXTH CIRCUIT

No. 24–808.  Argued November 4, 2025—Decided January 20, 2026

The  question  in  this  case  is  whether  Federal  Rule  of  Civil  Procedure
60(c)(1)’s requirement that parties make Rule 60(b) motions within a
“reasonable time” applies to a motion seeking relief from an allegedly
void  judgment  under  Rule  60(b)(4).    Vista-Pro  Automotive,  LLC,  en-
tered  bankruptcy  in  2014  and  initiated  adversarial  proceedings
against Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc., to collect $50,000 in
allegedly unpaid invoices.  Vista-Pro attempted to serve process on Co-
ney Island by mail but purportedly failed to comply with Federal Rule
of Bankruptcy Procedure 7004(b)(3)’s mail-service requirements.  Co-
ney Island did not file an answer, and the Bankruptcy Court entered
a default judgment.  Over the next six years, Vista-Pro’s bankruptcy
trustee attempted to enforce the judgment.  These efforts bore fruit in
2021 when a marshal seized funds from Coney Island’s bank account
in satisfaction of the judgment.  Coney Island filed a motion to vacate
the judgment under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60, arguing that
Vista-Pro’s failure to make proper service rendered the judgment void.
The Bankruptcy Court denied relief, holding that Coney Island failed
to abide by Rule 60’s requirement that parties make motions for relief
within a “reasonable time.”  The District Court and the Court of Ap-
peals for the Sixth Circuit affirmed.

Held: Rule 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit applies to a motion alleging

that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).  Pp. 2–6.

(a) The plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) provides that a “motion under Rule
60(b) must be made within a reasonable time,” and because a motion


2

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v.
BURTON
Syllabus

for  relief  from  an  allegedly  void  judgment  is  a  “motion  under  Rule
60(b),” the reasonable-time limit applies.  The structure of Rule 60 con-
firms the plain-text interpretation.  Rule 60 expressly modifies the de-
fault  reasonable-time  limit,  imposing  a  one-year  limit  on  Rule  60(b)
motions alleging mistakes, new evidence, or fraud.  Yet the Rule does
not include an analogous unlimited-time principle for motions alleging
voidness.  Pp. 2–3.

(b) The Court rejects the argument that because a “void judgment is
a legal nullity,” United Student Aid Funds, Inc. v. Espinosa, 559 U. S.
260, 270, no time limit should apply.  Even if the passage of time can-
not cure voidness, the same principle holds true for most legal errors,
yet statutes and rules routinely limit the time during which a party
can seek relief from a judgment infected by error.  A party would need
to show that some principle of law, such as the Due Process Clause,
gives a party the right to allege voidness at any time, but Coney Island
disclaims any such argument, and the Court cannot divine any such
principle.  Allowing parties to allege voidness at any time would have
extreme implications, such as allowing parties to ignore deadlines for
filing notices of appeal or petitions for certiorari when subject-matter
jurisdiction is contested.  The possibility that improper service is dif-
ferent from other legal errors because a party might not learn about
proceedings until long after judgment issues does not help Coney Is-
land.  Rule 60(c)(1) accommodates such a scenario by imposing a rea-
sonable-time requirement rather than a fixed time limit.  In the con-
text of a default judgment, it might be reasonable for a defendant not
to  seek  relief  before  learning  about  a  plaintiff’s  attempted  enforce-
ment.  Pp. 3–5.

(c) The Court rejects Coney Island’s argument that courts have his-
torically  allowed  litigants  to  seek  relief  from  void  judgments  at  any
time.  No such historical consensus exists, and in any event, for Rule
60(b) motions, the Rule’s text and structure take priority over histori-
cal practice.  The Court also rejects Coney Island’s reliance on Insur-
ance Corp. of Ireland v. Compagnie des Bauxites de Guinee, 456 U. S.
694, as that case undermines Coney Island’s plea for no time limits.
Lastly, the Court rejects Coney Island’s invocation of policy concerns,
Rule 60’s drafting history, and the canon of constitutional avoidance.
To the extent that these interpretive tools carry any weight, they do so
only when a Rule’s language is ambiguous.  Pp. 5–6.

109 F. 4th 438, affirmed.

ALITO, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which ROBERTS, C. J.,
and THOMAS, KAGAN, GORSUCH, KAVANAUGH, BARRETT, and JACKSON, JJ.,
joined.  SOTOMAYOR, J., filed an opinion concurring in the judgment.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

Opinion of the Court

NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the
United  States  Reports.  Readers  are  requested  to  notify  the  Reporter  of
Decisions,  Supreme  Court  of  the  United  States,  Washington,  D.  C.  20543,
pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–808
_________________

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC.,
PETITIONER v. JEANNE ANN BURTON,
CHAPTER 7 TRUSTEE FOR VISTA-PRO
AUTOMOTIVE, LLC

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE SIXTH CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE ALITO delivered the opinion of the Court.
A  party  seeking  relief  from  an  allegedly  void  judgment
may  file  a  motion  under  Federal  Rule  of  Civil  Procedure
60(b)(4).  Rule 60(c)(1) requires parties to make Rule 60(b)
motions within a “reasonable time.”  We hold that this time
limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void.

I
Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, entered bankruptcy in 2014.
As part of its bankruptcy litigation, Vista-Pro initiated ad-
versarial proceedings against Coney Island Auto Parts Un-
limited, Inc., to collect $50,000 in allegedly unpaid invoices.
Vista-Pro  attempted  to  serve  process  on  Coney  Island  by
mail, but in doing so, it purportedly failed to comply with
the  mail-service  requirements  in  Federal  Rule  of  Bank-
ruptcy Procedure 7004(b)(3).

Coney  Island  did  not  file  an  answer  in  the  adversarial
proceedings,  and  the  Bankruptcy  Court  entered  a  default
judgment against the company in 2015.  Over the next six
years, Vista-Pro’s bankruptcy trustee attempted to enforce


2

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v.
BURTON
Opinion of the Court

that judgment against Coney Island.  As part of these ef-
forts,  the  trustee  sent  a  demand  letter  to  the  company’s
CEO in April 2016.  Lower courts concluded that this letter
gave Coney Island notice of the judgment and the trustee’s
enforcement efforts.

These  efforts  bore  fruit  in  2021  when  a  marshal  seized
funds  from  Coney  Island’s  bank  account  in  satisfaction  of
the judgment.  In response, Coney Island filed a motion to
vacate the judgment under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure
60.  According to Coney Island, Vista-Pro’s failure to make
proper service rendered the judgment void.

The Bankruptcy Court denied relief.  It held that Coney
Island failed to abide by Rule 60’s requirement that parties
make  motions  for  relief  within  a  “reasonable  time.”    The
District  Court  and  Court  of  Appeals  for  the  Sixth  Circuit
affirmed.  We granted certiorari to resolve a split of author-
ity  on  whether  Rule  60’s  reasonable-time  limit  applies  to
motions seeking relief from allegedly void judgments.1  605
U. S. ___ (2025).

II
Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60 permits a court to “re-
lieve a party . . . from a final judgment, order, or proceed-
ing,” and subdivision (b)(4) specifically authorizes a court to

——————

1 Compare In re Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, 109 F. 4th 438, 444 (CA6
2024)  (case  below),  with  Austin  v.  Smith,  312  F. 2d  337,  343  (CADC
1962);  V.  T.  A.,  Inc.  v.  Airco,  Inc.,  597  F. 2d  220,  224,  and  n. 9  (CA10
1979);  Rodd  v.  Region  Constr.  Co.,  783  F. 2d  89,  91  (CA7  1986);  Hertz
Corp. v. Alamo Rent-A-Car, Inc., 16 F. 3d 1126, 1130 (CA11 1994); Sea-
Land  Serv.,  Inc.  v.  Ceramica  Europa  II,  Inc.,  160  F. 3d  849,  852  (CA1
1998); United States v. One Toshiba Color Television, 213 F. 3d 147, 157–
158 (CA3 2000) (en banc); Jackson v. FIE Corp., 302 F. 3d 515, 523 (CA5
2002).


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

Opinion of the Court

grant relief from a “void” judgment.2  Parties may seek re-
lief under Rule 60 by filing a motion with the court.

Rule 60 also imposes a time limit for such motions.  Rule
60(c)(1) provides that a “motion under Rule 60(b) must be
made within a reasonable time.”  Because a motion for relief
from  an  allegedly  void  judgment  is  a  “motion  under  Rule
60(b),” the reasonable-time limit applies.  Accord, Kemp v.
United  States,  596  U. S.  528,  533  (2022)  (“All  [Rule  60(b)
motions] must be filed ‘within a reasonable time’ ”).

The structure of Rule 60 confirms what the plain text of
subdivision (c)(1) provides.  When Rule 60 modifies the de-
fault reasonable-time limit, it does so expressly.  For exam-
ple, Rule 60(c)(1) imposes a 1-year limit on Rule 60(b) mo-
tions alleging mistakes, new evidence, or fraud.  Thus, one
would expect Rule 60 to include an analogous provision if a
special, unlimited-time principle applied to motions alleg-
ing voidness.  Cf. Kemp, 596 U. S., at 534–535.  But the Rule
does not.

Coney  Island,  several  Courts  of  Appeals,  and  a  promi-
nent  treatise  nonetheless  maintain  that  Rule  60(c)(1)’s
reasonable-time  limit  does  not  apply  to  motions  alleging
voidness.  See  n. 1,  supra;  11  C.  Wright,  A.  Miller,  &amp;  M.
Kane, Federal Practice and Procedure §2862, pp. 431–433
(3d ed. 2012).  These authorities acknowledge that their in-
terpretation clashes with Rule 60’s text.  See, e.g., Sea-Land
Serv., Inc. v. Ceramica Europa II, Inc., 160 F. 3d 849, 852
(CA1 1998).  But relying on the generally accepted maxim
that a “void judgment is a legal nullity,” United Student Aid
Funds, Inc. v. Espinosa, 559 U. S. 260, 270 (2010), they ar-
gue that the passage of time cannot turn such a nullity into
an  enforceable  judgment.  See,  e.g.,  Austin  v.  Smith,  312
F. 2d 337, 343 (CADC 1962).

——————

2 Rule  60  governs  motions  to  set  aside  default  judgments,  Fed.  Rule
Civ. Proc. 55(c), including those issued in bankruptcy proceedings, Fed.
Rules Bkrtcy. Proc. 7055 and 9024.


4

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v.
BURTON
Opinion of the Court

This argument cannot bear the weight that Coney Island
and others have placed on it.  Even if the passage of time
cannot cure voidness, the same principle holds true for most
legal  errors.  Nevertheless,  statutes  and  rules  routinely
limit the time during which a party can seek relief from a
judgment infected by error.  Therefore, a party in Coney Is-
land’s  position  would  need  to show  that  some principle  of
law, such as the Due Process Clause, gives a party the right
to allege voidness at any time.

Coney Island disclaims any such argument, and we can-
not divine any principle requiring courts to keep their doors
perpetually open to allegations of voidness.  Giving a party
a  “reasonable”  time  to  seek  relief  from  an  allegedly  void
judgment  may  well  be  all  that  due  process  demands.    By
contrast, the argument that a party may allege voidness at
any time, if taken to its logical conclusion, would have ex-
treme implications.  For example, if a federal district court
erroneously concluded that it possessed subject-matter ju-
risdiction and proceeded to enter a judgment, the adversely
affected party could wait as long as it wanted before filing
a  notice  of  appeal.    But  see  Fed.  Rule  App.  Proc.  4(a)(1).
Similarly, if a federal court of appeals erroneously asserted
subject-matter  jurisdiction,  the  adversely  affected  party
would not be required to comply with the deadline for filing
a  petition  for  a  writ  of  certiorari  imposed  by  this  Court’s
Rule 13.  It is hard to accept the proposition that due pro-
cess requires such a regime.3

——————

3 JUSTICE SOTOMAYOR contends that we should abstain from addressing
any potential due-process considerations.  Post, at 1 (opinion concurring in
judgment).    Although  Coney  Island  disclaims  any  constitutional  argu-
ment, it cites a longstanding consensus of authority holding that a party
may allege voidness at any time despite the contrary language in Rule
60.  And the only possible basis for such a holding is a rule of constitu-
tional law that prevents the imposition of the Rule’s reasonable-time re-
quirement.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

Opinion of the Court

Coney  Island  maintains  that  the  alleged  defect  in  this
case—failure  to  perform  proper  service—is  different  from
other legal errors that might render a judgment void.4  Co-
ney Island emphasizes that when a party does not receive
proper service, it might not learn about the proceedings un-
til long after the judgment issues.  But this possibility does
not  help  Coney  Island’s  position.   Rule  60(c)(1)  accommo-
dates  such  a  scenario  by  imposing  a  reasonable-time  re-
quirement, rather than a fixed time limit.  And in the con-
text  of  a  default  judgment,  it  might  be  reasonable  for  a
defendant not to seek relief before learning about a plain-
tiff ’s attempted enforcement.

Coney  Island  separately  contends  that  courts  have  his-
torically allowed litigants to seek relief from void judgments
at any time.  But the historical record is not so clear.  To be
sure, courts have granted relief from void judgments long
after their entry, especially when the issuing court lacked
jurisdiction over the defendant.  See, e.g., Harris v. Harde-
man, 14 How. 334, 338, 344–346 (1853) (affirming a lower
court order that set aside a judgment 11 years after its is-
suance where the plaintiff did not make proper service and
the defendant did not appear).  But there was no historical
consensus that a party could request such relief at any time.
Some  courts,  for  instance,  concluded  that  laches  or  other
time  limits  could  bar  relief,  even  when  a  litigant  alleged
voidness.  E.g., Stocking v. Hanson, 35 Minn. 207, 211–212,
28 N. W. 507, 507–508 (1886); Smith v. Jones, 174 Cal. 513,
515–517, 163 P. 890, 890–892 (1917).  In any event, for Rule
60(b) motions, the Rule’s “text and structure” take priority
over  historical  practice.5   See  Honeycutt  v.  United  States,
581 U. S. 443, 453 (2017).

——————

4 We express no view on whether the allegedly defective service in this

case would render the judgment void.

5 Rule 60(d) preserves parties’ ability to obtain relief from a judgment
in limited ways other than through a Rule 60(b) motion.  We express no


6

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v.
BURTON
Opinion of the Court

Coney Island turns next to this Court’s decision in Insur-
ance Corp. of Ireland v. Compagnie des Bauxites de Guinee,
456 U. S. 694 (1982).  There, we explained that a defendant
seeking  to  dispute  personal  jurisdiction  is  “always  free  to
ignore  the  judicial  proceedings,  risk  a  default  judgment,
and  then  challenge  that  judgment  . . .  in  a  collateral  pro-
ceeding.”  Id.,  at  706.    Citing  this  sentence,  Coney  Island
argues  that  defendants  need  not  comply  with  time  limits
when alleging a lack of personal jurisdiction.  But Insurance
Corp. also recognized that the “expression of legal rights is
often subject to certain procedural rules,” and “the failure
to enter a timely objection” may result in the loss of a legal
right.  Id., at 705.  Thus, Insurance Corp. undermines Co-
ney Island’s plea for no time limits.

Coney  Island  lastly  invokes  policy  concerns,  Rule  60’s
drafting history, and the canon of constitutional avoidance.
To the extent that these interpretive tools carry any weight,
they do so only when a Rule’s language is ambiguous.  See
BP p.l.c. v. Mayor and City Council of Baltimore, 593 U. S.
230,  245  (2021);  Milner  v.  Department  of  Navy,  562  U. S.
562, 572 (2011); Van Buren v. United States, 593 U. S. 374,
393–394  (2021).  Here,  the  operative  language  clearly  re-
quires parties to make Rule 60(b) motions within a reason-
able time.

III
Litigants seeking relief under Rule 60(b)(4) must comply
with  Rule  60(c)(1)  and  file  a  motion  within  a  reasonable
time.  Coney Island does not contend that it complied with
this  requirement.  Therefore,  we  need  not  expound  on
whether Coney Island’s timing was reasonable.  The judg-
ment  of  the  United  States  Court  of  Appeals  for  the  Sixth
Circuit is affirmed.

——————
view  regarding  the  limits  applicable  to  obtaining  relief  through  one  of
those methods.

It is so ordered.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

SOTOMAYOR, J., concurring in judgment

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–808
_________________

CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC.,
PETITIONER v. JEANNE ANN BURTON,
CHAPTER 7 TRUSTEE FOR VISTA-PRO
AUTOMOTIVE, LLC

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE SIXTH CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE SOTOMAYOR, concurring in the judgment.
The Court today rightly holds that a Rule 60(b)(4) motion
to set aside a default judgment that is void for lack of per-
sonal jurisdiction must be made “within a reasonable time.”
Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 60(c)(1).  Rule 60’s text and structure
require that conclusion, as the majority explains.

I concur in the judgment because the majority unneces-
sarily  opines  on  the  potential  validity  of  a  constitutional
challenge to the “reasonable time” limit under the Due Pro-
cess  Clause.  Ante,  at  4.    Coney  Island  did  not  make  this
argument below and the Sixth Circuit did not pass upon it.
See  In re  Vista-Pro  Automotive,  LLC,  109  F.  4th  438,  443
(2024)  (“Coney  Island does  not  mount  a  constitutional  at-
tack  on  Rule  60”).  In  this  Court,  Coney  Island  expressly
disclaimed any due process argument.  See Brief for Peti-
tioner 22 (“To be clear, Coney Island does not contend that
Rule 60 or Rule 60(c)(1) [is] unconstitutional”).  This Court
does  “not  generally  entertain  arguments  that  were  not
raised  below  and  are  not  advanced  in  this  Court  by  any
party.”  Burwell v. Hobby Lobby Stores, Inc., 573 U. S. 682,
721 (2014).  There is no reason to depart from that practice
absent unusual circumstances, which certainly are not pre-
sent here.&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776752/coney-island-auto-parts-unlimited-inc-v-burton/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berk v. Choy</title>
      <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776753/berk-v-choy/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776753/berk-v-choy/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/pdf/2026/01/20/berk_v._choy.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;(Slip Opinion)

OCTOBER  TERM,  2025

1

Syllabus

NOTE:  Where  it  is  feasible,  a  syllabus  (headnote)  will  be  released,  as  is
being  done  in  connection  with  this  case,  at  the  time  the  opinion  is  issued.
The  syllabus  constitutes  no  part  of  the  opinion  of  the  Court  but  has  been
prepared  by  the  Reporter  of  Decisions  for  the  convenience  of  the  reader.
See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

Syllabus

BERK v. CHOY ET AL.

CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR
THE THIRD CIRCUIT

No. 24–440.  Argued October 6, 2025—Decided January 20, 2026

Delaware law provides that a plaintiff may not sue for medical malprac-
tice unless a medical professional attests to the suit’s merit in an “af-
fidavit  of  merit”  that  “accompanie[s]”  the  plaintiff’s  complaint.    Del.
Code,  Tit.  18,  §6853(a)(1).    Petitioner  Harold  Berk  sued  Dr.  Wilson
Choy and Beebe Medical Center in federal court for medical malprac-
tice under Delaware law, but failed to provide the affidavit required by
§6853.  Berk argued that §6853 is not enforceable in federal court be-
cause it is displaced by the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.  The Dis-
trict Court dismissed Berk’s lawsuit for failure to comply with Dela-
ware’s affidavit law.  The Third Circuit affirmed.

Held: Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.  Pp. 3–11.
(a) When  a  plaintiff  brings  a  state-law  claim  in  federal  court,  the
court faces a choice-of-law problem: whether to apply state or federal
law.    The  Rules  of  Decision  Act  directs  federal  courts  to  apply  state
substantive law unless the Constitution, a treaty, or a statute other-
wise requires or provides.  28 U. S. C. §1652.  The Rules Enabling Act,
which authorizes the Supreme Court to adopt uniform rules of proce-
dure  for  district  courts,  provides  for  the  application  of  federal  law.
§2072(a).  So, when a valid Federal Rule of Civil Procedure is on point,
it displaces contrary state law even if the state law would qualify as
substantive under Erie R. Co. v. Tompkins, 304 U. S. 64.  The analysis
is  straightforward:  The  Court  first  asks  whether  a  Federal  Rule  an-
swers the disputed question.  If a Federal Rule does, it governs, unless
it “exceeds statutory authorization or Congress’s rulemaking power.”
Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates, P. A. v. Allstate Ins. Co., 559 U. S.
393, 398.  Pp. 3–4.


2

BERK v. CHOY

Syllabus

(b) Here, Rule 8 answers the disputed question whether Berk’s law-
suit may be dismissed because his complaint was not accompanied by
an affidavit.  Rule 8 prescribes the information a plaintiff must present
about the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation: “a short and
plain  statement  of  the  claim  showing  that  [he]  is  entitled  to  relief.”
Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 8(a)(2).  By requiring no more than a statement of
the claim, Rule 8 establishes “implicitly, but with unmistakable clar-
ity,” Hanna v. Plumer, 380 U. S. 460, 470, that evidence of the claim is
not required.  Rule 12 reinforces the point by providing only one ground
for dismissal based on the merits—“failure to state a claim upon which
relief can be granted,” Rule 12(b)(6)—and prohibiting courts from con-
sidering  “matters  outside  the  pleadings”  when  evaluating  whether  a
plaintiff has stated a claim, Rule 12(d).  The court instead asks only
whether the complaint’s factual allegations, if taken as true, “state a
claim  to  relief  that  is  plausible  on  its  face.”    Bell  Atlantic  Corp.  v.
Twombly, 550 U. S. 544, 570.  This Court has consistently rejected ef-
forts by lower federal courts to require more information than Rule 8
requires.  Delaware’s law and Rule 8 thus give different answers to the
question whether Berk’s complaint can be dismissed as insufficient be-
cause it was unaccompanied by an affidavit.
  Defendants offer a workaround: They rewrite Delaware’s law.  After
defendants’  edits,  the  Delaware  law  is  no  longer  a  pleading  require-
ment but a free-floating evidentiary requirement that can serve as the
basis  for  an  early  dismissal.    But  that  requirement  could  not  be  en-
forced under the Federal Rules.  Defendants concede that the absence
of an affidavit is not grounds for dismissal under Rule 12(b)(6).  And
Rule 56 already prescribes the mechanism for putting a plaintiff to his
proof: a motion for summary judgment.
  Finally, defendants’ argument that Rule 11’s proviso concerning af-
fidavits incorporates state affidavit laws like §6853 fails because the
proviso cannot be read to address affidavits from third parties.  Pp. 4–
10.

(c) Because Rule 8 and §6853 answer the same question, Rule 8 gov-
erns so long as it is valid under the Rules Enabling Act, which requires
that Federal Rules be procedural rather than substantive.  28 U. S. C.
§2072(b).  Rule 8 is valid under the Rules Enabling Act because it “re-
ally regulates  procedure.”  Sibbach v. Wilson &amp; Co., 312 U. S. 1, 14.
Defendants argue that determining whether a Rule is valid under the
Rules  Enabling  Act  requires  also  asking  whether  the displaced  state
law is substantive, but “the substantive nature of [a state] law, or its
substantive purpose, makes no difference” to the analysis of a Federal
Rule’s validity.  Shady Grove, 559 U. S., at 409.  Pp. 10–11.

Reversed and remanded.


Cite as: 607 U. S. ___ (2026)

3

Syllabus

BARRETT,  J.,  delivered  the  opinion  of  the  Court,  in  which  ROBERTS,
C. J.,  and  THOMAS,  ALITO,  SOTOMAYOR,  KAGAN,  GORSUCH,  and
KAVANAUGH, JJ., joined.  JACKSON, J., filed an opinion concurring in the
judgment.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

Opinion of the Court

NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the
United  States  Reports.  Readers  are  requested  to  notify  the  Reporter  of
Decisions,  Supreme  Court  of  the  United  States,  Washington,  D.  C.  20543,
pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–440
_________________

HAROLD R. BERK, PETITIONER v.
WILSON C. CHOY, ET AL.

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE THIRD CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE BARRETT delivered the opinion of the Court.
The cost of malpractice insurance for doctors and hospi-
tals has significantly increased in some areas of the coun-
try.  In response, several States have imposed a screening
mechanism on malpractice suits, requiring plaintiffs to sub-
mit an affidavit from a medical professional attesting to the
suit’s merit.  We consider whether Delaware’s affidavit re-
quirement applies in federal court and hold that it does not.

I

While on a trip to Delaware, Harold Berk fell out of bed.
According to his complaint, he was taken by ambulance to
a hospital owned by Beebe Medical Center, Inc., where an
X ray revealed a fractured ankle.  Dr. Wilson Choy recom-
mended that Berk be fitted with a protective boot.

The  fitting  did  not  go  well.    Hospital  employees  forced
Berk’s leg into the boot, twisting his fractured ankle.  Still,
Dr. Choy did not immediately order another X ray; he told
Berk to keep weight off his ankle, proposed a follow-up ap-
pointment in two weeks, and sent Berk on his way.  At the
follow-up, Berk got a second X ray, which showed that his


2

BERK v. CHOY

Opinion of the Court

ankle was not just fractured but also severely deformed, re-
quiring surgery.

Berk sued Beebe Medical Center and Dr. Choy (whom we
will  call  defendants)  for  medical  malpractice  under  Dela-
ware law.  Because Berk and defendants are citizens of dif-
ferent States, Berk could sue in federal court based on di-
versity jurisdiction.

Under Delaware law, a plaintiff may not sue for medical
malpractice unless an affidavit of merit “accompanie[s]” the
complaint.  Del. Code, Tit. 18, §6853(a)(1) (2025).  The affi-
davit  must  be  signed  by  a  medical  professional,  §6853(c),
and it must state that there are “reasonable grounds to be-
lieve  that  there  has  been  health-care  medical  negligence
committed by each defendant,” §6853(a)(1).  A plaintiff with
“good cause” may secure a single 60-day extension of time
in which to file the affidavit, ibid., but he must file the ex-
tension  motion  before  or  when  he  files  the  complaint,
§6853(a)(2).  If  an  affidavit  does  not  accompany  the  com-
plaint and the plaintiff has not filed a timely extension mo-
tion,  then  the  clerk  of  court  shall  “refuse  to  file  the  com-
plaint  and  it  shall  not  be  docketed.”  §6853(a)(1).  The
defendants  need  not  take  any  action  with  respect  to  the
complaint until 20 days after the affidavit of merit is filed.
§6853(a)(4).  Upon the defendants’ motion, the court must
determine in camera if the affidavit satisfies the statutory
requirements.  §6853(d).

Attempting  to  comply  with  §6853,  Berk  immediately
moved for an extension of time to file an affidavit.  The Dis-
trict Court granted Berk’s motion, and Berk tried to track
down  a  doctor  willing  to  provide  an  affidavit  (an  ordeal
spawning separate litigation).  But the clock ran out, and
coming  up  empty-handed,  Berk  instead  filed  his  medical
records under seal.  Defendants moved the District Court to
review Berk’s submissions in camera to determine whether
they complied with §6853.  Berk countered that §6853 is not
enforceable  in  federal court  because  it is  displaced  by  the


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

Opinion of the Court

Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.  The District Court disa-
greed  with  Berk  and  dismissed  his  lawsuit  for  failure  to
comply  with  Delaware’s  affidavit  law.  See  2023  WL
2770573, *1–*2 (D Del., Apr. 4, 2023).

The Third Circuit affirmed, holding that §6853 applies in
federal  court.  See  2024  WL  3534482,  *4  (July  25,  2024).
The court concluded that the Federal Rules of Civil Proce-
dure are silent as to whether an affidavit must accompany
the complaint.  Id., at *2–*3.  Where the Federal Rules are
silent, state law applies if it is substantive.  See Erie R. Co.
v. Tompkins, 304 U. S. 64, 78 (1938).  A state law is sub-
stantive if (1) it is outcome determinative, and (2) failing to
apply it in federal court would promote forum shopping and
the  inequitable  administration  of  the  law.    See  Hanna  v.
Plumer, 380 U. S. 460, 467–469 (1965).  After applying this
test, the Third Circuit concluded that §6853 is substantive
and  affirmed  the  dismissal  of  Berk’s  suit.  See  2024  WL
3534482, *3–*4.

We granted certiorari.  604 U. S. 1193 (2025).

II

State-law claims are usually brought in state court.  But
if the parties are citizens of different States and the amount
in controversy exceeds a certain threshold, a plaintiff may
choose to sue in federal court.  28 U. S. C. §1332.  In that
event,  the  federal  court  faces  a  choice-of-law  problem:
whether to apply state or federal law.  The Rules of Decision
Act  directs  federal  courts  to  apply  state  substantive  law,
leaving federal law to cover the rest.  §1652.  Following that
direction  is  harder  than  it  looks,  because  determining
whether a state law is substantive requires a court to enter
“Erie’s murky waters.”  Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates,
P. A. v. Allstate Ins. Co., 559 U. S. 393, 398 (2010).

Yet when a Federal Rule of Civil Procedure is on point, a
federal court bypasses Erie’s inquiry altogether.  That is be-
cause  the  Rules  of  Decision  Act  dictates  that  state


4

BERK v. CHOY

Opinion of the Court

substantive law must yield if the Constitution, a treaty, or
a statute “otherwise require[s] or provide[s].”  §1652.  And
the  Rules  Enabling  Act,  which  authorizes  the  Supreme
Court to adopt uniform rules of procedure for district courts,
provides  for  the  application  of  federal  law.    §2072(a);  see
also Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 1 (“These rules govern the proce-
dure  in  all  civil  actions  and  proceedings  in  the  United
States district courts . . . ”).  Thus, a valid Rule of Civil Pro-
cedure  displaces  contrary  state  law  even  if  the  state  law
would qualify as substantive under Erie’s test.  See Hanna,
380 U. S., at 469–474.

Analyzing whether a Federal Rule displaces state law is
straightforward.    We  first  ask  whether  the  Federal  Rule
“answers the question in dispute.”  Shady Grove, 559 U. S.,
at 398.  In doing so, we interpret the Federal Rules the same
way  we  interpret  federal  laws  more  generally:  by  giving
them their “plain meaning.”  Walker v. Armco Steel Corp.,
446 U. S. 740, 750, n. 9 (1980).  If a Federal Rule answers
the disputed question, it governs, unless it “exceeds statu-
tory  authorization  or  Congress’s  rulemaking  power.”
Shady Grove, 559 U. S., at 398.

A
In this case, the disputed question is whether Berk’s law-
suit  may  be  dismissed  because  his  complaint  was  not  ac-
companied by an expert affidavit.1  Rule 8 gives the answer.

——————

1 The concurrence objects to our framing the disputed question around
dismissal  because  doing  so  “assumes  that  Berk’s  lawsuit  has  already
been . . . filed and docketed.”  Post, at 4 (JACKSON, J., concurring in judg-
ment).  But  Berk’s  lawsuit  has  already  been  filed  and  docketed,  see
No. 1:22–cv–01506 (D Del., Nov. 18, 2022), ECF Doc. 1, which is how it
found its way here.  The only question in dispute is whether Berk’s law-
suit may be dismissed—indeed, that is the question on which we granted
certiorari.  See Pet. for Cert. i.  The concurrence reframes the question
in dispute as “what is required to start a medical malpractice case.”  Post,
at 4.  But because no one argues that the court violated §6853 by docket-
ing Berk’s complaint, the concurrence is ultimately forced to grapple with


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

Opinion of the Court

It prescribes the information a plaintiff must present about
the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation: “a short
and plain statement of the claim showing that [he] is enti-
tled to relief.”  Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 8(a)(2).  By requiring no
more than a statement of the claim, Rule 8 establishes “im-
plicitly, but with unmistakable clarity,” Hanna, 380 U. S.,
at 470, that evidence of the claim is not required.  Cf. Bur-
lington  Northern  R.  Co.  v.  Woods,  480  U. S.  1,  7–8  (1987)
(declining to apply a state statute where a Federal Rule “oc-
cupies the statute’s field of operation”).

Rule 12 reinforces the point.  It provides only one ground
for dismissal based on the merits: “failure to state a claim
upon  which  relief  can  be  granted.”    Fed.  Rule  Civ.
Proc. 12(b)(6).    When  evaluating  whether  a  plaintiff  has
stated a claim, the court cannot consider “matters outside
the  pleadings.”  Rule  12(d).    The  court  instead  asks  only
whether  the  complaint’s  factual  allegations,  if  taken  as
true,  “state  a  claim  to  relief  that  is  plausible  on  its  face.”
Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly, 550 U. S. 544, 570 (2007).
A  complaint  that  satisfies  this  standard  is  “well-pleaded”
and “may proceed even if it strikes a savvy judge that actual
proof of the facts alleged is improbable.”  Id., at 556.

By  design,  this  system  of  pleading  makes  it  relatively
easy for plaintiffs to subject defendants to discovery—even
for claims that are likely to fail.  To protect defendants from
this  burden,  lower  federal  courts  have  sometimes  tried  to
require  more  information  for  certain  kinds  of  claims:  42
U. S. C. §1983 actions against municipalities, Leatherman
v. Tarrant County Narcotics Intelligence and Coordination
Unit,  507  U. S.  163  (1993);  employment  discrimination
suits, Swierkiewicz v. Sorema N. A., 534 U. S. 506 (2002);
and prisoner suits, Jones v. Bock, 549 U. S. 199 (2007).  We

——————
the question whether Berk’s lawsuit may be “dismiss[ed].”  Post, at 11.
By focusing on dismissal from the start, we do not “jum[p] the gun,” post,
at 4, but rather cut to the chase.


6

BERK v. CHOY

Opinion of the Court

have consistently rejected such efforts.  As we explained in
Leatherman—which  dealt  with  a  demand  that  plaintiffs
plead  certain  §1983  claims  with  added  specificity—
Rule 8(a)(2) requires “only” a “ ‘short and plain statement of
the  claim.’ ”    507  U. S.,  at  165,  168  (quoting  Rule  8(a)(2)).
Unless  the  Federal  Rules  single  out  a  claim  for  special
treatment,  see,  e.g.,  Fed.  Rule  Civ.  Proc. 9,  Rule  8  sets  a
ceiling on the information that plaintiffs can be required to
provide about the merits of their claims.
  Delaware’s affidavit requirement is at odds with Rule 8
because it demands more: A medical malpractice suit can-
not  proceed  “unless  the  complaint  is  accompanied  by  . . .
[a]n affidavit of merit.”  §6853(a)(1).  Under Rule 8, factual
allegations are sufficient, but under the Delaware law, the
plaintiff needs evidence too.  See Dishmon v. Fucci, 32 A. 3d
338, 344 (Del. 2011) (describing §6853 as imposing a “prima
facie  evidentiary  requiremen[t]”);  see  also  Brief  for  Re-
spondent Beebe 23 (same).  The two rules thus give differ-
ent answers to the question whether Berk’s complaint can
be dismissed as insufficient because it was unaccompanied
by an affidavit.

It is true, as defendants and the concurrence are quick to
point out, that an affidavit of merit is a document separate
from  the  “pleading,”  and  that,  by  its  literal  terms,  Rule 8
defines only what the “pleading . . . must contain.”  But we
think it is fair to infer that by specifying what information
about  the  merits  is  required  in  the  “pleading,”  Rule  8  ex-
cludes the possibility of requiring even more information on
the same topic—whether in the “pleading” itself or on a sep-
arate sheet of paper attached to it.  Cf. Jones, 549 U. S., at
205, 212–217 (rejecting requirement that prisoners “attach
proof of exhaustion . . . to their complaints” as inconsistent
with Rule 8).  Rule 8 addresses what information a plaintiff
must provide about the merits of his claim at the outset of


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

7

Opinion of the Court

litigation.  Section 6853 addresses the same issue—and in
doing so, imposes a different standard.2

Resisting this conclusion, defendants cite Cohen v. Bene-
ficial  Industrial  Loan  Corp.,  337  U. S.  541  (1949),  for  the
broad proposition that all state “preconditions to proceed-
ing”  are  consistent  with  the  Federal  Rules.  Brief  for  Re-
spondent Beebe 26–27; see Brief for Respondent Choy 20–
21.  They substantially overread Cohen.  There, a state law
rendered an unsuccessful plaintiff in a shareholder deriva-
tive  suit  liable  for  all  the  defendant’s  expenses,  including
attorney’s fees, and as security for that potential liability,
required the plaintiff to post a bond before proceeding with
the action.  337 U. S., at 543.  The plaintiffs argued that the
bond  requirement  was  displaced  by  then-Rule  23,  which
governed shareholder derivative suits in federal court.  Id.,
at 556.  Cohen held that there was no conflict because the
state law and Rule 23 addressed different issues: The state
law created a liability, while Rule 23 dealt with “disclosure
to  the  court  and  notice  to  the  parties  in  interest.”   Id.,  at
555–556.

Cohen thus did not identify and exempt a broad category
of  so-called  preconditions  to  proceeding  from conflict  with

——————

2 The concurrence accuses us—and the “many Courts of Appeals” that
agree with us—of “contorting” Rule 8 by reading it to implicitly preclude
courts from requiring plaintiffs to provide additional information.  Post,
at 10, and n. 6.  Yet drawing a negative inference from text is sometimes
the best way to understand it.  See A. Scalia &amp; B. Garner, Reading Law:
The Interpretation of Legal Texts 107–111 (2012) (negative-implication
canon).  And while the concurrence criticizes the negative inference we
draw as “inattentively capacious,” post, at 8, its Rule 3 analysis depends
on an analogous inference.  Rule 3 establishes what happens once a com-
plaint is filed: “A civil action is commenced by filing a complaint with the
court.”    Fed.  Rule  Civ.  Proc.  3.    Section  6853,  meanwhile,  establishes
what is required “to file the complaint . . . with the court”: an affidavit of
merit or an extension motion.  §6853(a)(1).  The concurrence finds a col-
lision only by reading Rule 3 to implicitly foreclose any precondition to
filing the complaint.  So if a negative inference is a “contortion,” the con-
currence’s argument fails by its own measure.


8

BERK v. CHOY

Opinion of the Court

the Federal Rules.  It held that a particular state law ad-
dressed  a  matter  that  was  unaddressed  by  the  relevant
Federal Rule.  Here, by contrast, the state law and the Fed-
eral  Rule  address  the  same  issue:  the  information  that  a
plaintiff must provide about the merits of his claim at the
outset of litigation.  Describing the affidavit requirement as
a  “preconditio[n]  to  proceeding”  does  not  magically  dispel
the conflict.

Defendants offer a workaround: They rewrite Delaware’s
law.  While §6853 provides that an affidavit must “accom-
pan[y]” the complaint, defendants suggest that the district
court can simply require it “early in [a] case.”  Brief for Re-
spondent Beebe 13; see also Brief for Respondent Choy 36
(suggesting affidavit can be filed “weeks” or “months” after
the complaint).  This proposal is inspired by §6853’s allow-
ance for an extension of time in which to file the affidavit.
But  defendants  treat  this  exception—which  is  available
only  “for  good  cause  shown”—as  the  rule  and  rework  the
exception to boot.  In federal court, apparently, an extension
motion need not precede or accompany the complaint; nor
is  the  district  court  limited  to  granting  one  60-day  exten-
sion.  See, e.g., Brief for Respondent Beebe 23–25.  And de-
fendants’ proposed changes do not stop there: They would
also have us delete the provision that absolves a defendant
from “tak[ing] any action with respect to the complaint” un-
til the affidavit is filed.  §6853(a)(4).  Under Federal Rule
12(a)(1), service of the summons and complaint triggers a
defendant’s  obligation  to  respond,  and  defendants  admit
that the Federal Rule controls on this point.

After defendants’ edits, the Delaware law is no longer a
pleading requirement that serves a gatekeeping function; it
is a free-floating evidentiary requirement that can serve as
the basis for an early dismissal.  Yet even were it acceptable
to take creative license with the Delaware law, there would
be no way to enforce such a requirement.  Defendants con-
cede  that  the  absence  of  an  affidavit  is  not  grounds  for


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

9

Opinion of the Court

dismissal under Rule 12(b)(6).  They float the possibility of
dismissal  for  failure  to  prosecute,  but  that  does  not  work
because  Berk  actively  participated  in  the  litigation.    De-
fendants’ first choice is the course the District Court took
here:  dismissal  based  on  the  court’s  inherent  authority.
The  problem,  however,  is  that  the  Federal  Rules  already
prescribe a mechanism for putting a plaintiff to his proof: a
motion for summary judgment.  See Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 56.
And  that  does  not  offer  defendants  the  protection  they
want, because before ruling on the motion, the court must
allow the nonmovant “adequate time for discovery.”  Celotex
Corp.  v.  Catrett,  477  U.  S.  317,  322  (1986);  see  also  Rule
12(d) (requiring a “reasonable opportunity to present all the
[pertinent]  material”  if  motion  to  dismiss  is  converted  to
motion for summary judgment).  That defendants cannot fit
the affidavit requirement into the Federal Rules illustrates
that it has no place there.

Perhaps recognizing this, defendants devote most of their
energy to arguing that the Federal Rules contain a loophole.
According  to  defendants,  a  proviso  tucked  into  Rule  11
makes state affidavit laws applicable in federal court even
if they conflict with other Federal Rules.  Rule 11 provides
that “[u]nless a rule or statute specifically states otherwise,
a pleading need not be verified or accompanied by an affi-
davit.”  Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 11(a).  Defendants argue that
§6853  is  a  “statute  [that]  specifically  states  otherwise,”
ibid., and it therefore applies in federal court regardless of
whether it conflicts with other Federal Rules.

Even if Rule 11 incorporates some state affidavit laws, it
does not incorporate this one.  Rule 11 governs the conduct
of those who practice before courts: the “attorney of record”
or  the  “party  personally  if  the  party  is  unrepresented.”
Ibid.  It requires the attorney or pro se party to certify, after
“reasonable” inquiry, that the legal and factual representa-
tions  made  to  the  court  are  warranted.    Rule  11(b).  The
sentence on which defendants rely simply “acknowledges”


10

BERK v. CHOY

Opinion of the Court

that although Rule 11 generally puts the onus on the attor-
ney or  pro se party to vouch for representations, “in some
situations represented parties are required by rule or stat-
ute to verify pleadings or sign affidavits.”  Business Guides,
Inc.  v.  Chromatic  Communications  Enterprises,  Inc.,  498
U. S. 533, 542 (1991) (emphasis added); see, e.g., Fed. Rule
Civ. Proc. 23.1 (requiring complaints in shareholder deriv-
ative actions to be verified).  The sentence has nothing to do
with  affidavits  from  third  parties.    Accordingly,  Rule  11
does  not  shield  Delaware’s  law  from  displacement  by
Rule 8.

B
Because  Rule  8  and  §6853  answer  the  same  question,
Rule 8 governs so long as it is valid under the Rules Ena-
bling Act, which requires that Federal Rules be procedural
rather than substantive.  28 U. S. C. §2072(b) (“Such rules
shall not abridge, enlarge or modify any substantive right”).
The line between substance and procedure is hazy, and we
draw  it  differently  in  different  contexts.  See  Hanna,  380
U. S., at 471 (“The line between ‘substance’ and ‘procedure’
shifts as the legal context changes”).  For purposes of the
Rules Enabling Act, we use a modest test: whether the Fed-
eral Rule “really regulates procedure.”  Sibbach v. Wilson
&amp;  Co.,  312  U. S.  1,  14  (1941).    Or  put  differently,  “[w]hat
matters is what the Rule itself regulates: If it governs only
‘the manner and the means’ by which the litigants’ rights
are ‘enforced,’ it is valid.”  Shady Grove, 559 U. S., at 407
(plurality opinion) (quoting Mississippi Publishing Corp. v.
Murphree, 326 U. S. 438, 446 (1946)).

In applying this analysis, we have “rejected every statu-
tory challenge to a Federal Rule that has come before us.”
Shady Grove, 559 U. S., at 407 (plurality opinion).  We have
upheld  Rules  governing  the  certification  of  class  actions,
id., at 408 (Rule 23); see id., at 416, 436 (Stevens, J., con-
curring  in  part  and  concurring  in  judgment)  (Rule  23);


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

11

Opinion of the Court

service of process, Mississippi Publishing Corp., 326 U. S.,
at 445–446 (Rule 4(f )); compelled mental and physical ex-
aminations,  Sibbach,  312  U. S.,  at  14–16  (Rule  35);  sanc-
tions for frivolous appeals, Burlington, 480 U. S., at 8 (Rule
38); and sanctions for signing court papers without reason-
ably investigating the facts asserted, Business Guides, 498
U. S., at 551–554 (Rule 11).

Like  those  Rules,  Rule  8  “really  regulates  procedure.”
Sibbach,  312  U. S.,  at  14.    It  determines  what  plaintiffs
must present to the court about their claims at the outset
of litigation.  Although the Rule may have some “practical
effect on the parties’ rights,” it regulates “only the process
for enforcing those rights,” not “the rights themselves, the
available remedies, or the rules of decision.”  Shady Grove,
559 U. S., at 407–408 (plurality opinion).

Defendants do not contend otherwise.  Instead, they ar-
gue  that  determining  whether  a  Rule  is  valid  under  the
Rules  Enabling  Act  requires  asking  a  second  question:
whether the displaced state law is substantive.  We rejected
that approach eight decades ago and decline to reconsider
it now.  See Sibbach, 312 U. S., at 14.  On the contrary, we
underscore that “the substantive nature of [a state] law, or
its substantive purpose, makes no difference.”  Shady Grove,
559 U. S., at 409 (plurality opinion).  To determine whether
a Rule is valid under the Rules Enabling Act, the only ques-
tion  is  whether  it  “really  regulates  procedure.”    Sibbach,
312 U. S., at 14.  Rule 8 does, so it governs, and Delaware’s
affidavit law does not apply in federal court.

*

*
The judgment of the Court of Appeals is reversed, and the
case  is  remanded  for  further  proceedings  consistent  with
this opinion.

*

It is so ordered.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

_________________

No. 24–440
_________________

HAROLD R. BERK, PETITIONER v.
WILSON C. CHOY, ET AL.

ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
APPEALS FOR THE THIRD CIRCUIT

[January 20, 2026]

 JUSTICE JACKSON, concurring in the judgment.
I agree with the Court that Delaware’s affidavit require-
ment cannot apply in federal court.  I write separately be-
cause, in my view, the relevant conflicts are with Federal
Rules of Civil Procedure 3 and 12, not Rule 8.

I

As the majority explains, Delaware’s law is, at bottom, an
“affidavit requirement.”  Ante, at 1.  If a medical malprac-
tice  plaintiff  wants  her  complaint  deemed  “filed”  and  his
case  docketed,  the  statute  mandates  that  an  affidavit  of
merit signed by a medical professional (or a motion for an
extension of time to file the affidavit) must accompany the
complaint.  See Del. Code, Tit. 18, §6853(a)(1) (2025).  By
contrast, the Federal Rules require no such additional fil-
ing.  Rather, “[a] civil action is commenced by filing a com-
plaint with the court.”  Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 3.

Thus,  §6853  and  Rule 3  conflict  regarding  the  require-
ments to “commence” a medical malpractice action.  If a fed-
eral court were to follow Delaware’s law, a plaintiff would
have to do more than merely tender the complaint in order
for his medical malpractice lawsuit to be filed and docketed.
But, under the language of Rule 3, civil suits commence as
soon as the complaint—and only the complaint—has been


2

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

filed by the plaintiff.  In my view, this clash warrants re-
versal here.

As  the  majority  explains,  our  cases  make  clear  beyond
cavil  that  “a  valid  [Federal]  Rule  of  Civil  Procedure  dis-
places contrary state law.”  Ante, at 4.  Thus, the nub of the
conflict inquiry is to determine whether the State’s require-
ment is, in fact, contrary to a Federal Rule.  Over time, we
have expressed this central inquiry in various ways.  See,
e.g.,  Hanna  v.  Plumer,  380  U. S.  460,  472  (1965)  (asking
whether “the applicable Federal Rule is in direct collision
with the [state] law”); Burlington Northern R. Co. v. Woods,
480  U. S.  1,  4–5  (1987)  (asking  whether  the  scope  of  the
Federal Rule is “ ‘sufficiently broad’ ” to “ ‘control the issue’ ”
before  the  Court,  “thereby  leaving  no  room  for  the  opera-
tion” of the state law (quoting Walker v. Armco Steel Corp.,
446 U. S. 740, 749–750, and n. 9 (1980))).  But as the ma-
jority acknowledges, our most up-to-date approach to iden-
tifying the necessary conflict is to ask whether the Federal
Rule and the state statute “attemp[t] to answer the same
question.”  Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates, P. A. v. All-
state Ins. Co., 559 U. S. 393, 399 (2010); see also ante, at 4.1

——————

1 To the extent that the  Court suggests that the Federal Rule’s plain
text is all that matters when answering this question, that is not what
our  precedents  hold.    In  Gasperini  v.  Center  for  Humanities,  Inc.,  518
U. S. 415 (1996), we explained that Federal Rules must be interpreted
not  solely  based  on  their  text—as  the  much  earlier  case  of  Walker  v.
Armco Steel Corp. had suggested in a footnote—but also “with sensitivity
to important state interests and regulatory policies,” 518 U. S., at 427,
n. 7.  The  majority  opinion  in  Shady  Grove  subsequently  criticized
Gasperini’s “search for state interests and policies that are ‘important’ ”
as “standardless.”  559 U. S., at 405, n. 7.  But five Justices in that case
(i.e., a majority) agreed nevertheless with Gasperini’s approach to inter-
preting the Federal Rules in this context.  See 559 U. S., at 437 (Gins-
burg,  J.,  dissenting)  (writing  for  three  other  Justices  that  the  Court
should “continue to interpret Federal Rules with awareness of, and sen-
sitivity to, important state regulatory policies”); id., at 418 (Stevens, J.,
concurring  in  part  and  concurring  in  judgment)  (explaining  that  the


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

Per Shady Grove, once a conflict between the State’s re-
quirement and a Federal Rule has been identified, the Fed-
eral Rule displaces the State’s requirement so long as the
Rule is “valid,” meaning that it “governs only ‘the manner
and the means’ by which the litigants’ rights are ‘enforced.’ ”
559  U. S.,  at  407  (plurality  opinion)  (quoting  Mississippi
Publishing  Corp. v. Murphree, 326 U. S. 438, 446 (1946));
see also 28 U. S. C. §2072(b) (Rules Enabling Act).  And for
similar reasons to those given in Part II–B of the majority
opinion, Rule 3 easily satisfies this standard.  See ante, at
10–11;  see  also  Shady  Grove,  559  U. S.,  at  407  (plurality
opinion)  (noting  that  we  have  “rejected  every  statutory
challenge to a Federal Rule that has come before us”).

Accordingly, Delaware’s affidavit requirement cannot ap-

ply in federal court.

II
The majority and I start in the same place and ultimately
reach  the  same  conclusion,  but  we  have  taken  different
paths,  marked  by  different  assumptions  and  nuances.  I
agree with the majority that the first step of today’s analy-
sis  is  to  identify  the  relevant  conflict  by  ascertaining  the
question that the Delaware law and the Federal Rule “at-
temp[t]  to  answer.”  Shady  Grove,  559  U. S.,  at  399;  see
ante, at 4.  But I disagree that, in this case, “the disputed
question  is  whether  Berk’s  lawsuit  may  be  dismissed  be-
cause his complaint was not accompanied by an expert affi-
davit.”  Ante, at 4.  Here is why.

——————
Federal  Rules  “must  be  interpreted  with  some  degree  of  ‘sensitivity  to
important  state  interests  and  regulatory  policies’ ”  (quoting  Gasperini,
518 U. S., at 427, n. 7)).  So, under our precedents, courts must be mind-
ful of state interests and policies when determining whether a Federal
Rule conflicts with state law.


4

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

A
First and foremost, that formulation of the question as-
sumes  that  Berk’s  lawsuit  has  already  been  properly  ac-
cepted by the court clerk (i.e., filed and docketed) and thus
that §6853 is answering whether the “lawsuit may be dis-
missed” for want of the required affidavit.  Ante, at 4.  But
that assumption jumps the gun.  Delaware’s law states that
“[n]o  health-care  negligence  lawsuit  shall  be  filed  in  this
State unless the complaint is accompanied by: (1) [a]n affi-
davit of merit” or (2) “a motion to extend the time to file said
affidavit.”  §6853(a)(1) (emphasis added).  The statute fur-
ther  specifies  that  “[i]f  the  required  affidavit  does  not  ac-
company the complaint or if a motion to extend the time to
file said affidavit . . . has not been filed with the court, then
the . . . clerk of the court shall refuse to file the complaint
and it shall not be docketed with the court.”  Ibid. (emphasis
added).

Accordingly, the text of §6853 makes clear that the stat-
ute’s  first  order  of  business  is  not  to  address  the  require-
ments  for  dismissal  of  an  affidavit-free  lawsuit  such  as
Berk’s.  Instead, §6853 most directly answers the threshold
question of what is required to start a civil action for medi-
cal malpractice under Delaware law.  Delaware’s response
is that the plaintiff must submit an affidavit of merit, or a
motion  for  an  extension  of  time  to  file  such  affidavit,  be-
cause  (to  repeat)  the  clerk  cannot  “file  the  complaint”  or
“docke[t]”
filing.
§6853(a)(1).

the  case  without

that  additional

Rule 3 provides a completely different answer to the ques-
tion of what is required to start a medical malpractice case.
As explained above, under that Rule, “[a] civil action is com-
menced by filing a complaint with the court”—period.  That
answer leaves “no room” for Delaware’s insistence that an
affidavit of merit (or a motion for an extension) must be sub-
mitted in order to commence this kind of legal action.  Bur-
Indeed,  Rule  3  uses  the
lington,  480  U. S.,  at  5.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

uncompromising,  declarative  phrase  “is  commenced,”
plainly indicating that Congress meant for the “filing [of] a
complaint” to be both necessary and sufficient to begin any
civil case (including a malpractice action) in federal court.
Cf. Walker, 446 U. S., at 750, n. 10 (“ ‘Rule 3 simply provides
that an action is commenced by filing the complaint and has
as its primary purpose the measuring of time periods that
begin running from the date of commencement’ ” (quoting 4
C.  Wright  &amp;  A.  Miller,  Federal  Practice  and  Procedure
§1057, p. 191 (1969))); Hallstrom v. Tillamook County, 493
U. S.  20,  26  (1989)  (reading  Rule  3  to  mean  that  “filing  a
complaint  with  the  court”  is  synonymous  with  “fil[ing]
suit”).2

Resisting this conclusion, defendants rely on three cases
from 1949, arguing that “this Court has long found applica-
ble  in  federal  court”  “state-law  condition[s]  on  allowing
suits to proceed.”  Brief for Respondent Beebe 26–27, and

——————

2 The majority contends that its dismissal-focused formulation of the
question  is  the  right  one  because,  in  this  case,  “Berk’s  lawsuit  has  al-
ready been filed and docketed,” and “we granted certiorari” on the ques-
tion “whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed.”  Ante, at 4, n. 1.  That
argument conflates the question presented with the “question” that, un-
der Shady Grove, is supposed to serve as the linchpin of our conflict anal-
ysis.  559 U. S., at 401.  The latter comes not from the facts of the case,
but  rather  from  our  interpretations  of  the  potentially  conflicting  state
law and Federal Rule.  So, while it may be that the question presented is
“whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed,” the relevant question for our
Shady Grove analysis is “what is required to start a medical malpractice
case,” because that is the question that §6853 and, as it happens, Rule 3,
“attemp[t] to answer,” Id., at 399.

Nor is the majority correct that, regardless, I am “ultimately forced to
grapple with the question whether Berk’s lawsuit may be ‘dismiss[ed].’ ”
Ante, at 4, n. 1 (alteration in original).  As I stated above, §6853’s conflict
with Rule 3 is enough to hold that the law cannot apply in federal court.
And, as I have shown, the Rule 3 analysis is about the commencement of
the action, not its dismissal.  Once we determine that §6853 and Rule 3
answer  the  same  commencement-related  question,  §6853  cannot  apply
in federal court, meaning that Berk’s lawsuit cannot be thwarted for fail-
ure to satisfy the requirements of that state law.


6

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

n. 11; see also Brief for Respondent Choy 36–37.  But that
argument mischaracterizes our past rulings.  See Cohen v.
Beneficial  Industrial  Loan  Corp.,  337  U. S.  541  (1949);
Woods v. Interstate Realty Co., 337 U. S. 535 (1949); Walker
v. Armco Steel Corp., 446 U. S. 740.

The majority has already ably explained that defendants
“substantially overread” Cohen for the proposition that “all
state ‘preconditions to proceeding’ are consistent with the
Federal Rules.”  Ante, at 7.  I think Walker and Woods are
also easily distinguishable.

As  with  Cohen,  respondents  overstate  the  effect  of
Walker.  There, we held that a federal court sitting in diver-
sity  must  apply  an  Oklahoma  law  that  deemed  an  action
“commenced” upon service of the summons for purposes of
the State’s statute of limitations.  446 U. S., at 742.  Rule 3,
we explained, “governs the date from which various timing
requirements  of  the  Federal  Rules  begin  to  run,  but  does
not affect state statutes of limitations.”  Id., at 751.  Here,
by contrast, §6853 and Rule 3 serve precisely the same func-
tion, in the same context: Both establish when a malprac-
tice lawsuit is deemed initiated (i.e., filed and docketed) for
purposes of determining “the date from which various tim-
ing requirements of the Federal Rules begin to run.”  Ibid.
That is precisely the kind of conflict that bars the applica-
tion of state law in federal court under our precedents.3

Defendants’  reliance  on  Woods  is  similarly  unavailing.
There, we held that a federal court sitting in diversity must
apply  a  Mississippi
out-of-state
——————

law  prohibiting

3 Proving  this  point,  another  provision  of  the  Delaware  law,
§6853(a)(4), provides that a defendant is “not required to take any action
with respect to the complaint . . . until 20 days after plaintiff has filed
the affidavit.”  Under the Federal Rules, however, the deadline for a re-
sponsive act by the defendant is anchored to the filing of the complaint.
See Fed. Rules Civ. Proc. 4(m) (a plaintiff must serve the complaint and
summons “within 90 days after the complaint is filed”) and 12(a)(1)(A)(i)
(a defendant “must serve an answer . . . within 21 days after being served
with the summons and complaint”).


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

7

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

corporations  from  bringing  suit  in  the  State  unless  they
designated an agent for service of process.  337 U. S., at 536,
n.  1.  Mississippi’s  law  was  enacted  to  ensure  that  only
those out-of-state corporations that consented to being sued
in  Mississippi  had  the  privilege  of  accessing  Mississippi’s
courts.  See ibid.  In other words, Mississippi’s law had a
broad substantive purpose and effect that went well beyond
what the Federal Rules addressed.  That was why we had
to  wade  through  “Erie’s  murky  waters”  to  decide  the  con-
flicts question that case presented.  See Shady Grove, 559
U. S.,  at  398;  see  Erie  R. Co.  v.  Tompkins,  304  U. S.  64
(1938).  Delaware’s  affidavit  requirement,  by  contrast,  is
plainly procedural in scope and well within the territory of
the Federal Rules.

In short, our precedents establish that when a state law
and a valid Federal Rule conflict—because they answer the
same procedural question—the State’s requirement is inap-
plicable in federal court.  Because §6853 answers the same
question  about  what  is  required  to  commence  a  medical
malpractice action as the unquestionably valid Rule 3, Del-
aware’s law must give way.  See Hanna, 380 U. S., at 469–
474.

B

If we accept, for the sake of argument, that the question
Delaware’s law attempts to answer is “whether [a medical
malpractice complaint] may be dismissed because [it] was
not accompanied by an expert affidavit,” ante, at 4, a prob-
lem arises: The Federal Rule the majority points to does not
answer that same question.

The majority discerns a conflict with Rule 8 by reasoning
as follows.  With respect to the dismissal-related question
quoted  above,  Delaware’s  law  says  that  such  a  complaint
must be dismissed because the affidavit of merit is missing,
whereas  Rule  8  prescribes  all  “the  information  a  plaintiff
must present about the merits of his claim at the outset of


8

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

litigation”—namely,  “ ‘a  short  and  plain  statement  of  the
claim  showing  that  [he]  is  entitled  to  relief.’ ”    Ante,  at  5
(quoting  Fed.  Rule  Civ.  Proc.  8(a)(2)).  “By  requiring  no
more than a statement of the claim,” the majority contin-
ues, “Rule 8 establishes ‘implicitly, but with unmistakable
clarity,’  . . .  that  evidence  of  the  claim  is  not  required.’ ”
Ante, at 5.

The problem with this reasoning is not that it is based on
“a negative inference” about Rule 8, id., at 7, n. 2, but rather
the inattentively capacious scope of that negative inference.
I agree that Rule 8(a)’s finite list “preclude[s] courts” from
imposing  additional  requirements.  Ibid.;  see Leatherman
v. Tarrant County Narcotics Intelligence and Coordination
Unit, 507 U. S. 163, 168 (1993).  But context is critical: Rule
8 does not purport to establish all that a medical malprac-
tice plaintiff can be required to say about the merits of his
claims at the beginning of the case, much less that nothing
more than the filing of a complaint can be mandated.  Ra-
ther,  it  (more  narrowly)  addresses  what  any  “pleading”
stating  a  claim  for  relief  must  contain.    See  Rule 8(a)  (“A
pleading that states a claim for relief must contain . . .” (em-
phasis  added)).  The  majority  neither  holds  nor  suggests
that §6853’s affidavit of merit is, itself, a “pleading”; to the
contrary, the majority admits that the affidavit is not.  Ante,
at 6.  So, as I see it, Delaware’s law—which prescribes what
a plaintiff must submit in addition to his pleadings in order
for his complaint to be filed and his case docketed—does not
actually conflict with Rule 8.

The majority acknowledges this “pleading” problem and
offers, apparently as a solution, yet another formulation of
the question that Rule 8 is answering: Rule 8, it says, tells
us  “what  information  a  plaintiff  must  provide  about  the
merits of his claim.”  Ante, at 6.  But, again, this description
fails to acknowledge that Rule 8 operates entirely within a
specific universe: the pleadings.  The majority’s unbounded
characterization subtly frees Rule 8 from the constraint of


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

9

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

its  subject  matter,  allowing  it  to  expand  until  it  collides
with Delaware’s law.4

When properly construed, Rule 8 addresses a particular
(and  particularly  important)  procedural  question:  “What
must a pleading that states a claim for relief contain?”5  In
my  view,  this  narrower  formulation  of  the  question—the
one tethered to the required contents of a “pleading”—keeps
Rule 8 within the bounds of its plain meaning, consistent
with  Gasperini’s  command  not  to  overread  the  Federal
Rules at the expense of “important state interests and reg-
ulatory policies” in cases such as this one.  Gasperini v. Cen-
ter for Humanities, Inc., 518 U. S. 415, 427, n. 7 (1996); see
also n. 1, supra.

Accordingly,  because  §6853  does  not  address  or  govern
the required contents of a pleading, Delaware’s law does not
answer the same question as Rule 8.  Instead, the State’s
affidavit  requirement  (which,  incidentally,  neither  de-
scribes the affidavit of merit in relation to a plaintiff ’s obli-
gation to state a claim for relief nor treats it as evidence) is
an additional filing requirement for commencing any med-
See
ical  malpractice  civil  action  under  state  law.
§6853(a)(1)  (“No  health-care  negligence  lawsuit  shall  be

——————

4 The majority’s description of Rule 8’s work is inaccurate even if con-
fined to the universe of pleadings.  Rule 8 does not “addres[s] what infor-
mation  a  plaintiff  must  provide  about  the  merits  of  his  claim”  in  the
pleadings.  Ante, at 6 (emphasis added).  Instead, with respect to a plead-
ing that states a claim for relief (as opposed to one that does not, see Rule
7), Rule 8 governs how much a plaintiff must say concerning his claim.
Rule 8’s primary purpose is to install a “simplified pleading system” that
requires  a  complaint  to  include  nothing  more  than  “ ‘short  and  plain
statement[s]’ ”  of  the  claim,  the  grounds  for  jurisdiction,  and  the  relief
sought.  Swierkiewicz v. Sorema N. A., 534 U. S. 506, 512, 514 (2002).  In
other words, Rule 8’s innovation is the “short and plain” bit, not the sub-
stance of what is required to be stated in that manner.

5 The answer, under the Rule, is (1) “a short and plain statement of the
grounds for . . . jurisdiction,” (2) “a short and plain statement of the claim
showing that the pleader is entitled to relief,” and (3) “a demand for the
relief sought.”  Rule 8(a).


10

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

filed in [Delaware] unless the complaint is accompanied by
. . .  [a]n  affidavit  of  merit”).  Finding  a  Rule  8  conflict,  as
the majority does, thus requires contorting both Rule 8 and
§6853.  There is no need to do so here, especially given the
ready  conflict  with  Rule  3  (discussed  above)  and  Rule  12
(described below).6

III
The majority and I appear to agree that Delaware’s affi-
davit  requirement—as  interpreted  by  the  Delaware  Su-
preme  Court—conflicts  with  Rule  12(d).  See  ante,  at  5.
That conflict suffices to displace §6853’s requirement.  But
to the extent that the majority ties its Rule 12 analysis to
the purported Rule 8 conflict, see ibid., I think the majority
has gone further than it needs to, introducing incoherence
in the process.

While the statute itself does not so specify, the Delaware
Supreme Court has interpreted §6853 to mean that (assum-
ing the clerk of court accepts an affidavit-free medical mal-
practice  action  and  dockets  the  case  notwithstanding  the
statute’s prohibition) “[t]he filing of a healthcare negligence

——————

6 To be sure, many Courts of Appeals have also relied on a conflict with
Rule 8 to hold that state affidavit-of-merit laws like Delaware’s do not
apply in federal court.  See Albright v. Christensen, 24 F. 4th 1039, 1048–
1049  (CA6  2022);  Gallivan  v.  United  States,  943  F.  3d  291,  293  (CA6
2019); Pledger v. Lynch, 5 F. 4th 511, 519 (CA4 2021); Young v. United
States, 942 F. 3d 349, 351 (CA7 2019).  But a closer look at the relevant
cases reveals that these courts, like the majority, got there by manipu-
lating the relevant question.  In Gallivan, for example, the Sixth Circuit
posed  as  the  pertinent  question:  “[D]oes  someone  need  an  affidavit  of
merit to state a claim for medical negligence?”  943 F. 3d, at 293.  This
leading  question  not  only  ignores  (as  the majority  does)  that  Rule  8  is
solely about “pleadings,” but, worse, also preordains a conflict by naming
the very thing that the state law requires but the Federal Rule does not
(i.e., an affidavit).  The Fourth and Seventh Circuits make the same er-
ror.  See Pledger, 5 F. 4th, at 519 (asking “whether a medical malpractice
plaintiff must provide pre-suit expert support for his claim”); Young, 942
F. 3d, at 351 (asking whether Rule 8 “require[s] attachments”).


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

11

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

action  without  the  requisite  affidavit  of  merit  constitutes
grounds of dismissal of medical negligence claims as a mat-
ter of law.”  Hall v. Sorouri, 996 A. 2d 793 (Del. 2010) (Ta-
ble).  That reading of Delaware law answers the question,
“What can a court consider when dismissing a medical mal-
practice case?”  Because “[t]he highest state court is the fi-
nal  authority  on  state  law,”  Fidelity  Union  Trust  Co.  v.
Field, 311 U. S. 169, 177 (1940), we must read this statute
as  that  court  does,  i.e.,  as  establishing  dismissal  require-
ments for medical malpractice cases.  Thus, if a valid Fed-
eral Rule answers that same dismissal question, §6853 can-
not govern in federal court.  See Shady Grove, 559 U. S., at
398.

Enter Rule 12.  As the majority correctly explains, Rule
12(b)(6) provides the “only . . . ground for dismissal based
on the merits,” and Rule 12(d) prohibits courts from consid-
ering “ ‘matters outside the pleadings’ ” in deciding motions
to dismiss brought under Rule 12(b)(6).  Ante, at 5; see also
Stanley v. City of Sanford, 606 U. S. 46, 49 (2025) (explain-
ing that, under Rule 12(d), a judge considering a motion to
dismiss  must  “take  as  true  the  well-pleaded  facts  in  the
plaintiff ’s complaint, . . . and [must] not consider evidence
beyond that pleading”).  Furthermore, by all accounts, the
affidavit required by Delaware’s law is a “matte[r] outside
the pleadings.”  Rule 12(d); see ante, at 6 (“It is true . . . that
an affidavit of merit is a document separate from the ‘plead-
ing’ ”).

We know the affidavit of merit qualifies as a “matter out-
side the pleadings” for several reasons.  For one thing, Del-
aware law provides that the affidavit is to “accompany” the
complaint.  §6853(a)(1).  A thing cannot “accompany” that
of  which  it  is  already  a  part.7    Indeed,  Delaware’s
——————

7 To be sure, plaintiffs can, in limited contexts, “incorporat[e]” certain
documents  “into  the  complaint  by  reference.”    Tellabs,  Inc.  v.  Makor


12

BERK v. CHOY

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

Legislature apparently felt so strongly about the affidavit
not being part of the complaint that it mandated physical
separation: By statute, the affidavit must be filed in its own
sealed envelope, alongside (but apart from) the complaint.
See ibid.  Nor do the Federal Rules suggest that affidavits
of the nature specified by the Delaware law can qualify as
“pleadings.”  Rule 7, which sets forth a list of “[p]leadings
[a]llowed”  in  federal  court,  does  not  include  an  “affidavit”
(or anything like it) on its list.

Pulling these threads together, Delaware’s law, as inter-
preted by the Delaware Supreme Court, requires judges to
account for a matter outside the pleadings—i.e., the exist-
ence  or  sufficiency  of  an  affidavit  of  merit  (or  lack
thereof )—when deciding whether to dismiss a medical mal-
practice case.  Rule 12(d), however, forbids such extraneous
considerations.  And Rule 12 is valid under the Rules Ena-
bling  Act  (for  similar  reasons  as  the  Court  lays  out  in  its
opinion, see ante, at 10–11).  So Delaware’s law cannot be
enforced in federal court.

As far as I can tell, then, there is no daylight between my
view of the Rule 12 conflict and the majority’s assessment.
But far from “reinforc[ing]” a conflict with Rule 8, ante, at
5, our shared evaluation of Rule 12 is, to me, yet another
reason  why  Delaware’s  law  is  not  in  conflict  with  Rule  8.
See  Part  II–B,  supra.  The  conflicts  analysis  concerning
these two Rules is based on diametrically opposed charac-
terizations  of  Delaware’s  affidavit  of  merit:  The  affidavit
must be either a “matter outside the pleadings” (and thus
§6853  conflicts  with  Rule  12,  per  the  Delaware  Supreme
Court’s decision in Hall) or it is part of what the pleadings
must contain (giving rise to the purported conflict with Rule
8).  A coherent conflicts analysis cannot have it both ways.

——————
Issues &amp; Rights, Ltd., 551 U. S. 308, 322 (2007).  But the affidavit of merit
is  not  such  a document  because  its  content  is  neither discoverable  nor
admissible.  See §6853(d).


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

13

JACKSON, J., concurring in judgment

*

*

*
Read for what they are—by their “plain meaning,” sensi-
tive to context yet without distortions created by the task of
checking for a conflict, see Walker, 446 U. S., at 750, n. 9;
Gasperini, 518 U. S., at 427, n. 7—Rules 3 and 12 answer
the  same  questions  as  Delaware’s  affidavit  requirement.
That means that the majority and I share the same conclu-
sion: There is a conflict between state law and valid Federal
Rules,  precluding  application  of  Delaware’s  affidavit  re-
quirement  in  federal  court.  For  the  reasons  discussed
above,  I  think  the  majority  is  wrong  to  further  maintain
that  §6853  answers  the  same  question  as  Rule  8.    And  I
cannot see how the affidavit that the Delaware law requires
can be a “matter outside the pleadings” (for Rule 12-conflict
purposes) and also part of the “pleadings” (for Rule 8-con-
flict purposes).  Therefore, I concur only in the judgment.&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776753/berk-v-choy/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Howell v. Circuit Court of Indiana</title>
      <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776750/howell-v-circuit-court-of-indiana/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776750/howell-v-circuit-court-of-indiana/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/pdf/2026/01/20/howell_v._circuit_court_of_indiana.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

JACKSON, J., dissenting

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

INDIANA, EX REL. DANNY W. HOWELL v. CIRCUIT
COURT OF INDIANA, WELLS COUNTY, ET AL.

ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI AND MOTION FOR
LEAVE TO PROCEED IN FORMA PAUPERIS TO THE
SUPREME COURT OF INDIANA

No. 25–5557.  Decided January 20, 2026

The  motion  of  petitioner  for  leave  to  proceed  in  forma
pauperis is denied, and the petition for a writ of certiorari
is dismissed.  See Rule 39.8.  As the petitioner has repeat-
edly abused this Court's process, the Clerk is directed not
to accept any further petitions in noncriminal matters from
petitioner unless the docketing fee required by Rule 38(a) is
paid and the petition is submitted in compliance with Rule
33.1.  See Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals,
506 U. S. 1 (1992) (per curiam).

 JUSTICE  JACKSON,  dissenting  from  denial  of  motion  for

leave to proceed in forma pauperis.

To file a petition in this Court, litigants must pay a $300
fee, along with the (much higher) cost of printing 40 bound
copies of their filing.  Litigants who cannot afford the filing
fee and the cost of printing can request to proceed in forma
pauperis.  The Court largely grants these requests, allowing
those litigants to file for free, but our openness to indigent
litigants  has  its  limits.  In  fact,  the  Court  sometimes  im-
poses blanket filing bars that prohibit litigants from filing
any more in forma pauperis petitions in noncriminal mat-
ters going forward, regardless of the merits of their claims.
Today, the Court bars essentially all future filings from
Danny Howell (an indigent inmate serving a 70-year sen-
tence) because Howell previously submitted a handful of pe-


2

HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA

JACKSON, J., dissenting

titions we deemed “frivolous.”1  Even if Howell were to iden-
tify meritorious grounds for habeas relief or wanted to bring
a justifiable challenge to his conditions of confinement, he
will now be prevented from doing so unless he pays the fil-
ing fee—no matter what.  A categorical, forward-looking fil-
ing bar is a questionable restriction as to any litigant who
cannot afford to pay a filing fee.  For me, it is an intolerable
one as to incarcerated individuals.  Accordingly, I respect-
fully dissent.

I

The  Court  began  imposing  prospective  filing  bars  on  in
forma pauperis litigants in 1989.  First was Jessie McDon-
ald.  The Court’s decision to bar McDonald made intuitive
sense: He had filed 73 petitions over the preceding 18 years,
several of which were collateral attacks on a state convic-
tion for which he was no longer incarcerated.  In re McDon-
ald,  489  U. S.  180,  183  (per  curiam).  Over  the  dissent  of
four Justices, the Court barred McDonald from proceeding
in forma pauperis when seeking extraordinary writs in the
future.2

Less than two years later, over the dissent of three Jus-
tices, the Court imposed another filing bar, this time pre-
venting  Michael  Sindram  from  proceeding  in  forma

——————

1 See  this  Court’s  Rule  39.8  (“If  satisfied  that  a  petition  for  a  writ  of
certiorari, jurisdictional statement, or petition for an extraordinary writ
is frivolous or malicious, the Court may deny leave to proceed in forma
pauperis”).

2 We emphasized that extraordinary writs are “ ‘drastic and extraordi-
nary  remedies,’  to  be  ‘reserved  for  really  extraordinary  causes.’ ”    In re
McDonald, 489 U. S., at 185 (quoting Ex parte Fahey, 332 U. S. 258, 259–
260 (1947)).  We further noted that the Court had “not granted the sort
of extraordinary writ relentlessly sought by [McDonald] to any litigant—
paid or in forma pauperis—for at least a decade.”  489 U. S., at 184.  The
nature of extraordinary writs not only made McDonald’s repeated filings
frivolous, but it also meant that the filing bar—which targeted only fu-
ture requests for that particular form of relief—did not significantly bur-
den McDonald’s access to the Court.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

JACKSON, J., dissenting

pauperis  when  seeking  extraordinary  writs  in  the  future.
Sindram had filed 43 separate petitions over the prior three
years, the majority of which related to a speeding ticket he
had received years earlier.  In re Sindram, 498 U. S. 177,
177–178 (1991) (per curiam).

The following year, the Court significantly expanded the
reach  of  its  filing  bar.    Over  the  course  of  a  decade,  peti-
tioner  James  Martin  had  filed  54  in  forma  pauperis  peti-
tions requesting writs of certiorari in connection with a va-
riety  of  civil  disputes.    With  two  Justices  dissenting,  the
Court barred Martin from filing any future petitions for cer-
tiorari  in  noncriminal  cases;  unlike  McDonald  and  Sin-
dram, this bar was not limited to requests for extraordinary
writs.  Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals, 506
U. S.  1,  2–3  (1992)  (per  curiam).    Martin’s  circumstances
lent this Court a useful shorthand: When we bar indigent
litigants from filing any future in forma pauperis petitions,
we now say that we are “Martinizing” them.

The Court’s exasperation with McDonald, Sindram, and
Martin  was  understandable.    Each  of  those  litigants  had
flooded the Court with dozens of frivolous filings, causing
significant administrative burdens.  In the Court’s view, a
prospective  filing  bar  was  necessary  to  “curb  serious
abuses” of its docket and to ensure that the Court could al-
locate its resources “in a way that promotes the interests of
justice.”  McDonald, 489 U. S., at 184.

Even so, its decision to permanently restrict an indigent
litigant’s access to this Court was hotly contested.  The dis-
senters in McDonald worried that, in the Court’s “fervor [to]
ensur[e] that rights granted to the poor are not abused,” it
had  “embark[ed]  on  [an]  unprecedented  and  dangerous
course.”  Id.,  at  185–187  (Brennan,  J.,  dissenting).  Simi-
larly, to the dissenters in Sindram, even though prolific lit-
igants do cause a “minimal annoyance,” preserving their ac-
cess  was  “well  worth  the  cost”  given  the  Court’s
“longstanding  tradition  of  leaving  [its]  door  open  to  all


4

HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA

JACKSON, J., dissenting

classes of litigants.”  498 U. S., at 182 (Marshall, J., dissent-
ing).  The  dissenters  feared  that  in  forma  pauperis  filing
bars  abandoned  that  “proud  and  decent”  tradition.    Ibid.
They also predicted that what started as a rare step would
turn out to be “merely the prelude” to a more habitual shut-
ting of the courthouse doors.  McDonald, 489 U. S., at 187
(Brennan, J., dissenting).

II
The  dissenters  were  right.  The  Court  has  steadily  ex-
panded  the  reach  of  Martin,  transforming  what  was  once
an extraordinary measure into a routine order.

Howell’s case is a prime example.  He has filed only six
petitions over the span of 14 years—hardly a flood.  Before
this one, Howell’s last petition was in 2018, eight years ago.
Moreover,  quite  unlike  McDonald,  Sindram,  or  Martin,
Howell  is  in  state  custody  and  serving  a  long  prison  sen-
tence; all six of his petitions have raised claims challenging
aspects of his conviction.

Howell’s case is not an outlier.  By my count, the Court
has now invoked Martin hundreds of times to prospectively
bar indigent litigants from filing in forma pauperis.  We no
longer wait for a petitioner to inundate the Court with friv-
olous filings.  Instead, we reflexively Martinize petitioners
after only a few petitions.  See, e.g., In re Nelson, 607 U. S.
___ (2025) (Martinized after five petitions); Navarro Martin
v. Florida, 607 U. S. ___ (2025) (Martinized after six peti-
tions).

Even more troubling, though the Court did not have oc-
casion  to  consider  in  McDonald,  Sindram,  or  Martin
whether filing bars were necessary or appropriate for incar-
cerated  litigants,  we  now  routinely  impose  filing  bars  on
prisoners.  See,  e.g.,  Crosby  v.  Starr,  607  U. S.  ___  (2025)
(Martinized after filing a petition for certiorari arising from
habeas  proceedings  raising  claims  under  the  First  Step
Act); Brunson v. Herring, 604 U. S. ___ (2024) (Martinized


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

JACKSON, J., dissenting

after filing a petition for certiorari arising from habeas pro-
ceedings  raising  claims  of  actual  innocence);  Kaetz  v.
United States, 602 U. S. ___ (2024) (Martinized after filing
a petition for certiorari arising from proceedings under 28
U. S. C.  §2255  raising
ineffective-assistance-of-counsel
claims).  According to our Clerk’s Office, more than half of
the petitioners whose filings we have categorically rejected
per Martin in the past 22 years were prisoners.

III
  Applying  Martin routinely  to  bar  the  filings of  indigent
incarcerated  petitioners  goes  too  far.    In  my  view,  such  a
restriction foolishly trades a pound of values for an ounce of
convenience.  That is, the Court now blocks indigent incar-
cerated  individuals  from  ever  more  accessing  our  court-
house, just to avoid a minor administrative burden.

To  be  clear:  Martinized  petitioners  are  totally  barred
from ever filing in forma pauperis noncriminal petitions in
the  future—even  to  raise  new  claims  based  on  favorable
changes in the law (which sometimes happen), or to chal-
lenge the ongoing conditions of their confinement (which, in
our society, prisoners are allowed to do).  The future is fa-
mously hard to predict.  So the justification for a permanent
filing bar—even one related to the Court’s administrative
convenience—is murky at best.

Changes  in  the  law  can  give  rise  to  meritorious  chal-
lenges that a prisoner might be able to raise by filing a civil
habeas  petition.  Consider,  for  instance,  the  pro se  peti-
tioner in Welch v. United States, 578 U. S. 120 (2016), who
filed an in forma pauperis petition raising a collateral chal-
lenge to his sentence in light of our prior decision in John-
son  v.  United  States,  576  U. S.  591  (2015).    Welch’s  filing
ultimately resulted in the Court applying Johnson retroac-
tively.  578 U. S., at 130.  But if Welch had been Martinized,
he would have been unable to seek relief in this Court.


6

HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA

JACKSON, J., dissenting

Similarly, the conditions of a prisoner’s confinement may
give rise to new constitutional claims.  In Wilkins v. Gaddy,
559 U. S. 34 (2010) (per curiam), for example, we held that
a pro se petitioner proceeding in forma pauperis had stated
an Eighth Amendment claim based on an assault by prison
officials.  Had Wilkins been Martinized, he would have been
barred from obtaining the relief to which he was due under
our Constitution.  Unfortunately, poor conditions in prisons
across the country continue to pose potential constitutional
problems.3  Indigent prisoners who are Martinized are un-
able to come to this Court to challenge these unsafe condi-
tions and vindicate their constitutional rights.

In short, because time moves on after a person is impris-
oned and things happen, we simply do not and cannot know
whether indigent prisoners who have filed multiple “frivo-
lous” petitions in the past might have a meritorious claim
in the future.  When liberty, bodily integrity, or fundamen-
tal fairness is at stake, preventing such litigants from ever
again accessing our review imperils our ability to provide
equal justice for all.

Meanwhile,  the  administrative  burden  involved  in  re-
viewing repeated (even frivolous) petitions filed by prison-
ers is minimal.  It is the rare incarcerated person who has
the wherewithal to flood the Court with filings, at least in
the  way  that  Martin,  Sindram,  and  McDonald  had  done.
Practicalities ordinarily do not allow for this, since prison-
ers often lack regular access to paper, pens, envelopes, and
stamps.  Pro se prisoners also usually handwrite their fil-
ings—a  time-intensive  process.    And,  regardless,  it  is  not

——————

3 See,  e.g.,  Dept.  of  Justice,  Investigation  of  Alabama’s  State  Prisons
for  Men  5–6  (Apr.  2,  2019),  https://www.justice.gov/crt/case-document/
file/1149971/dl?inline= (detailing Alabama’s failure to provide safe con-
ditions for its prisoners); Dept. of Justice, Investigation of Georgia Pris-
https://www.justice.gov/d9/2024-09/
ons
findings_report_-_investigation_of_georgia_prisons.pdf
(describing
Georgia’s failure to protect incarcerated people from violence).

2024),

(Oct.

1,

3


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

7

JACKSON, J., dissenting

difficult for Court staff to sort out in forma pauperis filings
that raise new, potentially meritorious claims from repeti-
tive, meritless petitions.

I believe that when balancing prisoners’ access to judicial
review, on the one hand, and reducing our administrative
burden, on the other, we should err on the side of keeping
our  courthouse  doors  open.    For  a  system  designed  to  ad-
minister justice, reflexively rejecting (potentially meritori-
ous) petitions from incarcerated litigants has a cost that is
much too high when compared to the (meager) administra-
tive efficiency gains.  Nor should we forget the role that in-
digent  incarcerated  litigants  have  played  in  the  develop-
ment  of  important  constitutional  doctrines—and  through
habeas  proceedings  no  less.   See,  e.g.,  Gideon  v.  Wain-
wright, 372 U. S. 335 (1963); see also Sindram, 498 U. S.,
at 181 (Marshall, J., dissenting).

Accordingly,  I  would  not  apply  the  filing  bar  that  the
Court  imposes  for  frequent  “frivolous”  filers  to  prisoners
who, like Howell, seek to proceed in forma pauperis.&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10776750/howell-v-circuit-court-of-indiana/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klein v. Martin</title>
      <link>https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10779476/klein-v-martin/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10779476/klein-v-martin/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/pdf/2026/01/26/klein_v._martin.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

1

Per Curiam

SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES

CHRISTOPHER KLEIN, SUPERINTENDENT,
DEPARTMENT OF DETENTION FACILITIES
FOR ANNE ARUNDEL COUNTY, ET AL. v.
CHARLES BRANDON MARTIN

ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED
STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE FOURTH CIRCUIT

No. 25–51.  Decided January 26, 2026

 PER CURIAM.
Under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act
of 1996 (AEDPA), strict standards govern the grant of fed-
eral  habeas  relief  to  prisoners  convicted  in  state  court.
Faithful application of those standards sometimes puts fed-
eral district courts and courts of appeals in the disagreeable
position of having to deny relief in cases they would have
analyzed differently if they had been in the shoes of the rel-
evant state court.  But federal courts are dutybound to com-
ply  with  AEDPA,  and  we  have  granted  summary  relief
when the lower courts have departed from the role AEDPA
assigns.  See,  e.g.,  Clark  v.  Sweeney,  607  U. S.  ___  (2025)
(per curiam); Dunn v. Reeves, 594 U. S. 731 (2021) (per cu-
riam);  Mays  v.  Hines,  592  U. S.  385  (2021)  (per curiam);
Virginia v. LeBlanc, 582 U. S. 91 (2017) (per curiam); White
v. Wheeler, 577 U. S. 73 (2015) (per curiam).

This is such a case.  Respondent Charles Brandon Martin
was convicted in a Maryland court for the attempted mur-
der  of  one  of  his  girlfriends,  Jodi  Torok.    The  evidence
against him was strong, his conviction was affirmed on ap-
peal, and an appellate court held in a state postconviction
proceeding  that  the  State’s  failure  to  disclose  certain  im-
peachment  evidence  that  was  favorable  under  Brady  v.
Maryland, 373 U. S. 83 (1963), did not warrant a new trial
because  there  was  no  “reasonable  probability  that  the  re-
sult  of  [the]  trial  would  have  been  different”  had  the


2

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

evidence  been  turned  over.  App.  to  Pet.  for  Cert.  115a
(App.); see Kyles v. Whitley, 514 U. S. 419, 434 (1995) (the
“touchstone of materiality is a ‘reasonable probability’ of a
different result”).  Because that decision neither was “con-
trary  to”  nor  “involved  an  unreasonable  application”  of
“clearly established Federal law,” AEDPA required the de-
nial  of  Martin’s  federal  habeas  petition.
28  U. S. C.
§2254(d)(1).  Yet the Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit
affirmed the award of a new trial based on reasoning that
departed from what AEDPA prescribes.  We therefore grant
the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reverse.

I
A
Torok, the victim of the attempted murder, had been da-
ting  Martin  for  about  a  year  when  she  told  him  she  was
pregnant with a baby she thought was his.  Angered by this
news, Martin demanded that Torok have an abortion.  She
refused and informed him that she intended to go to court
to compel him to provide child support.  She also threatened
to tell his “wife or baby mama” about the child.  App. 254a.
A few weeks later, Martin sent Torok a text message ask-
ing: “ ‘What time do u work[?]’ ”  Martin v. State, 218 Md.
App. 1, 14, 96 A. 3d 765, 773 (2014) (alteration in original).
Torok  replied,  “ ‘I’m  off  [today],’ ”  thus  verifying  that  she
would likely be home.  Ibid.  Later that day, just before 3
p.m., Torok was alone in her apartment in Crofton, Mary-
land, speaking on the phone with a close friend, Blair Wolfe,
who lived in Pittsburgh.  During their call, a man purport-
ing to be a salesman knocked on Torok’s front door.  Torok
hung  up  to  speak  to  the  man  but  promised  to  call  Wolfe
back.  When she did not, Wolfe called her several times, but
no  one  answered.    Growing  increasingly  concerned,  Wolfe
called Torok’s housemate, Jessica Higgs, and asked her to
return home to see if Torok was safe.  Higgs found Torok
unconscious on the floor, bleeding from a gunshot wound to


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

3

Per Curiam

her head.  Torok survived, but her unborn baby did not, and
Torok suffered serious permanent injuries.

When the police examined the scene of the shooting, they
found no sign of forced entry and recovered several items of
evidentiary  value  from  the  floor  near  where  Torok  lay:  a
shell casing and bullet from a .380-caliber cartridge and a
peculiarly modified Gatorade bottle.  (Photos of this bottle
appear in the appendix to this opinion.)  The upper part of
the bottle was covered with two layers of tape, white medi-
cal tape underneath and silver duct tape on top.  There was
a rectangular hole in the tape over the mouth of the bottle
and a jagged hole at the bottom of the bottle.

Circumstantial evidence strongly suggested that this ob-
ject was likely brought to the apartment and left there by
Torok’s assailant.  Higgs testified that the bottle was not on
the floor when she left for work that morning.  Both Torok
and Higgs testified that they did not drink Gatorade or keep
it at home,  and both said that  they would not have left a
bottle on the floor.

The three items found at the crime scene played a part in
the  State’s  case.  Federal  firearms  records  showed  that
Martin owned a .380-caliber semiautomatic handgun that
could have fired the bullet and ejected the casing.  One of
Martin’s girlfriends testified that she had seen him with a
“small” “semiautomatic” gun in the weeks before the shoot-
ing.  App. 379a.  Michael Bradley,  the brother of still an-
other of Martin’s girlfriends, Maggie McFadden, added that
on  several  occasions  he  had  seen  Martin  with  a  “small”
“semi-automatic gun.”  Id., at 331a–333a, 371a.

As  for  the  bottle,  the  State  offered  evidence  suggesting
that  it  was  a  homemade  silencer.    A  police  sergeant  said
that the tape on the mouth of the bottle bore a “rectangular
impression”  that  likely  resulted  from  something  being
“stuck in there.”  Id., at 292a.  The bottle was available for
examination  by  the  jury,  and  the  State  argued  that  the
opening  in  the  tape  was  shaped  like  the  muzzle  of  a


4

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

semiautomatic  handgun.    The  State  also  noted  that  the
edges of the hole at the bottom of the bottle were bent out-
ward, suggesting that the hole had been created by a force
emanating from inside the bottle.  The police sergeant tes-
tified that the bottle resembled homemade silencing devices
he had seen in a film and in online videos.  A detective tes-
tified  that  he  found  “black  soot”  inside  the  bottle,  id.,  at
310a–311a, but that he did not smell burnt or burning ma-
rijuana in the bottle, id., at 314a–315a, and another witness
testified  that  he  found  no  “signs  or  evidence  of  controlled
dangerous substances” in the bottle, id., at 309.  Based on
this  evidence  and  the  fact  that  none  of  Torok’s  neighbors
had heard a gunshot at the apartment on the afternoon of
the shooting, the State argued that the bottle had been used
as a silencer.

Testing of the bottle revealed DNA evidence that strongly
implicated  Martin.  A  hair  was  found  on  the  tape  on  the
bottle,  and  one  of  the  State’s  expert  witnesses,  a  forensic
scientist, determined that although the hair could not have
come from 99.94 percent of the population of North Amer-
ica, she could not rule out Martin as the source of hair.

Besides the DNA taken from the hair, trace DNA from at
least three persons, including at least one male, was found
on the mouth of the bottle.  A forensic chemist testified that
she could rule out 96 percent of the black population as po-
tential sources of this DNA but could not rule out Martin
(who is black).*

This DNA evidence linking Martin to the bottle was bol-
stered by the testimony of Michael Bradley.  Bradley testi-
fied that on the afternoon of the shooting, he, his brother
Frank,  Martin,  and  an  acquaintance  named  Jerry  Burks
smoked marijuana at McFadden’s home.  At one point, ac-
cording  to  Michael,  Frank  went  upstairs  and  came  back
with white “medical tape.”  Id., at 337a.  Martin and Frank

——————
*Nor could she rule out Torok.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

5

Per Curiam

then  went  upstairs  together.  Frank  came  downstairs,
grabbed a Gatorade bottle, and headed back up the stairs
with it.

Based on this testimony, the State suggested that Martin
helped to make the bottle into the silencing device that the
shooter used.  This theory was supported by the discovery
in the McFadden home of the same kind of white medical
tape that was affixed to the bottle.

Michael Bradley further testified that Martin acted sus-
piciously at the time of and shortly after the shooting.  Ac-
cording to his testimony, Martin and Burks left the house
together before 2 p.m. and were still out when he returned
from  picking  up  his  niece  at  around  3  p.m.  Martin  and
Burks  eventually  reappeared  together  some  time  before
6:30 p.m.  Martin then handed Frank Bradley a “brown pa-
per bag” and told him to “get rid of this.”  Id., at 353a.  The
State  suggested  that  this  bag  contained  the  hit  weapon,
which  was  never  found.    Neither  did  police  ever  find  the
.380-caliber  pistol  that,  according  to  federal  firearms  rec-
ords and witness testimony, Martin owned.

In addition to all this evidence, Sheri Carter, another of
Martin’s girlfriends, testified for the State.  Carter said that
Martin had kept at her home a laptop that he said he had
obtained  from  a  former  employer.  She  testified  that  she
had seen Martin “looking up gun silencers” on this laptop
not long before the shooting.  Id., at 377a.  Martin, she as-
serted, took the laptop from her apartment after the shoot-
ing and “got rid of it” “in case [the] apartment got searched,”
because he “didn’t want it found there.”  Id., at 378a–379a.
The trial judge instructed the jury that Martin could be
found  guilty  if  he  had  “ ‘aided’ ”  or  “ ‘encouraged’ ”  the  at-
tempted murder and assault with the intent that the crime
succeed.  Id., at 79a.  The jury found him guilty as an acces-
sory  before  the  fact.  The  court  sentenced  him  to  life  in
prison,  and  his  conviction  and  sentence  were  affirmed  on
direct appeal.  Martin, 218 Md. App. 1, 96 A. 3d 765.


6

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

B
Martin  then  sought  postconviction  relief  in  state  court.
He argued that the State had violated his right to due pro-
cess  by  failing  to  disclose  a  forensic  report  that  had  ana-
lyzed five computers found at his home.  One of these ma-
chines,  a  laptop,  had  been  issued  to  Martin  by  a  former
employer.  The  report  found  no  evidence  that  this  laptop
had  been  used  since  2005,  and  it  noted  that  a  keyword
search  for  words  such  as  “ ‘Handgun,’ ”  “ ‘Gatorade,’ ”  “ ‘si-
lencer,’ ”  and  “ ‘Homemade  silencer’ ”  had  yielded  no  hits.
App. 103a–104a.

Martin argued that this computer was the one to which
Carter  had  referred  in  her  testimony  and  that  the  report
tended to discredit her claim that he had used the laptop at
her  home  to  research  silencers.    The  postconviction  court
agreed and ordered a new trial, but a unanimous panel of
the  Maryland  Court  of  Special  Appeals  reversed  on  the
ground that the report was not material.  Based on its re-
view of the whole record, the court concluded that even if
the report had “totally discredit[ed]” Carter, the other evi-
dence linking Martin to the crime was so “strong” that there
was  no  “reasonable  probability  that  the  result  of  his  trial
would have been different.”  Id., at 112a, 115a.  The State’s
high court denied review, Martin v. State, 466 Md. 554, 222
A. 3d 1075 (2020) (table), as did this Court, see Martin v.
Maryland, 590 U. S. 973 (2020).

C
Martin sought habeas relief in federal court, and the Dis-
trict Court granted his petition based on the State’s failure
to disclose the forensic report.  A sharply divided panel of
the  Fourth  Circuit  affirmed.    The  majority  acknowledged
that the state appellate court had correctly stated the rule
on materiality set out in our decisions and had claimed to
apply that rule.  Yet the majority concluded that the state
court had not actually done what it said it did—had not held


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

7

Per Curiam

that there was no “reasonable probability” that the disclo-
sure of the forensic report would have changed the verdict—
but instead had applied the sufficiency-of-the-evidence rule
that we condemned in Kyles.  App. 21a–22a; see 514 U. S.,
at  434–435  (a  Brady  claimant  need  not  show  that,  “after
discounting the inculpatory evidence in light of the undis-
closed evidence, there would not have been enough left to
convict”).  According to the majority, the state court “never
engaged”  with  some  evidence,  “disregarded  or  miscon-
strued” other evidence, and failed to assess in a “nuanced”
way the evidence it did discuss.  App. 24a–26a.  The major-
ity then ruled that no fairminded jurist could agree with the
state court’s decision.  Id., at 27a.

Judge Niemeyer dissented, contending that the majority

had defied AEDPA’s standard of review.

II
A
As we have noted many times, AEDPA sharply limits fed-
eral review of habeas claims raised by state prisoners.  A
federal court may grant habeas relief on a claim that a state
court resolved on the merits only when the state court’s “de-
cision” was “contrary to, or involved an unreasonable appli-
cation of, clearly established Federal law,” or “was based on
an unreasonable determination of the facts in light of the
evidence  presented”  in  state  court.  28  U. S. C.  §2254(d).
These standards require federal courts to give the “benefit
of the doubt” to merits decisions issued by the courts of the
sovereign  States.  Woodford  v.  Visciotti,  537  U. S.  19,  24
(2002) (per curiam).  AEDPA review provides an important
but  limited  safeguard:  It  protects  against  “ ‘extreme  mal-
functions’ ” in the state courts’ adjudication of constitutional
claims.  Harrington v. Richter, 562 U. S. 86, 102 (2011).  So
in  order  to  obtain  federal  habeas  relief,  a  state  prisoner
must “show far more” than “ ‘clear error.’ ”  Shinn v. Kayer,
592  U. S.  111,  118  (2020)  (per curiam)  (quoting  LeBlanc,


8

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

582 U. S., at 94).  The habeas claimant must instead estab-
lish  that  the  state  court  “blunder[ed]  so  badly  that  every
fairminded jurist would disagree” with the decision.  Mays,
592 U. S., at 392.  Only then is a decision “so lacking in jus-
tification” that its error precludes even the “possibility for
fairminded” dispute.  Richter, 562 U. S., at 103.

“If this rule means anything,” we have said, it means that
a federal court must “carefully consider all the reasons and
evidence supporting the state court’s decision.”  Mays, 592
U. S., at 391.  That requirement is pivotal because federal
courts  have  “no  authority  to  impose  mandatory  opinion-
writing  standards  on  state  courts.”  Johnson  v.  Williams,
568 U. S. 289, 300 (2013).  And a state court “need not make
detailed findings addressing all the evidence before it.”  Mil-
ler-El  v.  Cockrell,  537  U. S.  322,  347  (2003).    Indeed,
AEDPA requires deference even if the state court does not
discuss the evidence at all.  Richter, 562 U. S., at 99.  What
matters under §2254(d)(1)—the standard relevant here—is
whether a decision is contrary to, or involves an unreason-
able application of, this Court’s holdings, not whether the
state  court’s  opinion  satisfies  the  federal  court’s  opinion-
writing standards.

B
The panel majority contravened these well-settled princi-
ples  in  two  ways.  First,  it  grounded  its  holding  that  the
state appellate court applied the wrong legal rule on its con-
clusion that the state court had not actually applied the ma-
teriality  test  that  it  clearly  invoked.    Second,  it  erred  in
holding that no fairminded jurist could find the forensic re-
port on the computer to be immaterial.

1
The  panel majority  first  erred  in  holding  that  the  state
appellate court failed to apply the right rule for Brady ma-
teriality.  Undisclosed  evidence  is  material  if  it  could


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

9

Per Curiam

reasonably  have  “ ‘put  the  whole  case  in  such  a  different
light as to undermine confidence in the verdict.’ ”  Strickler
v. Greene, 527 U. S. 263, 290 (1999).  But when the evidence
could not have reasonably had such an effect, it is not ma-
terial, and its erroneous nondisclosure does not justify re-
lief.  Under this rule, even if undisclosed evidence “entirely
discredit[s]” a prosecution witness, the failure to turn over
the evidence is not material if “considerable” other evidence
“link[s]” the defendant to the crime and the record provides
“strong support” that the defendant would have been con-
victed anyway.  Id., at 292–294.

The state appellate court applied these rules instead of a
sufficiency-of-the-evidence test.  The state court accurately
summarized our Brady precedents, correctly stated the gov-
erning  rule  on  materiality,  and  stated  unequivocally  that
its  decision  was  based  on  that  rule.  It  recounted  salient
trial evidence, acknowledged where the State’s theory of the
case was “attenuated,” and said that the disclosure of the
forensic  report  would  likely  have  eliminated  any  adverse
inference based on the concealment of evidence.  App. 114a–
115a, and n. 14.  It also assumed that the jury would have
“totally discredit[ed]” Carter’s testimony had the State dis-
closed the report.  Id., at 112a.  Yet based on its review of
the  “ ‘entire  record,’ ”  the  court  found  that  the  evidence
“linking” Martin to the crime was so “strong” that there was
no “reasonable probability that the result of his trial would
have been different.”  Id., at 109a–110a, 112a, 115a.  That
standard was legally correct.  And except when it was quot-
ing  our  precedent,  the  state  court  did  not  use  words  like
“sufficient,”  “insufficient,”  “adequate,”  or  “inadequate”  in
analyzing the Brady claim.

The panel majority nonetheless held that the state appel-
late court applied the wrong rule because that court failed
to  discuss  certain  evidence  that  tended  to  undermine  the
State’s  case  and  because  its  analysis  was  not  sufficiently
“nuanced.”  App.  24a–26a.  That  holding  was  a  basic


10

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

misapplication  of  AEDPA,  which  bars  federal  courts  from
imposing opinion-writing standards on state courts and de-
mands  that  the  relevant  state-court  decision be  given  the
“benefit of the doubt.”  Woodford, 537 U. S., at 24.  The ma-
jority’s “readiness to attribute error” to the state appellate
court despite that court’s correct citation and synthesis of
our precedent was both “inconsistent with the presumption
that state courts know and follow the law” and “incompati-
ble with §2254(d)’s ‘highly deferential standard for evaluat-
ing state-court rulings.’ ”  Ibid. (quoting Lindh v. Murphy,
521 U. S. 320, 333, n. 7 (1997)).

2
a
The panel majority also went astray in holding that every
fairminded jurist would find that the undisclosed forensic
report  about  Martin’s  laptop  was  material.  On  the  con-
trary,  the  record  contains  “strong  support”  for  the  state
court’s conclusion that Martin “would have been convicted”
even  if  the  forensic  report  “severely  impeached”  Carter.
Strickler, 527 U. S., at 294.

DNA  evidence  tied  Martin  tightly  to  the  modified  Ga-
torade  bottled  that  resembled  a  homemade  silencer  and
that had apparently been used in the shooting.  Evidence
also suggested that Martin was present when the bottle was
modified.  Michael Bradley testified that shortly before the
shooting Martin was in the room to which Frank Bradley
brought both a Gatorade bottle and tape that matched the
white medical tape on the mouth of the bottle found at the
crime scene.

Martin  had  a  strong  motive  for  aiding  the  attempted
murder of Torok: She had refused to get an abortion, had
expressed  her  intent  to  take  him  to  court  to  obtain  child
support, and had threatened to tell his wife about the baby.
On  the  day  of  the  shooting,  Martin  had  texted  Torok  in


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

11

Per Curiam

what a reasonable jury could think was an effort to find a
time when she would be home.

Martin owned the kind of gun that seemed to have been
used to shoot Torok, and multiple witnesses testified that
they had seen him with such a weapon.  Michael Bradley
also  testified  that  Martin  left  McFadden’s  house  not  long
before the hit and that, upon returning, Martin told Frank
Bradley  to  get  rid  of  a  brown  paper  bag  that  Martin  had
been  holding.  Because  the  police  never  found  Martin’s
handgun or the weapon used in the shooting, a reasonable
jury might well have concluded that Martin allowed his gun
to be used and then ensured its disposal.

In light of all this evidence, a fairminded jurist could eas-
ily conclude that the disclosure of the forensic report on the
computer would not have “undercut” the relevance or force
of these “item[s] of the State’s case,” Kyles, 514 U. S., at 451,
or “ ‘put the whole case in such a different light as to under-
mine confidence in the verdict,’ ” Strickler, 527 U. S., at 290.

b
The  panel  majority’s  reasons  for  concluding  otherwise
were  not  consistent  with  the  deference  that  AEDPA  re-
quires.  First, the majority argued that the disclosure of the
report would have bolstered the defense’s primary theory of
the case: that the bottle was a device used to smoke mari-
juana,  not  a  silencer.  But  a  fairminded  jurist  could  find
that theory farfetched.  Among other things, the mouth of
the bottle was covered in tape that looked like it had nestled
the muzzle of a semiautomatic firearm.  The bottle did not
smell like burnt marijuana and bore no trace of controlled
substances.  The outward-punched puncture at the bottom
of the bottle also looked like a bullet hole, and the defense
never  explained  why  anyone  wanting  to  construct  a  bong
would have poked a hole in the bottom of the bottle.

The panel majority ventured that Carter’s testimony was
the  “only  evidence  connecting  Martin  to  his  potential


12

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Per Curiam

construction  of  the  Gatorade  bottle  for  use  as  a  silencer.”
App. 21a.  A fairminded jurist could easily disagree based
on both the bottle itself and Michael Bradley’s eyewitness
testimony about what had occurred upstairs in the McFad-
den house shortly before the shooting.

The  panel  majority  discounted  the  strength  of  the  evi-
dence  against  Martin  because  it  thought  that  strong  evi-
dence linked McFadden to the commission of the crime.  Yet
that theory was inconsistent with the undisputed testimony
that Torok ended her phone call with Wolfe to speak with a
man who was at the door.  Nor did any evidence tie McFad-
den  to  the  Gatorade  bottle  or  the  disposal  of  the  firearm.
And even if McFadden were somehow involved in the crime,
Martin could have been an accessory anyway.  After all, a
fairminded  jurist  could  decide  that  no  evidence  suggests
that  McFadden  knew  about  Torok,  or  had  any  reason  to
want her killed, except through and because of Martin.  See
id., at 439a.

Last, the panel majority voiced serious doubt about Mi-
chael  Bradley’s  credibility,  and  the  defense  certainly  had
material  to  use  in  its  effort  to  convince  the  jury  that  he
should not be believed.  But his testimony about Martin’s
role in the creation of the makeshift silencer was supported
by the DNA evidence, and the jury was able to assess his
credibility firsthand.

Based on all the evidence, a fairminded jurist could easily
conclude that disclosure of the forensic report on the laptop
would not have made a difference.

*

*
We grant the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari, re-
verse the judgment of the Fourth Circuit, and remand the
case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.

*

It is so ordered.


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

13

Per Curiam

 JUSTICE  JACKSON  would  deny  the  petition  for  a  writ  of

certiorari.


14

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Appendix to Per Curiam Opinion

APPENDIX

App. 442a


Cite as:  607 U. S. ____ (2026)

15

Appendix to Per Curiam Opinion

App. 445a


16

KLEIN v. MARTIN

Appendix to Per Curiam Opinion

App. 444a&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10779476/klein-v-martin/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
