<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court of the United States - Recent Decisions</title>
    <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text</link>
    <description>Most recent SCOTUS decisions, generated from Cornell LII.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 18:15:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482"&gt;Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 24-482 argued date: October 14, 2025  decided date: January 20, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main class="container-fluid" id="main"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: center;"&gt; ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="#tab_default_1"&gt;
                        Supreme Court &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'text' content area --&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES&lt;br/&gt;113 F. 4th 839, reversed and remanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syllabus&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-482_SYLLABUS"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Syllabus]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-482.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion&lt;/strong&gt;, Kavanaugh &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-482_OPINION_4"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Kavanaugh Opinion]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-482.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurrence&lt;/strong&gt;, Thomas &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-482_CONCUR_5"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Thomas Concurrence]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-482.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued. The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader. See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Detroit Timber &amp;amp; Lumber Co.,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/200/321"&gt;200 U. S. 321&lt;/a&gt;, 337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center; text-align: justify;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;ELLINGBURG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;UNITED STATES&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the eighth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;No. 24–482. Argued October 14, 2025—Decided  January 20, 2026&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;The Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996 requires defendants convicted of certain federal crimes to pay monetary restitution to victims.  Although petitioner Ellingburg committed his crime &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the MVRA’s enactment, he was sentenced under the MRVA and ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution.  Ellingburg raised an Ex Post Facto Clause challenge to his continued restitution obligation.  The Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Held&lt;/em&gt;: Restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.  Whether a law violates the Ex Post Facto Clause requires evaluating whether the law imposes a criminal or penal sanction as opposed to a civil remedy.  That question is one “of statutory construction” that requires the Court to “consider the statute’s text and its structure.”  &lt;em&gt;Smith &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Doe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/538/84"&gt;538 U. S. 84&lt;/a&gt;, 92 (quotation marks omitted).  When viewed as a whole, the MVRA makes abundantly clear that restitution is criminal punishment.  The MVRA labels restitution as a “penalty” for a criminal “offense.”  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/3663A#a_1"&gt;18 U. S. C. §3663A(a)(1)&lt;/a&gt;.  Only a criminal defendant convicted of a qualifying crime may be ordered to pay restitution.  Restitution is imposed at sentencing for that offense together with other criminal punishments such as imprisonment and fines.  And at the sentencing proceeding where restitution is imposed, the Government, not the victim, is the party adverse to the defendant.  Further, the federal MVRA restitution regime is codified in Title 18, “Crimes and Criminal Procedure,” and the statutory provisions authorizing restitution orders are contained in Chapter 232 of that Title, entitled “Miscellaneous Sentencing Provisions.”  A district court imposing restitution must follow the  procedures applicable to other criminal penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Court’s precedents have understood restitution under the MVRA to be criminal punishment.  See &lt;em&gt;Manrique &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/581/116"&gt;581 U. S. 116&lt;/a&gt;, 118.  And the Court’s precedents on related issues further buttress the conclusion that MVRA restitution is criminal punishment.  See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Bajakajian&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/524/321"&gt;524 U. S. 321&lt;/a&gt;, 328; &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;One Assortment of 89 Firearms&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/465/354"&gt;465 U. S. 354&lt;/a&gt;, 363–366.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Finally, while Congress intended restitution under the MVRA to both punish offenders and compensate victims, victims cannot initiate or settle the restitution process as they would if it were a civil proceeding.  The text and structure of the Act demonstrate that Congress intended restitution under the Act to impose criminal punishment.  Pp. 2–5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;113 F. 4th 839, reversed and remanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Kavanaugh, J., &lt;/span&gt;delivered the opinion for a unanimous Court.  &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., filed a concurring opinion, in which &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Gorsuch&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;J.,&lt;/span&gt; joined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the United States Reports. Readers are requested to notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Washington, D. C. 20543, pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–482&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;HOLSEY ELLINGBURG, JR., PETITIONER  &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the eighth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Kavanaugh&lt;/span&gt; delivered the opinion of the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Under the Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996, defendants convicted of certain federal crimes must pay monetary restitution to the victims.  That Act, known as the MVRA, became law on April 24, 1996.  Petitioner Ellingburg was sentenced later in 1996 and ordered to pay restitution in the amount of $7,567.25.  He has not yet satisfied that obligation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Ellingburg has now raised an Ex Post Facto Clause challenge to his continued restitution obligation because he committed his crime &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the enactment of the MVRA.  The Ex Post Facto Clause issue turns in part on the threshold question of whether restitution under the MVRA is criminal punishment.  Applying Circuit precedent, the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment.  113 F. 4th 839, 841–842 (2024).  We now reverse. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In this Court, Ellingburg and the United States agree that the Eighth Circuit erred and that MVRA restitution is criminal punishment.  The Court therefore appointed John F. Bash as &lt;em&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/em&gt; to defend the judgment of the  Eighth Circuit.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/605/908"&gt;605 U. S. 908 (2025)&lt;/a&gt;.  He has ably discharged his responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When determining whether a law violates the Ex Post Facto Clause, the Court must evaluate whether the law imposes a criminal or penal sanction as opposed to a civil remedy.  Assessing whether “a statutory scheme is civil or criminal is first of all a question of statutory construction” that requires the Court to “consider the statute’s text and its structure.”  &lt;em&gt;Smith &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Doe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/538/84"&gt;538 U. S. 84&lt;/a&gt;, 92 (2003) (quotation marks omitted).&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Here, the statutory analysis is straightforward:  Restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Numerous features of the MVRA lead to that conclusion.  The MVRA labels restitution as a “penalty” for a criminal “offense.”  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/3663A#a_1"&gt;18 U. S. C. §3663A(a)(1)&lt;/a&gt;.  A court may order restitution only with respect to a criminal “defendant” and only after that defendant’s conviction of a qualifying crime.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Restitution is imposed during “sentencing” for the offense.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.  &lt;/em&gt;At the sentencing proceeding where restitution is ordered, the Government, not the victim, is the party adverse to the defendant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; At sentencing, restitution is imposed together with other criminal punishments such as imprisonment and fines.  Indeed, for misdemeanors, restitution may be “in lieu of ” those punishments, making restitution the sole  punishment for a federal offense in certain circumstances.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  In addition, when a defendant does not make the required restitution payments, the court may modify the terms of his supervised release or probation and impose imprisonment if the court determines that “alternatives to imprisonment are not adequate to serve the purposes of punishment and deterrence.”  §§3614(b)(2), 3613A(a)(1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As a further sign that MVRA restitution is criminal punishment, the federal MVRA restitution regime is codified in Title 18, “Crimes and Criminal Procedure.”  The main statutory provisions authorizing restitution orders, §3663 and §3663A, are contained in Chapter 232 of Title 18, entitled “Miscellaneous Sentencing Provisions.”  Another statutory provision, §3556, states that a court “shall order restitution” in “imposing a sentence” for covered offenses.  That provision is housed in Chapter 227 of Title 18, entitled “Sentences.”  The statute also refers to a “sentence that imposes an order of restitution.”  §3664(o).  When imposing restitution, a district court must follow the procedures applicable to other criminal penalties, including the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure.  See §3664(c).  And §3663(c) directs the U. S. Sentencing Commission to promulgate criminal sentencing guidelines for restitution.  §208, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/110_Stat._1240"&gt;110 Stat. 1240&lt;/a&gt;; §3663(c)(7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When viewed as a whole, then, the MVRA makes abundantly clear that restitution is criminal punishment.  We are not saying that all of the statutory features present here are necessary to constitute criminal punishment, but they are sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  Given the statutory text and structure, it comes as no surprise that this Court’s precedents have understood restitution under the MVRA to be criminal punishment.  In &lt;em&gt;Manrique &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, the Court stated that the MVRA requires courts “to impose restitution as part of the sentence.”  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/581/116"&gt;581 U. S. 116&lt;/a&gt;, 118 (2017).  In &lt;em&gt;Pasquantino&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, the Court explained that restitution under  the MVRA is designed “to mete out appropriate criminal punishment.”  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/544/349"&gt;544 U. S. 349&lt;/a&gt;, 365 (2005).  And in &lt;em&gt;Paroline&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, the Court repeated that description.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/572/434"&gt;572 U. S. 434&lt;/a&gt;, 456 (2014). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;This Court’s precedents on related issues further buttress the conclusion that MVRA restitution is criminal punishment.  For example, forfeiture under &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/982#a_1"&gt;18 U. S. C. §982(a)(1)&lt;/a&gt;—like restitution under the MVRA—occurs at the culmination of a criminal proceeding and requires conviction of an underlying crime.  That forfeiture, the Court concluded, is criminal punishment.  See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Bajakajian&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/524/321"&gt;524 U. S. 321&lt;/a&gt;, 328 (1998).  By contrast, the Court determined that the forfeiture of firearms under &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/924#d"&gt;18 U. S. C. §924(d)&lt;/a&gt; ordered during an &lt;em&gt;in rem&lt;/em&gt; proceeding is a civil sanction.  &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;One Assortment of 89 Firearms&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/465/354"&gt;465 U. S. 354&lt;/a&gt;, 363–366 (1984).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As the Government cautions, not everything that occurs at criminal sentencing or even that appears in a criminal judgment may necessarily be part of the punishment.  See Tr. of Oral Arg. 22–23.  But we need not explore that point further here because, for the reasons we have explained, MVRA restitution is criminal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; Amicus&lt;/em&gt; relies heavily on &lt;em&gt;Smith &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Doe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/538/84"&gt;538 U. S. 84&lt;/a&gt;.  There, this Court considered a law requiring a defendant convicted of certain crimes to register as a sex offender.  The Court held that the registration mandate was civil.  The legislature adopted “distinctly civil procedures” for the imposition of registration requirements.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 96 (quotation marks omitted).    By contrast, to reiterate what we said above, MVRA restitution is labeled as a penalty, is codified in the criminal code, is predicated on a criminal conviction, is imposed against a criminal defendant, is sometimes imposed in lieu of other penalties, is ordered at sentencing where the United States is the adverse party, and can result in resentencing when the defendant refuses to pay.  So &lt;em&gt;Smith &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Doe &lt;/em&gt;does not control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  It is true, as &lt;em&gt;amicus&lt;/em&gt; thoroughly explains, that the MVRA seeks to compensate crime victims, a nonpunitive goal.  Several provisions of the MVRA reflect that objective, such as a provision requiring that restitution amounts be based on a victim’s loss.  §3664(f )(1)(A); see also, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., §3664(j).  But those provisions show only that Congress intended restitution under the MVRA to both punish and compensate.  And so long as the text and structure of the Act demonstrate that Congress intended at least “to impose punishment,” that “ends the inquiry.”  &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 92; see &lt;em&gt;Paroline&lt;/em&gt;, 572 U. S., at 456; &lt;em&gt;Pasquantino&lt;/em&gt;, 544 U. S., at 365.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; To be sure, as &lt;em&gt;amicus &lt;/em&gt;points out, victims receive notice of sentencing proceedings and are consulted by prosecutors.  But outreach to victims and some participation by victims in criminal proceedings are not unusual.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., §3771(a).  With respect to restitution, the key point is that victims do not have the power to initiate or settle the restitution process as they would if it were a civil proceeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Our ruling today does not mean that a restitution statute can never be civil.  But the statutory text and structure of the MVRA demonstrate that restitution under that Act is criminal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; For those reasons, we reverse the judgment of the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit and remand the case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.  On remand, the Court of Appeals may consider the Government’s separate arguments for affirmance of the District Court’s judgment.        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;     It is so ordered.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  If the text and structure of a statute do not demonstrate that Congress intended criminal punishment, the statute may still be deemed criminal or penal if the “party challenging the statute provides ‘the clearest proof’ that ‘the statutory scheme [is] so punitive either in purpose or effect as to negate [the Government’s] intention’ to deem it ‘civil.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Kansas&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hendricks&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/521/346"&gt;521 U. S. 346&lt;/a&gt;, 361 (1997) (quoting &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Ward&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/448/242"&gt;448 U. S. 242&lt;/a&gt;, 248–249 (1980)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Amicus&lt;/em&gt; contends that Ellingburg’s restitution was not imposed under the MVRA even though Ellingburg was sentenced after the MVRA took effect in 1996.  But the Eighth Circuit decided this case on the understanding that the MVRA was applied to Ellingburg.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Concurrence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–482&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;HOLSEY ELLINGBURG, JR., PETITIONER  &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the eighth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, with whom &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Justice Gorsuch&lt;/span&gt; joins, concurring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; I join the Court’s opinion in full because it correctly applies our precedent.  I write separately to clarify the foundation of that precedent.  This Court’s 1798 decision in &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt;, 3 Dall. 386, established that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses forbid only those retroactive laws that impose “punishment” for a “crime.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 386, 389–391 (opinion of Chase, J.).  Over the 228 years since &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;, the Court has struggled to articulate what it means for a law to impose punishment for a crime, and thus to be subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses.  The Court’s more recent precedents have implemented &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;through two multifactor tests that turn largely on whether the legislature labels the law as criminal or civil.  But in 1798, “punishment” for a “crime” would have been understood to refer to any coercive penalty for a public wrong.  Many laws that are nominally civil today would therefore have been subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses under &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;.  I would restore &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s approach to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Constitution twice prohibits &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws.  As to the Federal Government, it provides that “No Bill of Attainder or ex post facto Law shall be passed.”  Art. I, §9, cl. 3.   As to the States, it provides that “No State shall . . . pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts.”  Art. I, §10, cl. 1.  In its general sense, a law is &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt;—meaning “after the fact”—when it applies retroactively to conduct that occurred before the law was enacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The two &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses reflected the importance of the protection to the Founding Fathers.  James Iredell believed that the protection against &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws was “the most essential right of all,” which was worth “ten thousand declarations of rights” without it.  Answers to Mr. Mason’s Objections to the New Constitution, in Pamphlets on the Constitution of the United States 334, 368 (P. Ford ed. 1888) (reprint 1968).  “A man may feel some pride in his security,” Iredell wrote, “when he knows that what he does innocently and safely to-day in accordance with the laws of his country, cannot be tortured into guilt and danger to-morrow.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  In the Federalist Papers, Alexander Hamilton placed “the prohibition of &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws” among the greatest “securities to liberty and republicanism.”  The Federalist No. 84, p. 571 (P. Ford ed. 1898).  James Madison argued that &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws are “contrary to the first principles of the social compact.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., No. 44, at 296.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws lack legitimacy because laws must precede the actions that they govern.  Laws regulating actions after the fact “deprive citizens of notice and fair warning and are, therefore, an affront to man’s ‘reason and freewill.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Peugh&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/569/530"&gt;569 U. S. 530&lt;/a&gt;, 561 (2013) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., dissenting) (quoting 1 W. Blackstone, Commentaries on the Laws of England 39 (1765) (Blackstone)).  As Blackstone explained, “it is impossible that the party could foresee” that his actions would become unlawful if they were lawful when he took them.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 46.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;When a man had no notice that his actions were unlawful, “all punishment for not abstaining must of consequence be cruel and unjust.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  An &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; law is even “more  unreasonable,” Blackstone thought, than the reviled practice of the Roman emperor “Caligula, who . . . wrote his laws in a very small character, and hung them up upon high pillars, the more effectually to ensnare the people.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Many believed that no constitutional prohibition was necessary because an &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; law would be invalid as contrary to natural law.  At the Constitutional Convention, Oliver Ellsworth argued that “[i]t cannot . . . be necessary to prohibit” &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws because “no lawyer, no civilian . . . would not say that ex post facto laws were void of themselves.”  2 M. Farrand, Records of the Federal Convention of 1787, p. 376 (1966) (Farrand).  James Wilson thought that a constitutional prohibition on &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws would suggest that the Convention denied that such laws were already forbidden by natural law, to its embarrassment.  “It will bring reflexions on the Constitution—and proclaim that we are ignorant of the first principles of Legislation.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  In fact, “[a]ll the delegates who spoke explicitly or implicitly regarded an ex post facto law as a violation of natural law, and most of them therefore thought it unnecessary to include such a basic natural law principle in the written constitution.”  S. Sherry, The Founders’ Unwritten Constitution, 54 U. Chi. L. Rev. 1127, 1157 (1987).  The Convention nonetheless adopted the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses after it was urged that “the Judges can take hold of ” them if a legislature ever enacts such a law.  2 Farrand 376 (Williamson).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The lodestar of this Court’s &lt;em&gt;ex post facto &lt;/em&gt;jurisprudence is &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt;, which established that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses apply only to laws that impose “punishment” for “crime[s].”  3 Dall., at 389–391.  &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;—and especially Justice Chase’s lead &lt;em&gt;seriatim&lt;/em&gt; opinion—has since provided the definitive gloss on the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses.  Justice Chase’s definition of “&lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; laws” continues to  “provid[e] an authoritative account of the scope of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clause.”  &lt;em&gt;Stogner &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;California&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/539/607"&gt;539 U. S. 607&lt;/a&gt;, 611 (2003); accord, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Peugh&lt;/em&gt;, 569 U. S., at 532–533.  This Court’s modern precedents, including today’s opinion, decide whether a law is subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses based on whether it satisfies &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s requirement that it be “criminal or penal.”  &lt;em&gt;Weaver&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Graham&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/450/24"&gt;450 U. S. 24&lt;/a&gt;, 29 (1981); see also &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 2.  But this Court’s implementation of &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;seems to have lost sight of how &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; would have been understood when it was decided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;concerned a state legislature’s intervention in a traditional private-law dispute.  The case&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;arose out of the probate proceedings for the estate of a Connecticut man named Normand Morison.  In 1779, Morison wrote a will leaving his property to his wife Abigail and her heirs.  See 8 The Documentary History of the Supreme Court of the United States, 1789–1800, p. 89 (M. Marcus ed. 2007).  Soon after Morison wrote his will, he and Abigail had a son.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  When the son was young, Morison died.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Abigail started the probate process so that she could inherit Morison’s property as his will promised.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  But the probate judge held up the process because he wanted to check whether the birth of their son affected the will’s validity.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  At the time, Abigail did not mind the delay because the default intestacy rules would have given the property to her and her son anyway.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 89–90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; But later events jeopardized Abigail’s right to inherit Morison’s property.  First, Connecticut changed the default intestacy rules so that, absent a valid will, property like Morison’s would pass to his nearest blood relative, not to a surviving spouse like Abigail.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 90, and n. 9.  Second, the probate court, without telling Abigail, disapproved Morison’s original will.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 90.  And third, a few years later, Abigail and Morison’s son died.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  After her son died, Abigail and her new husband Caleb Bull returned to probate court.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  The Bulls were surprised to learn that the  probate court had disapproved Morison’s will years earlier without telling Abigail—apparently on the theory that he would have wanted to change it after his son was born.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  And, since Connecticut had enacted new default intestacy rules in the meantime, the absence of a valid will meant that Morison’s estate would pass on to his blood relatives rather than to Abigail.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Morison’s blood relatives, the Calders, were suddenly the lawful heirs of his property.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 90–91.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Abigail and Caleb Bull petitioned the Connecticut Legislature for relief.  They convinced the legislature that Morison did not intend to revoke his will after his son died, so the legislature issued a decree in 1795 granting them a rehearing on the validity of Morison’s original will.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 91.  The legislature’s 1795 decree effectively vacated the original probate-court decision deeming the will void and granted a new hearing at which the probate court could adjudicate the will’s validity.  &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 91, 107.  The probate court held a new hearing pursuant to the decree and concluded that Morison’s original will was valid after all. &lt;em&gt; Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 91.  Having now lost in probate court, the Calders appealed this new decision and challenged the legislature’s decree that had granted the Bulls a new hearing.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 91–92.  The Calders argued, eventually to this Court, that the legislature’s decree was an unconstitutional &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; law because it retroactively voided the probate court’s original decision, which caused them to lose an inheritance that would otherwise have been theirs.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 92.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt;, this Court gave two reasons why the legislature’s decree granting a new trial did not violate the State &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clause.  See Art. I, §10, cl. 1.  The first reason was that the legislature’s decree operated on a legal decision by a court, not a past action by the Calders.  There was nothing that the parties had done in the past that was “in any manner affected by the law or resolution of Connecticut.”  3 Dall., at 392 (opinion of Chase, J.).  “It does not &lt;em&gt;concern&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;relate&lt;/em&gt; to, &lt;em&gt;any act done by them&lt;/em&gt;.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Instead, the decree effectively vacated a probate decision and gave the court an opportunity to correct its decision, just like appellate courts do every day.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  The new hearing, after all, was conducted under the same substantive laws as were in force at the original hearing.  In fact, the Justices seemed to believe that the Connecticut Legislature’s “resolution or law,” &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 387, was not a legislative but a judicial act, consistent with state legislatures’ traditional judicial power to review state-court decisions—and thus could not be an &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; “law” at all.  See &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 395–396 (opinion of Paterson, J.) (“[W]e may, in the present instance, consider the Legislature of the State, as having acted in their customary judicial capacity”); &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 398 (opinion of Iredell, J.) (“an exercise of judicial, not of legislative, authority”); &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 400 (opinion of Cushing, J.) (“If the act is a judicial act, it is not touched by the Federal Constitution”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The more lasting legacy of &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;, however, was its second reason.  Three of the four &lt;em&gt;seriatim&lt;/em&gt; opinions in &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; limited the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses to laws imposing criminal punishment.  On their view, the Clauses did not forbid other kinds of retroactive laws.  Justice Chase, in what has proved to be the most influential opinion, gave a comprehensive account of the scope of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses.  He understood the Clauses to be limited to retroactive laws imposing criminal punishment.  He explained that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses covered only those laws that “&lt;em&gt;create&lt;/em&gt;” a “&lt;em&gt;crime&lt;/em&gt;,” “&lt;em&gt;aggravate&lt;/em&gt;” a crime, “encrease the punishment” for a crime, or “change the rules of evidence, &lt;em&gt;for the purpose of conviction&lt;/em&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 391.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Justice Chase’s account implied that the Clauses did not apply to other kinds of retroactive laws.  First, on his view, the Clauses did not touch private law.  Justice Chase did “not think” that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clause “was inserted to Secure the citizen in his &lt;em&gt;private rights&lt;/em&gt;, of either &lt;em&gt;property&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;contracts&lt;/em&gt;.”  &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 390.  Accordingly, the Clauses would not  prohibit a law that retroactively paused a debtor’s obligations to a creditor or voided a contract.  Such laws, in Justice Chase’s view, were governed by separate constitutional prohibitions on impairing the obligations of contracts and making anything but gold or silver a tender in payments of debts.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.; see Art. I, §10, cl. 1.  Second, because the Clauses were meant as protections against the government, they did not apply to laws that retroactively made a law more lenient.  They would not, for example, forbid a law that retroactively “mollifies the rigor of the &lt;em&gt;criminal&lt;/em&gt; law.”  &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;, 3 Dall., at 391 (opinion of Chase, J.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The other two &lt;em&gt;seriatim&lt;/em&gt; opinions in &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;that addressed the question agreed.  Justice Paterson explained that “the meaning, annexed to the terms &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;laws&lt;/em&gt;, unquestionably refers to crimes, and nothing else.”  &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 396.  Justice Iredell—an adamant proponent of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses, see &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt;, at 2—likewise thought that they did not “extend to civil cases, to cases that merely affect the private property of citizens.”  &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;, 3 Dall., at 400.  Instead, the Clauses applied only to laws that retroactively “inflict a punishment” for an “offence.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Some, myself included, have questioned whether &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;was right to limit the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses to laws imposing criminal punishment.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Satterlee&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Matthewson&lt;/em&gt;, 2 Pet. 380, 416, and n. (a) (1829) (opinion of Johnson, J.) (arguing that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses protect more); O. Field, Ex Post Facto in the Constitution, 20 Mich. L. Rev. 315, 331 (1922) (“[T]here have been reputable authorities, both past and present, who incline to the view that the &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; provisions of the Constitution prohibited civil as well as criminal legislation”); &lt;em&gt;Eastern Enterprises&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Apfel&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/524/498"&gt;524 U. S. 498&lt;/a&gt;, 538–539 (1998) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., concurring).  Others have defended &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s limitation.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., R. Natelson, Statutory Retroactivity: The Founders’ View, 39 Idaho L. Rev. 489, 493–494 (2003); C. Nelson, Originalism and Interpretive Conventions, 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 519, 578– 582 (2003).  But often lost in that debate has been the question of what &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; meant when it limited the Clauses to laws imposing criminal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This Court’s recent precedents have attempted to implement &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s limitation of the Clauses to criminal punishment.  But, in doing so, they have adopted a framework that turns largely on legislative labeling, has little basis in history, and is unnecessarily convoluted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The modern precedents follow &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s limitation of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses to laws that impose criminal punishment.  Based on “Justice Chase’s now familiar opinion in &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;,” this Court has repeatedly held that the Clauses apply exclusively to laws that “retroactively alter the definition of crimes or increase the punishment for criminal acts,” but not to other kinds of retroactive laws.  &lt;em&gt;Collins&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Youngblood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/497/37"&gt;497 U. S. 37&lt;/a&gt;, 41–43 (1990); see also, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Kansas&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hendricks&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/521/346"&gt;521 U. S. 346&lt;/a&gt;, 370 (1997); &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Doe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/538/84"&gt;538 U. S. 84&lt;/a&gt;, 92 (2003).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; But in defining criminal punishment—and thus the scope of &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s limitation—the Court’s modern framework applies two multifactor tests developed in the 20th century.  The first multifactor test asks whether the legislature “intended” the law to be viewed as criminal or penal.  &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 92–93; see also &lt;em&gt;ante&lt;/em&gt;, at 2, n. 1.  Under this test, a law is subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses “[i]f the intention of the legislature was to impose punishment.”  &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 92.  But if “the intention was to enact a regulatory scheme that is civil and nonpunitive,” then a law is presumptively not subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  This test has included up to five factors, most of which allow a legislature to avoid the Clauses through labeling or semantics.  Those five factors are whether the legislature  had a “ ‘preference’ ” for “ ‘one label or the other,’ ” &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 93 (quoting &lt;em&gt;Hudson &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/522/93"&gt;522 U. S. 93&lt;/a&gt;, 99 (1997)); whether the “codification” was in the criminal or civil code, &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;94; whether legislative history or similar indicators suggested nonpunitive goals, &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;One Assortment of 89 Firearms&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/465/354"&gt;465 U. S. 354&lt;/a&gt;, 364 (1984); whether the legislature provided traditional “safeguards associated with the criminal process,” &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 96; and whether the legislature gave enforcement power to an agency with power to enforce civil laws, &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The second multifactor test, which applies only if the law survives the first test, asks whether the law’s other features render it criminal or penal.  See &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 92.  Under this second test, a law is subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses if it is “so punitive either in purpose or effect as to negate [the legislature’s] intention to deem it civil.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;. (internal quotation marks omitted).  The Court has at times said that this second test is a function of up to seven factors: whether the law involves an affirmative disability or restraint, imposes what has historically been regarded as a punishment, requires a finding of scienter, promotes the traditional aims of punishment, applies to behavior which is already a crime, lacks a rational alternative purpose, or is excessive in relation to that purpose.  &lt;em&gt;Kennedy&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Mendoza-Martinez&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/372/144"&gt;372 U. S. 144&lt;/a&gt;, 168–169 (1963); see &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 97 (explaining that &lt;em&gt;Mendoza-Martinez &lt;/em&gt;factors “migrated” to &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; jurisprudence).  So long as a law survives the first test, “ ‘only the clearest proof ’ ” under the second test can make it subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses.  &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 92 (quoting &lt;em&gt;Hudson&lt;/em&gt;, 522 U. S., at 100).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This modern framework is incongruous with the historical purpose of &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses.  The modern framework, because of how much it turns on legislative labeling and semantics, allows a legislature to manipulate when the  protection will apply.  Under the first test, for example, a legislature might be able to impose a retroactive $10,000 fine on some previously innocent conduct—such as drinking coffee or going to the gym—if it labeled the law “civil,” placed it in the civil code, expressed a nonpunitive purpose, &lt;em&gt;omitted&lt;/em&gt; protections for the accused, and let non-traditional prosecutors (such as a health agency) enforce it.  See &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt;, at 2–3.  Under the second test, the legislature might be able to prevail by aggravating the fair-notice problems that motivate the Clauses, such as by having its retroactive law impose strict liability and then applying it only to previously innocent conduct.  See &lt;em&gt;Mendoza-Martinez&lt;/em&gt;, 372 U. S., at 168–169.  It is unlikely that a constitutional prohibition designed to curb a “cruel and unjust” legislature, 1 Blackstone 46, can be so easily manipulated by the same legislature.  See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Rahimi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/602/680"&gt;602 U. S. 680&lt;/a&gt;, 776 (2024) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., dissenting) (explaining that the Constitution does not “allow . . . majoritarian interests to determine” the scope of “constitutional rights”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The modern framework is also convoluted.  It is difficult for courts, let alone ordinary citizens, to predict how this Court will weigh the modern framework’s combined twelve factors spread over two tests.  This Court’s own precedents admit that the twelve factors are “neither exhaustive nor dispositive,” &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Ward&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/448/242"&gt;448 U. S. 242&lt;/a&gt;, 249 (1980), and need not be given equal weights, &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 105.  Such “multifactor balancing test[s]” invite “policy-driven, ‘arbitrary discretion.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Gamble&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/587/678"&gt;587 U. S. 678&lt;/a&gt;, 724 (2019) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., concurring).  We should strive to avoid such unclear rules in any context, but especially when interpreting a constitutional guarantee of clear notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;IV&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;said that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses apply only to laws imposing punishment for crimes, it was  referring to an established category of laws.  A crime meant a “public wrong,” which is an injury to the sovereign in its sovereign capacity&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; therefore encompassed offenses against the sovereign regardless of whether they were nominally criminal or civil.  And punishment simply referred to the law’s coercive sanction—meaning a traditional deprivation of life, liberty, or property—redressing that public wrong.  Applying this understanding would restore the Clauses to their proper role without the problems attendant to the more recent precedents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The English common law divided all unlawful acts into “private wrongs” and “public wrongs.”  See 3 Blackstone 2.  Blackstone titled the third and fourth volumes of his Commentaries, respectively, “Of Private Wrongs” and “Of Public Wrongs.”  This dichotomy was fundamental to English and American law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Public wrongs were injuries to the sovereign.  A public wrong was “a breach and violation of public rights and duties, which affect the whole community, considered as a community.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Because a public wrong injured the community, it was deemed an injury to the sovereign in his sovereign capacity.  4 Blackstone 2–7.  It followed that an action to redress a public wrong was brought on behalf of the sovereign, not the victim.  J. Locke, Second Treatise of Civil Government 7 (J. Gough ed. 1948) (Locke).  In concrete terms, actions for public wrongs were brought in England on behalf of the King, and here on behalf of the State or the United States—typically by public prosecutors, rather than privately by the victims.  The sovereign “is supposed by the law to be the person injured by every infraction of the public rights belonging to that community, and is therefore in all cases the proper prosecutor for every public offense.”  4 Blackstone 2; see also &lt;em&gt;Robertson&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States ex rel. Watson&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/560/272"&gt;560 U. S. 272&lt;/a&gt;, 279 (2010) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Roberts&lt;/span&gt;, C. J.,  dissenting) (a criminal prosecution is an action “on behalf of the sovereign, seeking to vindicate a public wrong”).  Public wrongs included all wrongs deemed injuries to the sovereign and redressable by the sovereign, from murder to mayhem to public nuisance.  4 Blackstone 5–6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Private wrongs, in contrast, were injuries to individuals in their private capacity.  An action inflicted a private wrong insofar as it infringed “the private or civil rights belonging to individuals, considered as individuals.”  3 Blackstone 2.  For example, a dispute with a fellow citizen over a land claim or a failure to pay a debt concerned a private wrong.  “[I]f I detain a field from another man, to which the law has given him a right, this is a civil injury, and not a crime,” Blackstone explained, because “only the right of an individual is concerned, and it is immaterial to the public, which of us is in possession of the land.”  4 Blackstone 5.  Private wrongs were redressable by the individuals whose rights were violated, not the sovereign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; A single act could be both a private wrong and a public wrong.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 5–6.  “The same acts will generally constitute a private injury, as well as a public crime.  A public punishment is inflicted on the part of the state, to restrain such conduct, and the party injured is entitled to a compensation for the injury he has sustained.”  2 Z. Swift, System of the Laws of the State of Connecticut 292 (1796); accord &lt;em&gt;ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  (“If one man assaults and beats another, he is punished by a fine for disturbing the peace, and compelled to compensate in money the person he has abused and wounded.”).  The private suit brought by the individual vindicated the private wrong, and the public prosecution brought by the sovereign vindicated the public wrong.  This overlap carries forward to modern law: Theft can be redressed through a tort suit brought by the victim and a criminal prosecution brought by the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When the opinions in &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;spoke of “crimes,” they meant public wrongs.  The prevailing definition of a “crime”  around the time of &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;was “a violation of law to the injury of the public, a public offense.”  N. Webster, A Compendious Dictionary of the English Language 72 (1806) (Webster).  Blackstone used the terms “crimes” and “public wrongs” interchangeably.  See 4 Blackstone 1–5.  His fourth volume covered “public wrongs, or crimes and misdemeanors.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 1.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  The “common-law conception of crime,” this Court has long recognized, was an “offense against the sovereignty of the government.”  &lt;em&gt;Heath&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Alabama&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/474/82"&gt;474 U. S. 82&lt;/a&gt;, 88 (1985).  So &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;limitation of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses to crimes would have originally been understood to include all public wrongs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; Calder &lt;/em&gt;itself confirms this understanding.  Justice Chase distinguished crimes not with nominally civil laws enforced by the sovereign, but with laws that merely “secure[d] &lt;em&gt;private rights&lt;/em&gt;,” like contract laws.  3 Dall., at 390.  Justices Chase and Iredell used “crime” interchangeably with “offence.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 400 (opinion of Iredell, J.).  Justices Chase and Paterson said that their definitions tracked Blackstone’s.  See &lt;em&gt;id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 391 (opinion of Chase, J.) (“&lt;em&gt;Sir William Blackstone&lt;/em&gt;, in his commentaries, considers an &lt;em&gt;ex post facto law&lt;/em&gt; precisely in the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; light I have done.”); &lt;em&gt;id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 396 (opinion of Paterson, J.) (similar).  Justice Iredell explained in a contemporaneous opinion that the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses could be limited to crimes because “there . . . is little reason to apprehend a legislative interference for the sake of unjustly transferring property from one man to another.”  &lt;em&gt;Minge&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Gilmour&lt;/em&gt;, 17 F. Cas. 440, 443, No. 9,631 (CC NC 1798).  And, of course, the occasion for &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s distinction was a probate dispute, where only private rights are implicated.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In turn, when &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;referred to criminal “punishment,” it simply meant whatever coercive sanction—or deprivation of life, liberty, or property—the law imposed as redress for committing those crimes.  Blackstone understood punishment to include the traditional “coercive penalties” that the law imposed as redress for a public wrong.  See 4 Blackstone 7–8.  Dictionaries defined “punishment” broadly as “[a]ny infliction or pain imposed in vengeance of a crime,” S. Johnson, A Dictionary of the English Language (6th ed. 1785), or “any thing inflicted for a crime,” Webster 241.  The power of punishing an offender was the power to harm the offender in a way that was otherwise forbidden: “[N]o one ought to harm another in his life, health, liberty, or possessions”—“&lt;em&gt;unless&lt;/em&gt; it be to do justice on an offender.”  Locke 5 (emphasis added); see also &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 6 (describing when “one man may lawfully do harm to another, which is that we call punishment”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  The &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses therefore prohibit retroactive laws that impose coercive penalties for public wrongs.  Contrary to the modern framework, it does not matter what the legislature labels the law, where it places the law, which agency it vests enforcement with, what its stated goals were, whether it provides safeguards for the accused, whether it requires a showing of scienter, or whether the conduct to which it applies is already a crime.  Contra, &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, 538 U. S., at 96; &lt;em&gt;Martinez-Mendoza&lt;/em&gt;, 372 U. S., at 168–169.  What matters is what the law does.  If it punishes a public wrong—or an injury to the sovereign in its sovereign capacity—then it is subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt;  Clauses.  If it changes merely private relations, such as the rules of contract or property or probate, then it is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Whether a law is subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses will therefore typically depend on how it is enforced.  If it is enforced on behalf of the sovereign to redress a sovereign injury, then it is subject to the Clauses.  See 4 Blackstone 2.  If instead it is enforced by a private person to vindicate his own private rights, then it is not.  In this case, for example, the law was subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses because it was enforced against Ellingburg by the United States, not by the First Union National Bank, whose private rights Ellingburg violated when he robbed it.  And the United States’s action was redressing a sovereign injury to the community as a whole, not a private wrong.  Cf. 3 Blackstone 257 (explaining that the King can bring “common law actions” to redress private wrongs to himself, such as an “action for trespass for taking away his goods”).&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s understanding secures &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clause protection in a wide range of contexts involving nominally civil laws.  Those contexts include civil proceedings seeking fines for public offenses.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Army Corps of Engineers&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hawkes Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/578/590"&gt;578 U. S. 590&lt;/a&gt;, 600 (2016) (describing “civil penalties of up to $37,500 for each day [the challenger] violated the Act”).  They include enforcement proceedings brought by administrative agencies.  See &lt;em&gt;Axon Enterprise, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;FTC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/598/175"&gt;598 U. S. 175&lt;/a&gt;, 196 (2023) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, J., concurring) (describing the 20th-century rise of such proceedings).  And they include municipal sanctions like speeding tickets.  “If  one were to commit a minor traffic offense at a time the offense was to be punished by a $25 fine, and the government were to then amend the statute and impose a fine of $1,000,000 dollars, it would be nonsensical to treat that fine as non-punitive simply because the offense was processed civilly.”  Brief for Professor Beth Colgan as &lt;em&gt;Amicus Curiae&lt;/em&gt; 8, n. 3.  Because all of these offenses impose punishments for public wrongs, &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; would treat them all as subject to the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto&lt;/em&gt; Clauses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This understanding of &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;long prevailed.  Courts took the position that “the relevant line for the Clause’s scope” lay between “punishments imposed in response to public offenses whether prosecuted criminally or civilly on the one hand, and purely private disputes on the other.”  Brief for Professor Beth Colgan as &lt;em&gt;Amicus Curiae &lt;/em&gt;5.  This Court confirmed, contrary to the modern precedents, that “the &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; effect of a law cannot be evaded by giving a civil form to that which is essentially criminal.”  &lt;em&gt;Burgess &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Salmon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/97/381"&gt;97 U. S. 381&lt;/a&gt;, 385 (1878).  The influential commentator Thomas Cooley likewise explained that a “law will be &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; in the constitutional sense” if it “subject[s] an individual to a pecuniary penalty” or “deprives a party of any valuable right” retroactively, even if “it does not in terms declare the acts to which the penalty is attached criminal.”  Constitutional Limitations&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;321 (6th ed. 1890).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In a similar context, when a State sought nominally civil fines against a company for doing business without proper forms, this Court explained that the statute “was in the strictest sense a penal statute.”  &lt;em&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Pelican Ins. Co&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/127/265"&gt;127 U. S. 265&lt;/a&gt;, 299 (1888).  The Court held that the nominally civil statute was penal because “[t]he cause of action was not any private injury, but solely the offence committed against the State by violating her law.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Likewise, “[t]he prosecution was in the name of the State.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.   The Court explained that “[t]he real nature of the case is not affected by the forms provided by the law of the State”; these forms were “immaterial” to whether the law was criminal or penal in a constitutional sense.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Thus, the Court concluded, “[i]n whatever form the State pursues her right to punish the offence against her sovereignty,” an action is criminal or penal in substance whenever it seeks to “compe[l ] the offender to pay a pecuniary fine by way of punishment for the offence.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Other decisions followed the same reasoning.  For example, when the United States brought a nominally civil action for damages based on a public offense, the defendants were entitled to other criminal-procedure protections because the action “was in its nature and essence, though not its form, a penal or criminal action.”  &lt;em&gt;United States &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Poyllon&lt;/em&gt;, 27 F. Cas. 608, 611, No. 16,081 (NY 1812).  And when a statute forbade “any fine or forfeiture under any penal statute,” the statute applied to a nominally civil action for debt on behalf of the sovereign against someone who committed a public offense.  &lt;em&gt;Adams&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Woods&lt;/em&gt;, 2 Cranch 336, 337, 340–341 (1805) (emphases deleted).  Chief Justice Marshall explained that the category of penal laws referred “not to any particular mode of proceeding, but generally to any prosecution, trial, or punishment for the offence.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This understanding of &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; harmonizes the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses with their historical purpose.  It means that the Clauses ensure fair notice against government enforcement actions, regardless of whether the legislature labels them civil.  As &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Justice&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Gorsuch&lt;/span&gt; has explained, today’s “civil” laws “regularly impose penalties far more severe than those found in many criminal statutes.”  &lt;em&gt;Sessions&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Dimaya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/584/148"&gt;584 U. S. 148&lt;/a&gt;, 184 (2018) (opinion concurring in part and concurring in the judgment).  “Today’s ‘civil’ penalties include confiscatory rather than compensatory fines, forfeiture provisions that allow homes to be taken, remedies that strip persons of their professional licenses and  livelihoods, and the power to commit persons against their will indefinitely.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  This understanding also helps reconcile &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;with its critics, many of whom have focused on the injustice of allowing the government to retroactively impose sanctions for public offenses that it deems civil.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., Brief for Professor Wayne A. Logan as &lt;em&gt;Amicus Curiae &lt;/em&gt;31–32; cf. D. Troy, Retroactive Legislation 49–55 (1998).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;This understanding of &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; also simplifies the law.  Rather than making the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clauses’ application depend on twelve factors with indeterminate weights, this understanding makes it depend on a simple legal inquiry with a long pedigree in our legal tradition—whether the law imposes a coercive penalty to redress a public wrong.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Pelican Ins. Co&lt;/em&gt;., 127 U. S., at 299; &lt;em&gt;Robertson&lt;/em&gt;, 560 U. S., at 278–279 (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Roberts&lt;/span&gt;, C. J., dissenting).  In most cases, that inquiry will just come down to who enforces the law, the sovereign or the injured private party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;*  *  *&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Collins &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Youngblood&lt;/em&gt;, this Court explained that any “departure from &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s explanation of the original understanding of the &lt;em&gt;Ex Post Facto &lt;/em&gt;Clause[s] was . . . unjustified.”  497 U. S., at 49.  The Court understood itself to be bound by what &lt;em&gt;Calder &lt;/em&gt;meant rather than by its intervening precedents that misunderstood &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;.  497 U. S., at 49–50.  Today, this Court’s precedents concerning the scope of laws imposing criminal punishment have departed from &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s understanding of that category.  In a future case, the Court should consider returning to &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt;’s understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  Crimes and misdemeanors were for these purposes “synonymous.”  4 Blackstone 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  Professor Caleb Nelson has read &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; along the same lines: “By ‘criminal’ laws,” he has explained, “Justice Iredell and his colleagues may simply have meant laws that defined offenses and imposed punishments for them,” even if “the penalties that they prescribed could be collected through civil suits.”  C. Nelson, Originalism and Interpretive Conventions, 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 519, 582, n. 255 (2003). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-4ref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;  Sovereigns sometimes delegated enforcement of public wrongs to private persons.  But, unlike in actions redressing private wrongs, the private persons in those circumstances acted “on behalf of the sovereign” and were subject to the sovereign’s control.  &lt;em&gt;Robertson &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;United States ex rel. Watson&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/560/272"&gt;560 U. S. 272&lt;/a&gt;, 279 (2010) (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Roberts&lt;/span&gt;, C. J., dissenting); see &lt;em&gt;ibid&lt;/em&gt;. (collecting authorities).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'notes' content area --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/main&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557"&gt;Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 25-5557 argued date:   decided date: January 20, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main class="container-fluid" id="main"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: center;"&gt; HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="#tab_default_1"&gt;
                        Supreme Court &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'text' content area --&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;TOP
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Dissent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;INDIANA, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;ex rel.&lt;/span&gt; DANNY W. HOWELL &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA, WELLS COUNTY, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;et al.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on petition for writ of certiorari and motion for leave to proceed in forma pauperis to the  supreme court of indiana&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;No. 25–5557. Decided January 20, 2026&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;The motion of petitioner for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; is denied, and the petition for a writ of certiorari is dismissed.  See Rule 39.8.  As the petitioner has repeatedly abused this Court's process, the Clerk is directed not to accept any further petitions in noncriminal matters from petitioner unless the docketing fee required by Rule 38(a) is paid and the petition is submitted in compliance with Rule 33.1.  See &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/506/1"&gt;506 U. S. 1 (1992)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Jackson&lt;/span&gt;, dissenting from denial of motion for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; To file a petition in this Court, litigants must pay a $300 fee, along with the (much higher) cost of printing 40 bound copies of their filing.  Litigants who cannot afford the filing fee and the cost of printing can request to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.  The Court largely grants these requests, allowing those litigants to file for free, but our openness to indigent litigants has its limits.  In fact, the Court sometimes imposes blanket filing bars that prohibit litigants from filing any more &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; petitions in noncriminal matters going forward, regardless of the merits of their claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Today, the Court bars essentially all future filings from Danny Howell (an indigent inmate serving a 70-year sentence) because Howell previously submitted a handful of pe-  titions we deemed “frivolous.”&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Even if Howell were to identify meritorious grounds for habeas relief or wanted to bring a justifiable challenge to his conditions of confinement, he will now be prevented from doing so unless he pays the filing fee—no matter what.  A categorical, forward-looking filing bar is a questionable restriction as to any litigant who cannot afford to pay a filing fee.  For me, it is an intolerable one as to incarcerated individuals.  Accordingly, I respectfully dissent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Court began imposing prospective filing bars on &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; litigants in 1989.  First was Jessie McDonald.  The Court’s decision to bar McDonald made intuitive sense: He had filed 73 petitions over the preceding 18 years, several of which were collateral attacks on a state conviction for which he was no longer incarcerated.  &lt;em&gt;In re McDonald&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/489/180"&gt;489 U. S. 180&lt;/a&gt;, 183 (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).  Over the dissent of four Justices, the Court barred McDonald from proceeding &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; when seeking extraordinary writs in the future.&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Less than two years later, over the dissent of three Justices, the Court imposed another filing bar, this time preventing Michael Sindram from proceeding &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; when seeking extraordinary writs in the future.  Sindram had filed 43 separate petitions over the prior three years, the majority of which related to a speeding ticket he had received years earlier.  &lt;em&gt;In re Sindram&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/498/177"&gt;498 U. S. 177&lt;/a&gt;, 177–178 (1991) (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The following year, the Court significantly expanded the reach of its filing bar.  Over the course of a decade, petitioner James Martin had filed 54 &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; petitions requesting writs of certiorari in connection with a variety of civil disputes.  With two Justices dissenting, the Court barred Martin from filing any future petitions for certiorari in noncriminal cases; unlike &lt;em&gt;McDonald &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Sindram&lt;/em&gt;, this bar was not limited to requests for extraordinary writs.  &lt;em&gt;Martin &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/506/1"&gt;506 U. S. 1&lt;/a&gt;, 2–3 (1992) (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).  Martin’s circumstances lent this Court a useful shorthand: When we bar indigent litigants from filing any future &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; petitions, we now say that we are “&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;izing” them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Court’s exasperation with McDonald, Sindram, and Martin was understandable.  Each of those litigants had flooded the Court with dozens of frivolous filings, causing significant administrative burdens.  In the Court’s view, a prospective filing bar was necessary to “curb serious abuses” of its docket and to ensure that the Court could allocate its resources “in a way that promotes the interests of justice.”  &lt;em&gt;McDonald&lt;/em&gt;, 489 U. S., at 184.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Even so, its decision to permanently restrict an indigent litigant’s access to this Court was hotly contested.  The dissenters in &lt;em&gt;McDonald&lt;/em&gt; worried that, in the Court’s “fervor [to] ensur[e] that rights granted to the poor are not abused,” it had “embark[ed] on [an] unprecedented and dangerous course.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 185–187 (Brennan, J., dissenting).  Similarly, to the dissenters in &lt;em&gt;Sindram&lt;/em&gt;, even though prolific litigants do cause a “minimal annoyance,” preserving their access was “well worth the cost” given the Court’s “longstanding tradition of leaving [its] door open to all  classes of litigants.”  498 U. S., at 182 (Marshall, J., dissenting).  The dissenters feared that &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; filing bars abandoned that “proud and decent” tradition. &lt;em&gt; Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  They also predicted that what started as a rare step would turn out to be “merely the prelude” to a more habitual shutting of the courthouse doors.  &lt;em&gt;McDonald&lt;/em&gt;, 489 U. S., at 187 (Brennan, J., dissenting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The dissenters were right.  The Court has steadily expanded the reach of &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;, transforming what was once an extraordinary measure into a routine order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Howell’s case is a prime example.  He has filed only six petitions over the span of 14 years—hardly a flood.  Before this one, Howell’s last petition was in 2018, eight years ago.  Moreover, quite unlike McDonald, Sindram, or Martin, Howell is in state custody and serving a long prison sentence; all six of his petitions have raised claims challenging aspects of his conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Howell’s case is not an outlier.  By my count, the Court has now invoked &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; hundreds of times to prospectively bar indigent litigants from filing &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.  We no longer wait for a petitioner to inundate the Court with frivolous filings.  Instead, we reflexively &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ize petitioners after only a few petitions.  See, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;In re Nelson&lt;/em&gt;, 607 U. S. ___ (2025) (&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized after five petitions); &lt;em&gt;Navarro Martin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Florida&lt;/em&gt;, 607 U. S. ___ (2025) (&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized after six petitions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Even more troubling, though the Court did not have occasion to consider in &lt;em&gt;McDonald&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sindram&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; whether filing bars were necessary or appropriate for incarcerated litigants, we now routinely impose filing bars on prisoners.  See, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Crosby&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Starr&lt;/em&gt;, 607 U. S. ___ (2025) (&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized after filing a&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;petition for certiorari arising from habeas proceedings raising claims under the First Step Act); &lt;em&gt;Brunson&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Herring&lt;/em&gt;, 604 U. S. ___ (2024) (&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized  after filing a petition for certiorari arising from habeas proceedings raising claims of actual innocence); &lt;em&gt;Kaetz&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, 602 U. S. ___ (2024) (&lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized after filing a&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;petition for certiorari arising from proceedings under &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2255"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2255&lt;/a&gt; raising ineffective-assistance-of-counsel claims).  According to our Clerk’s Office, more than half of the petitioners whose filings we have categorically rejected per &lt;em&gt;Martin &lt;/em&gt;in the past 22 years were prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Applying &lt;em&gt;Martin &lt;/em&gt;routinely to bar the filings of indigent incarcerated petitioners goes too far.  In my view, such a restriction foolishly trades a pound of values for an ounce of convenience.  That is, the Court now blocks indigent incarcerated individuals from ever more accessing our courthouse, just to avoid a minor administrative burden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; To be clear: &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized petitioners are totally barred from ever filing &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; noncriminal petitions in the future—even to raise new claims based on favorable changes in the law (which sometimes happen), or to challenge the ongoing conditions of their confinement (which, in our society, prisoners are allowed to do).  The future is famously hard to predict.  So the justification for a permanent filing bar—even one related to the Court’s administrative convenience—is murky at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Changes in the law can give rise to meritorious challenges that a prisoner might be able to raise by filing a civil habeas&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;petition.  Consider, for instance, the &lt;em&gt;pro se &lt;/em&gt;petitioner in &lt;em&gt;Welch &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/578/120"&gt;578 U. S. 120 (2016)&lt;/a&gt;, who filed an &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis &lt;/em&gt;petition raising a collateral challenge to his sentence in light of our prior decision in &lt;em&gt;Johnson&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/576/591"&gt;576 U. S. 591 (2015)&lt;/a&gt;.  Welch’s filing ultimately resulted in the Court applying &lt;em&gt;Johnson&lt;/em&gt; retroactively.  578 U. S., at 130.  But if Welch had been &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized, he would have been unable to seek relief in this Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  Similarly, the conditions of a prisoner’s confinement may give rise to new constitutional claims.  In &lt;em&gt;Wilkins&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Gaddy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/34"&gt;559 U. S. 34 (2010)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;), for example, we held that a &lt;em&gt;pro se&lt;/em&gt; petitioner proceeding &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; had stated an &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/eighth_amendment"&gt;Eighth Amendment&lt;/a&gt; claim based on an assault by prison officials.  Had Wilkins been &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized, he would have been barred from obtaining the relief to which he was due under our Constitution.  Unfortunately, poor conditions in prisons across the country continue to pose potential constitutional problems.&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Indigent prisoners who are &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;ized are unable to come to this Court to challenge these unsafe conditions and vindicate their constitutional rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In short, because time moves on after a person is imprisoned and things happen, we simply do not and cannot know whether indigent prisoners who have filed multiple “frivolous” petitions in the past might have a meritorious claim in the future.  When liberty, bodily integrity, or fundamental fairness is at stake, preventing such litigants from ever again accessing our review imperils our ability to provide equal justice for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Meanwhile, the administrative burden involved in reviewing repeated (even frivolous) petitions filed by prisoners is minimal.   It is the rare incarcerated person who has the wherewithal to flood the Court with filings, at least in the way that Martin, Sindram, and McDonald had done.  Practicalities ordinarily do not allow for this, since prisoners often lack regular access to paper, pens, envelopes, and stamps.  &lt;em&gt;Pro se &lt;/em&gt;prisoners also usually handwrite their filings—a time-intensive process.  And, regardless, it is not  difficult for Court staff to sort out &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis &lt;/em&gt;filings that raise new, potentially meritorious claims from repetitive, meritless petitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; I believe that when balancing prisoners’ access to judicial review, on the one hand, and reducing our administrative burden, on the other, we should err on the side of keeping our courthouse doors open.  For a system designed to administer justice, reflexively rejecting (potentially meritorious) petitions from incarcerated litigants has a cost that is much too high when compared to the (meager) administrative efficiency gains.  Nor should we forget the role that indigent incarcerated litigants have played in the development of important constitutional doctrines—and through habeas proceedings no less.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Gideon&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Wainwright&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/372/335"&gt;372 U. S. 335 (1963)&lt;/a&gt;; see also &lt;em&gt;Sindram&lt;/em&gt;, 498 U. S., at 181 (Marshall, J., dissenting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Accordingly, I would not apply the filing bar that the Court imposes for frequent “frivolous” filers to prisoners who, like Howell, seek to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-1ref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;  See this Court’s Rule 39.8 (“If satisfied that a petition for a writ of certiorari, jurisdictional statement, or petition for an extraordinary writ is frivolous or malicious, the Court may deny leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  We emphasized that extraordinary writs are “ ‘drastic and extraordinary remedies,’ to be ‘reserved for really extraordinary causes.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;In re McDonald&lt;/em&gt;, 489 U. S., at 185 (quoting &lt;em&gt;Ex parte Fahey&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/332/258"&gt;332 U. S. 258&lt;/a&gt;, 259–260 (1947)).  We further noted that the Court had “not granted the sort of extraordinary writ relentlessly sought by [McDonald] to any litigant—paid or &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;—for at least a decade.”  489 U. S., at 184.  The nature of extraordinary writs not only made McDonald’s repeated filings frivolous, but it also meant that the filing bar—which targeted only future requests for that particular form of relief—did not significantly burden McDonald’s access to the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#DISSENT_3-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  See, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, Dept. of Justice, Investigation of Alabama’s State Prisons for Men 5–6 (Apr. 2, 2019), https://www.justice.gov/crt/case-document/ file/1149971/dl?inline= (detailing Alabama’s failure to provide safe conditions for its prisoners); Dept. of Justice, Investigation of Georgia Prisons 3 (Oct. 1, 2024), https://www.justice.gov/d9/2024-09/ findings_report_-_investigation_of_georgia_prisons.pdf (describing Georgia’s failure to protect incarcerated people from violence).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'notes' content area --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/main&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BERK v. CHOY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440"&gt;Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 24-440 argued date: October 6, 2025  decided date: January 20, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main class="container-fluid" id="main"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: center;"&gt; BERK v. CHOY &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="#tab_default_1"&gt;
                        Supreme Court &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'text' content area --&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BERK v. CHOY&lt;br/&gt;Reversed and remanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syllabus&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-440_SYLLABUS"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Syllabus]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-440.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion&lt;/strong&gt;, Barrett &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-440_OPINION_4"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Barrett Opinion]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-440.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurrence&lt;/strong&gt;, Jackson &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-440_CONCUR_5"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Jackson Concurrence]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-440.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued. The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader. See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Detroit Timber &amp;amp; Lumber Co.,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/200/321"&gt;200 U. S. 321&lt;/a&gt;, 337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center; text-align: justify;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;BERK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;CHOY et al.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the third circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;No. 24–440. Argued October 6, 2025—Decided January 20, 2026&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;Delaware law provides that a plaintiff may not sue for medical malpractice unless a medical professional attests to the suit’s merit in an “affidavit of merit” that “accompanie[s]” the plaintiff’s complaint.  Del. Code, Tit. 18, §6853(a)(1).  Petitioner Harold Berk sued Dr. Wilson Choy and Beebe Medical Center in federal court for medical malpractice under Delaware law, but failed to provide the affidavit required by §6853.  Berk argued that §6853 is not enforceable in federal court because it is displaced by the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.  The District Court dismissed Berk’s lawsuit for failure to comply with Delaware’s affidavit law.  The Third Circuit affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Held&lt;/em&gt;: Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.  Pp. 3–11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; (a) When a plaintiff brings a state-law claim in federal court, the court faces a choice-of-law problem: whether to apply state or federal law.  The Rules of Decision Act directs federal courts to apply state substantive law unless the Constitution, a treaty, or a statute otherwise requires or provides.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/1652"&gt;28 U. S. C. §1652&lt;/a&gt;.  The Rules Enabling Act, which authorizes the Supreme Court to adopt uniform rules of procedure for district courts, provides for the application of federal law.  §2072(a).  So, when a valid Federal Rule of Civil Procedure is on point, it displaces contrary state law even if the state law would qualify as substantive under &lt;em&gt;Erie R. Co.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Tompkins&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/304/64"&gt;304 U. S. 64&lt;/a&gt;.  The analysis is straightforward: The Court first asks whether a Federal Rule answers the disputed question.  If a Federal Rule does, it governs, unless it “exceeds statutory authorization or Congress’s rulemaking power.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates, P. A.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Allstate Ins. Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/393"&gt;559 U. S. 393&lt;/a&gt;, 398.  Pp. 3–4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  (b) Here, Rule 8 answers the disputed question whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed because his complaint was not accompanied by an affidavit.  Rule 8 prescribes the information a plaintiff must present about the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation: “a short and plain statement of the claim showing that [he] is entitled to relief.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_8#rule_8_a_2"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 8(a)(2)&lt;/a&gt;.  By requiring no more than a statement of the claim, Rule 8 establishes “implicitly, but with unmistakable clarity,” &lt;em&gt;Hanna &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Plumer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/380/460"&gt;380 U. S. 460&lt;/a&gt;, 470, that evidence of the claim is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required.  Rule 12 reinforces the point by providing only one ground for dismissal based on the merits—“failure to state a claim upon which relief can be granted,” Rule 12(b)(6)—and prohibiting courts from considering “matters outside the pleadings” when evaluating whether a plaintiff has stated a claim, Rule 12(d).  The court instead asks only whether the complaint’s factual allegations, if taken as true, “state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.”  &lt;em&gt;Bell Atlantic Corp.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Twombly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/550/544"&gt;550 U. S. 544&lt;/a&gt;, 570.  This Court has consistently rejected efforts by lower federal courts to require more information than Rule 8 requires.  Delaware’s law and Rule 8 thus give different answers to the question whether Berk’s complaint can be dismissed as insufficient because it was unaccompanied by an affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Defendants offer a workaround: They rewrite Delaware’s law.  After defendants’ edits, the Delaware law is no longer a pleading requirement but a free-floating evidentiary requirement that can serve as the basis for an early dismissal.  But that requirement could not be enforced under the Federal Rules.  Defendants concede that the absence of an affidavit is not grounds for dismissal under Rule 12(b)(6).  And Rule 56 already prescribes the mechanism for putting a plaintiff to his proof: a motion for summary judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Finally, defendants’ argument that Rule 11’s proviso concerning affidavits incorporates state affidavit laws like §6853 fails because the proviso cannot be read to address affidavits from third parties.  Pp. 4–10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; (c) Because Rule 8 and §6853 answer the same question, Rule 8 governs so long as it is valid under the Rules Enabling Act, which requires that Federal Rules be procedural rather than substantive.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2072#b"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2072(b)&lt;/a&gt;.  Rule 8 is valid under the Rules Enabling Act because it “really regulates procedure.”  &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Wilson &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/312/1"&gt;312 U. S. 1&lt;/a&gt;, 14.  Defendants argue that determining whether a Rule is valid under the Rules Enabling Act requires also asking whether &lt;em&gt;the displaced state law&lt;/em&gt; is substantive, but “the substantive nature of [a state] law, or its substantive purpose, &lt;em&gt;makes no difference&lt;/em&gt;” to the analysis of a Federal Rule’s validity.  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 409.  Pp. 10–11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;Reversed and remanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Barrett&lt;/span&gt;, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Roberts&lt;/span&gt;, C. J., and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Alito&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Sotomayor,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Kagan&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Gorsuch&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Kavanaugh&lt;/span&gt;, JJ., joined.  &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Jackson&lt;/span&gt;, J., filed an opinion concurring in the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the United States Reports. Readers are requested to notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Washington, D. C. 20543, pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–440&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;HAROLD R. BERK, PETITIONER &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt;  WILSON C. CHOY, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;et al.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the third circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Barrett&lt;/span&gt; delivered the opinion of the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The cost of malpractice insurance for doctors and hospitals has significantly increased in some areas of the country.  In response, several States have imposed a screening mechanism on malpractice suits, requiring plaintiffs to submit an affidavit from a medical professional attesting to the suit’s merit.  We consider whether Delaware’s affidavit requirement applies in federal court and hold that it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; While on a trip to Delaware, Harold Berk fell out of bed.  According to his complaint, he was taken by ambulance to a hospital owned by Beebe Medical Center, Inc., where an X ray revealed a fractured ankle.  Dr. Wilson Choy recommended that Berk be fitted with a protective boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The fitting did not go well.  Hospital employees forced Berk’s leg into the boot, twisting his fractured ankle.  Still, Dr. Choy did not immediately order another X ray; he told Berk to keep weight off his ankle, proposed a follow-up appointment in two weeks, and sent Berk on his way.  At the follow-up, Berk got a second X ray, which showed that his  ankle was not just fractured but also severely deformed, requiring surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Berk sued Beebe Medical Center and Dr. Choy (whom we will call defendants) for medical malpractice under Delaware law.  Because Berk and defendants are citizens of different States, Berk could sue in federal court based on diversity jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Under Delaware law, a plaintiff may not sue for medical malpractice unless an affidavit of merit “accompanie[s]” the complaint.  Del. Code, Tit. 18, §6853(a)(1) (2025).  The affidavit must be signed by a medical professional, §6853(c), and it must state that there are “reasonable grounds to believe that there has been health-care medical negligence committed by each defendant,” §6853(a)(1).  A plaintiff with “good cause” may secure a single 60-day extension of time in which to file the affidavit, &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;, but he must file the extension motion before or when he files the complaint, §6853(a)(2).  If an affidavit does not accompany the complaint and the plaintiff has not filed a timely extension motion, then the clerk of court shall “refuse to file the complaint and it shall not be docketed.”  §6853(a)(1).  The defendants need not take any action with respect to the complaint until 20 days after the affidavit of merit is filed.  §6853(a)(4).  Upon the defendants’ motion, the court must determine &lt;em&gt;in camera&lt;/em&gt; if the affidavit satisfies the statutory requirements.  §6853(d).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Attempting to comply with §6853, Berk immediately moved for an extension of time to file an affidavit.  The District Court granted Berk’s motion, and Berk tried to track down a doctor willing to provide an affidavit (an ordeal spawning separate litigation).  But the clock ran out, and coming up empty-handed, Berk instead filed his medical records under seal.  Defendants moved the District Court to review Berk’s submissions &lt;em&gt;in camera&lt;/em&gt; to determine whether they complied with §6853.  Berk countered that §6853 is not enforceable in federal court because it is displaced by the  Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.  The District Court disagreed with Berk and dismissed his lawsuit for failure to comply with Delaware’s affidavit law.  See 2023 WL 2770573, *1–*2 (D Del., Apr. 4, 2023).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Third Circuit affirmed, holding that §6853 applies in federal court.  See 2024 WL 3534482, *4 (July 25, 2024).  The court concluded that the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure are silent as to whether an affidavit must accompany the complaint.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at *2–*3.  Where the Federal Rules are silent, state law applies if it is substantive.  See &lt;em&gt;Erie R. Co.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Tompkins&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/304/64"&gt;304 U. S. 64&lt;/a&gt;, 78 (1938).  A state law is substantive if (1) it is outcome determinative, and (2) failing to apply it in federal court would promote forum shopping and the inequitable administration of the law.  See &lt;em&gt;Hanna &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Plumer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/380/460"&gt;380 U. S. 460&lt;/a&gt;, 467–469 (1965).  After applying this test, the Third Circuit concluded that §6853 is substantive and affirmed the dismissal of Berk’s suit.  See 2024 WL 3534482, *3–*4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; We granted certiorari.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/604/1193"&gt;604 U. S. 1193 (2025)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; State-law claims are usually brought in state court.  But if the parties are citizens of different States and the amount in controversy exceeds a certain threshold, a plaintiff may choose to sue in federal court.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/1332"&gt;28 U. S. C. §1332&lt;/a&gt;.  In that event, the federal court faces a choice-of-law problem: whether to apply state or federal law.  The Rules of Decision Act directs federal courts to apply state substantive law, leaving federal law to cover the rest.  §1652.  Following that direction is harder than it looks, because determining whether a state law is substantive requires a court to enter “&lt;em&gt;Erie&lt;/em&gt;’s murky waters.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates, P. A.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Allstate Ins. Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/393"&gt;559 U. S. 393&lt;/a&gt;, 398 (2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Yet when a Federal Rule of Civil Procedure is on point, a federal court bypasses &lt;em&gt;Erie&lt;/em&gt;’s inquiry altogether.  That is because the Rules of Decision Act dictates that state  substantive law must yield if the Constitution, a treaty, or a statute “otherwise require[s] or provide[s].”  §1652.  And the Rules Enabling Act, which authorizes the Supreme Court to adopt uniform rules of procedure for district courts, provides for the application of federal law.  §2072(a); see also &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_1"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 1&lt;/a&gt; (“These rules govern the procedure in all civil actions and proceedings in the United States district courts . . . ”).  Thus, a valid Rule of Civil Procedure displaces contrary state law even if the state law would qualify as substantive under &lt;em&gt;Erie&lt;/em&gt;’s test.  See &lt;em&gt;Hanna&lt;/em&gt;, 380 U. S., at 469–474.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Analyzing whether a Federal Rule displaces state law is straightforward.  We first ask whether the Federal Rule “answers the question in dispute.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 398.  In doing so, we interpret the Federal Rules the same way we interpret federal laws more generally: by giving them their “plain meaning.”  &lt;em&gt;Walker&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Armco Steel Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/446/740"&gt;446 U. S. 740&lt;/a&gt;, 750, n. 9 (1980).  If a Federal Rule answers the disputed question, it governs, unless it “exceeds statutory authorization or Congress’s rulemaking power.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 398.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In this case, the disputed question is whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed because his complaint was not accompanied by an expert affidavit.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Rule 8 gives the answer.   It prescribes the information a plaintiff must present about the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation: “a short and plain statement of the claim showing that [he] is entitled to relief.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_8#rule_8_a_2"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 8(a)(2)&lt;/a&gt;.  By requiring no more than a statement of the claim, Rule 8 establishes “implicitly, but with unmistakable clarity,” &lt;em&gt;Hanna&lt;/em&gt;, 380 U. S., at 470, that evidence of the claim is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required.  Cf. &lt;em&gt;Burlington Northern R. Co.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Woods&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/480/1"&gt;480 U. S. 1&lt;/a&gt;, 7–8 (1987) (declining to apply a state statute where a Federal Rule “occupies the statute’s field of operation”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Rule 12 reinforces the point.  It provides only one ground for dismissal based on the merits: “failure to state a claim upon which relief can be granted.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_12#rule_12_b_6"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 12(b)(6)&lt;/a&gt;.  When evaluating whether a plaintiff has stated a claim, the court cannot consider “matters outside the pleadings.”  Rule 12(d).  The court instead asks only whether the complaint’s factual allegations, if taken as true, “state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.”  &lt;em&gt;Bell Atlantic Corp.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Twombly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/550/544"&gt;550 U. S. 544&lt;/a&gt;, 570 (2007).  A complaint that satisfies this standard is “well-pleaded” and “may proceed even if it strikes a savvy judge that actual proof of the facts alleged is improbable.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 556.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; By design, this system of pleading makes it relatively easy for plaintiffs to subject defendants to discovery—even for claims that are likely to fail.  To protect defendants from this burden, lower federal courts have sometimes tried to require more information for certain kinds of claims: &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/42/1983"&gt;42 U. S. C. §1983&lt;/a&gt; actions against municipalities, &lt;em&gt;Leatherman &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Tarrant County Narcotics Intelligence and Coordination Unit&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/507/163"&gt;507 U. S. 163 (1993)&lt;/a&gt;; employment discrimination suits, &lt;em&gt;Swierkiewicz &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Sorema N. A.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/534/506"&gt;534 U. S. 506 (2002)&lt;/a&gt;; and prisoner suits, &lt;em&gt;Jones &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Bock&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/549/199"&gt;549 U. S. 199 (2007)&lt;/a&gt;.  We  have consistently rejected such efforts.  As we explained in &lt;em&gt;Leatherman&lt;/em&gt;—which dealt with a demand that plaintiffs plead certain §1983 claims with added specificity—Rule 8(a)(2) requires “only” a “ ‘short and plain statement of the claim.’ ”  507 U. S., at 165, 168 (quoting Rule 8(a)(2)).  Unless the Federal Rules single out a claim for special treatment, see, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_9"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 9&lt;/a&gt;, Rule 8 sets a ceiling on the information that plaintiffs can be required to provide about the merits of their claims. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Delaware’s affidavit requirement is at odds with Rule 8 because it demands more: A medical malpractice suit cannot proceed “unless the complaint is accompanied by . . . [a]n affidavit of merit.”  §6853(a)(1).  Under Rule 8, factual allegations are sufficient, but under the Delaware law, the plaintiff needs evidence too.  See &lt;em&gt;Dishmon &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Fucci&lt;/em&gt;, 32 A. 3d 338, 344 (Del. 2011) (describing §6853 as imposing a “&lt;em&gt;prima facie &lt;/em&gt;evidentiary requiremen[t]”); see also Brief for Respondent Beebe 23 (same).  The two rules thus give different answers to the question whether Berk’s complaint can be dismissed as insufficient because it was unaccompanied by an affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; It is true, as defendants and the concurrence are quick to point out, that an affidavit of merit is a document separate from the “pleading,” and that, by its literal terms, Rule 8 defines only what the “pleading . . . must contain.”  But we think it is fair to infer that by specifying what information about the merits is required in the “pleading,” Rule 8 excludes the possibility of requiring even more information on the same topic—whether in the “pleading” itself or on a separate sheet of paper attached to it.  Cf. &lt;em&gt;Jones&lt;/em&gt;, 549 U. S., at 205, 212–217 (rejecting requirement that prisoners “attach proof of exhaustion . . . to their complaints” as inconsistent with Rule 8).  Rule 8 addresses what information a plaintiff must provide about the merits of his claim at the outset of  litigation.  Section 6853 addresses the same issue—and in doing so, imposes a different standard.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Resisting this conclusion, defendants cite &lt;em&gt;Cohen&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Beneficial Industrial Loan Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/337/541"&gt;337 U. S. 541 (1949)&lt;/a&gt;, for the broad proposition that all state “preconditions to proceeding” are consistent with the Federal Rules.  Brief for Respondent Beebe 26–27; see Brief for Respondent Choy 20–21.  They substantially overread &lt;em&gt;Cohen&lt;/em&gt;.  There, a state law rendered an unsuccessful plaintiff in a shareholder derivative suit liable for all the defendant’s expenses, including attorney’s fees, and as security for that potential liability, required the plaintiff to post a bond before proceeding with the action.  337 U. S., at 543.  The plaintiffs argued that the bond requirement was displaced by then-Rule 23, which governed shareholder derivative suits in federal court.  &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 556.  &lt;em&gt;Cohen&lt;/em&gt; held that there was no conflict because the state law and Rule 23 addressed different issues: The state law created a liability, while Rule 23 dealt with “disclosure to the court and notice to the parties in interest.”  &lt;em&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 555–556.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Cohen&lt;/em&gt; thus did not identify and exempt a broad category of so-called preconditions to proceeding from conflict with  the Federal Rules.  It held that a particular state law addressed a matter that was unaddressed by the relevant Federal Rule.  Here, by contrast, the state law and the Federal Rule address the same issue: the information that a plaintiff must provide about the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation.  Describing the affidavit requirement as a “preconditio[n] to proceeding” does not magically dispel the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Defendants offer a workaround: They rewrite Delaware’s law.  While §6853 provides that an affidavit must “accompan[y]” the complaint, defendants suggest that the district court can simply require it “early in [a] case.”  Brief for Respondent Beebe 13; see also Brief for Respondent Choy 36 (suggesting affidavit can be filed “weeks” or “months” after the complaint).  This proposal is inspired by §6853’s allowance for an extension of time in which to file the affidavit.  But defendants treat this exception—which is available only “for good cause shown”—as the rule and rework the exception to boot.  In federal court, apparently, an extension motion need not precede or accompany the complaint; nor is the district court limited to granting one 60-day extension.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., Brief for Respondent Beebe 23–25.  And defendants’ proposed changes do not stop there: They would also have us delete the provision that absolves a defendant from “tak[ing] any action with respect to the complaint” until the affidavit is filed.  §6853(a)(4).  Under Federal Rule 12(a)(1), service of the summons and complaint triggers a defendant’s obligation to respond, and defendants admit that the Federal Rule controls on this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; After defendants’ edits, the Delaware law is no longer a pleading requirement that serves a gatekeeping function; it is a free-floating evidentiary requirement that can serve as the basis for an early dismissal.  Yet even were it acceptable to take creative license with the Delaware law, there would be no way to enforce such a requirement.  Defendants concede that the absence of an affidavit is not grounds for  dismissal under Rule 12(b)(6).  They float the possibility of dismissal for failure to prosecute, but that does not work because Berk actively participated in the litigation.  Defendants’ first choice is the course the District Court took here: dismissal based on the court’s inherent authority.  The problem, however, is that the Federal Rules already prescribe a mechanism for putting a plaintiff to his proof: a motion for summary judgment.  See &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_56"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 56&lt;/a&gt;.  And that does not offer defendants the protection they want, because before ruling on the motion, the court must allow the nonmovant “adequate time for discovery.”  &lt;em&gt;Celotex Corp.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Catrett&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/477/317"&gt;477 U. S. 317&lt;/a&gt;, 322 (1986); see also Rule 12(d) (requiring a “reasonable opportunity to present all the [pertinent] material” if motion to dismiss is converted to motion for summary judgment).  That defendants cannot fit the affidavit requirement into the Federal Rules illustrates that it has no place there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Perhaps recognizing this, defendants devote most of their energy to arguing that the Federal Rules contain a loophole.  According to defendants, a proviso tucked into Rule 11 makes state affidavit laws applicable in federal court even if they conflict with other Federal Rules.  Rule 11 provides that “[u]nless a rule or statute specifically states otherwise, a pleading need not be verified or accompanied by an affidavit.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_11#rule_11_a"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 11(a)&lt;/a&gt;.  Defendants argue that §6853 is a “statute [that] specifically states otherwise,” &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;, and it therefore applies in federal court regardless of whether it conflicts with other Federal Rules.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Even if Rule 11 incorporates some state affidavit laws, it does not incorporate this one.  Rule 11 governs the conduct of those who practice before courts: the “attorney of record” or the “party personally if the party is unrepresented.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  It requires the attorney or &lt;em&gt;pro se&lt;/em&gt; party to certify, after “reasonable” inquiry, that the legal and factual representations made to the court are warranted.  Rule 11(b).  The sentence on which defendants rely simply “acknowledges”  that although Rule 11 generally puts the onus on the attorney or &lt;em&gt;pro se&lt;/em&gt; party to vouch for representations, “in some situations &lt;em&gt;represented parties&lt;/em&gt; are required by rule or statute to verify pleadings or sign affidavits.”  &lt;em&gt;Business Guides, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Chromatic Communications Enterprises, Inc.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/498/533"&gt;498 U. S. 533&lt;/a&gt;, 542 (1991) (emphasis added); see, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_23.1"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 23.1&lt;/a&gt; (requiring complaints in shareholder derivative actions to be verified).  The sentence has nothing to do with affidavits from third parties.  Accordingly, Rule 11 does not shield Delaware’s law from displacement by Rule 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Because Rule 8 and §6853 answer the same question, Rule 8 governs so long as it is valid under the Rules Enabling Act, which requires that Federal Rules be procedural rather than substantive.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2072#b"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2072(b)&lt;/a&gt; (“Such rules shall not abridge, enlarge or modify any substantive right”).  The line between substance and procedure is hazy, and we draw it differently in different contexts.  See &lt;em&gt;Hanna&lt;/em&gt;, 380 U. S., at 471 (“The line between ‘substance’ and ‘procedure’ shifts as the legal context changes”).  For purposes of the Rules Enabling Act, we use a modest test: whether the Federal Rule “really regulates procedure.”  &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Wilson &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/312/1"&gt;312 U. S. 1&lt;/a&gt;, 14 (1941).  Or put differently, “[w]hat matters is what the Rule itself &lt;em&gt;regulates&lt;/em&gt;: If it governs only ‘the manner and the means’ by which the litigants’ rights are ‘enforced,’ it is valid.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 407 (plurality opinion) (quoting &lt;em&gt;Mississippi Publishing Corp.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Murphree&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/326/438"&gt;326 U. S. 438&lt;/a&gt;, 446 (1946)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In applying this analysis, we have “rejected every statutory challenge to a Federal Rule that has come before us.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 407 (plurality opinion).  We have upheld Rules governing the certification of class actions, &lt;em&gt;id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 408 (Rule 23); see &lt;em&gt;id.&lt;/em&gt;, at 416, 436 (Stevens, J., concurring in part and concurring in judgment) (Rule 23);  service of process, &lt;em&gt;Mississippi Publishing Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, 326 U. S., at 445–446 (Rule 4(f )); compelled mental and physical examinations, &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt;, 312 U. S., at 14–16 (Rule 35); sanctions for frivolous appeals, &lt;em&gt;Burlington&lt;/em&gt;, 480 U. S., at 8 (Rule 38); and sanctions for signing court papers without reasonably investigating the facts asserted, &lt;em&gt;Business Guides&lt;/em&gt;, 498 U. S., at 551–554 (Rule 11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Like those Rules, Rule 8 “really regulates procedure.”  &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt;, 312 U. S., at 14.  It determines what plaintiffs must present to the court about their claims at the outset of litigation.  Although the Rule may have some “practical effect on the parties’ rights,” it regulates “only the process for enforcing those rights,” not “the rights themselves, the available remedies, or the rules of decision.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 407–408 (plurality opinion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Defendants do not contend otherwise.  Instead, they argue that determining whether a Rule is valid under the Rules Enabling Act requires asking a second question: whether &lt;em&gt;the displaced state law&lt;/em&gt; is substantive.  We rejected that approach eight decades ago and decline to reconsider it now.  See &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt;, 312 U. S., at 14.  On the contrary, we underscore that “the substantive nature of [a state] law, or its substantive purpose, &lt;em&gt;makes no difference&lt;/em&gt;.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 409 (plurality opinion).  To determine whether a Rule is valid under the Rules Enabling Act, the only question is whether it “really regulates procedure.”  &lt;em&gt;Sibbach&lt;/em&gt;, 312 U. S., at 14.  Rule 8 does, so it governs, and Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;*  *  *&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The judgment of the Court of Appeals is reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;It is so ordered&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  The concurrence objects to our framing the disputed question around dismissal because doing so “assumes that Berk’s lawsuit has already been . . . filed and docketed.”  &lt;em&gt;Post&lt;/em&gt;, at 4 (&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Jackson&lt;/span&gt;, J., concurring in judgment).  But Berk’s lawsuit &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; already been filed and docketed, see No. 1:22–cv–01506 (D Del., Nov. 18, 2022), ECF Doc. 1, which is how it found its way here.  The only question in dispute is whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed—indeed, that is the question on which we granted certiorari.  See Pet. for Cert. i.  The concurrence reframes the question in dispute as “what is required to start a medical malpractice case.”  &lt;em&gt;Post&lt;/em&gt;, at 4.  But because no one argues that the court violated §6853 by docketing Berk’s complaint, the concurrence is ultimately forced to grapple with the question whether Berk’s lawsuit may be “dismiss[ed].”  &lt;em&gt;Post&lt;/em&gt;, at 11.  By focusing on dismissal from the start, we do not “jum[p] the gun,” &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt;, at 4, but rather cut to the chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  The concurrence accuses us—and the “many Courts of Appeals” that agree with us—of “contorting” Rule 8 by reading it to implicitly preclude courts from requiring plaintiffs to provide additional information.  &lt;em&gt;Post&lt;/em&gt;, at 10, and n. 6.  Yet drawing a negative inference from text is sometimes the best way to understand it.  See A. Scalia &amp;amp; B. Garner, Reading Law: The Interpretation of Legal Texts 107–111 (2012) (negative-implication canon).  And while the concurrence criticizes the negative inference we draw as “inattentively capacious,” &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt;, at 8, its Rule 3 analysis depends on an analogous inference.  Rule 3 establishes what happens once a complaint is filed: “A civil action is commenced by filing a complaint with the court.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_3"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 3&lt;/a&gt;.  Section 6853, meanwhile, establishes what is required “to file the complaint . . . with the court”: an affidavit of merit or an extension motion.  §6853(a)(1).  The concurrence finds a collision only by reading Rule 3 to implicitly foreclose any precondition to filing the complaint.  So if a negative inference is a “contortion,” the concurrence’s argument fails by its own measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Concurrence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–440&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;HAROLD R. BERK, PETITIONER &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt;  WILSON C. CHOY, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;et al.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the third circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Jackson&lt;/span&gt;, concurring in the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; I agree with the Court that Delaware’s affidavit requirement cannot apply in federal court.  I write separately because, in my view, the relevant conflicts are with &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_3"&gt;Federal Rules of Civil Procedure 3&lt;/a&gt; and 12, not Rule 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As the majority explains, Delaware’s law is, at bottom, an “affidavit requirement.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 1.  If a medical malpractice plaintiff wants her complaint deemed “filed” and his case docketed, the statute mandates that an affidavit of merit signed by a medical professional (or a motion for an extension of time to file the affidavit) must accompany the complaint.  See Del. Code, Tit. 18, §6853(a)(1) (2025).  By contrast, the Federal Rules require no such additional filing.  Rather, “[a] civil action is commenced by filing a complaint with the court.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_3"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Thus, §6853 and Rule 3 conflict regarding the requirements to “commence” a medical malpractice action.  If a federal court were to follow Delaware’s law, a plaintiff would have to do more than merely tender the complaint in order for his medical malpractice lawsuit to be filed and docketed.  But, under the language of Rule 3, civil suits commence as soon as the complaint—and only the complaint—has been  filed by the plaintiff.  In my view, this clash warrants reversal here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As the majority explains, our cases make clear beyond cavil that “a valid [Federal] Rule of Civil Procedure displaces contrary state law.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4.  Thus, the nub of the conflict inquiry is to determine whether the State’s requirement is, in fact, contrary to a Federal Rule.  Over time, we have expressed this central inquiry in various ways.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Hanna&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Plumer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/380/460"&gt;380 U. S. 460&lt;/a&gt;, 472 (1965) (asking whether “the applicable Federal Rule is in direct collision&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;with the [state] law”); &lt;em&gt;Burlington Northern R. Co&lt;/em&gt;. v. &lt;em&gt;Woods&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/480/1"&gt;480 U. S. 1&lt;/a&gt;, 4–5 (1987) (asking whether the scope of the Federal Rule is “ ‘sufficiently broad’ ” to “ ‘control the issue’ ” before the Court, “thereby leaving no room for the operation” of the state law (quoting &lt;em&gt;Walker&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Armco Steel Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/446/740"&gt;446 U. S. 740&lt;/a&gt;, 749–750, and n. 9 (1980))).  But as the majority acknowledges, our most up-to-date approach to identifying the necessary conflict is to ask whether the Federal Rule and the state statute “attemp[t] to answer the same question.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove Orthopedic Associates, P. A&lt;/em&gt;. v. &lt;em&gt;Allstate Ins. Co&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/393"&gt;559 U. S. 393&lt;/a&gt;, 399 (2010); see also &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Per &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, once a conflict between the State’s requirement and a Federal Rule has been identified, the Federal Rule displaces the State’s requirement so long as the Rule is “valid,” meaning that it “governs only ‘the manner and the means’ by which the litigants’ rights are ‘enforced.’ ”  559 U. S., at 407 (plurality opinion) (quoting &lt;em&gt;Mississippi Publishing Corp.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Murphree&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/326/438"&gt;326 U. S. 438&lt;/a&gt;, 446 (1946)); see also &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2072#b"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2072(b)&lt;/a&gt; (Rules Enabling Act).  And for similar reasons to those given in Part II–B of the majority opinion, Rule 3 easily satisfies this standard.  See &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 10–11; see also &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 407 (plurality opinion) (noting that we have “rejected every statutory challenge to a Federal Rule that has come before us”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Accordingly, Delaware’s affidavit requirement cannot apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The majority and I start in the same place and ultimately reach the same conclusion, but we have taken different paths, marked by different assumptions and nuances.  I agree with the majority that the first step of today’s analysis is to identify the relevant conflict by ascertaining the question that the Delaware law and the Federal Rule “attemp[t] to answer.”  &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;559 U. S., at 399; see &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4.  But I disagree that, in this case, “the disputed question is whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed because his complaint was not accompanied by an expert affidavit.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4.  Here is why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; First and foremost, that formulation of the question assumes that Berk’s lawsuit has already been properly accepted by the court clerk (&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;., filed and docketed) and thus that §6853 is answering whether the “lawsuit may be dismissed” for want of the required affidavit.  &lt;em&gt;Ante&lt;/em&gt;, at 4.  But that assumption jumps the gun.  Delaware’s law states that “[n]o health-care negligence lawsuit shall be &lt;em&gt;filed&lt;/em&gt; in this State unless the complaint is accompanied by: (1) [a]n affidavit of merit” or (2) “a motion to extend the time to file said affidavit.”  §6853(a)(1) (emphasis added).  The statute further specifies that “[i]f the required affidavit does not accompany the complaint or if a motion to extend the time to file said affidavit . . . has not been filed with the court, then the . . . clerk of the court shall &lt;em&gt;refuse to file&lt;/em&gt; the complaint and it shall not be &lt;em&gt;docketed&lt;/em&gt; with the court.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt; (emphasis added).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Accordingly, the text of §6853 makes clear that the statute’s first order of business is not to address the requirements for dismissal of an affidavit-free lawsuit such as Berk’s.  Instead, §6853 most directly answers the threshold question of what is required &lt;em&gt;to start&lt;/em&gt; a civil action for medical malpractice under Delaware law.  Delaware’s response is that the plaintiff must submit an affidavit of merit, or a motion for an extension of time to file such affidavit, because (to repeat) the clerk cannot “file the complaint” or “docke[t]” the case without that additional filing.  §6853(a)(1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Rule 3 provides a completely different answer to the question of what is required to start a medical malpractice case.  As explained above, under that Rule, “[a] civil action is commenced by filing a complaint with the court”—period.  That answer leaves “no room” for Delaware’s insistence that an affidavit of merit (or a motion for an extension) must be submitted in order to commence this kind of legal action.  &lt;em&gt;Burlington&lt;/em&gt;, 480 U. S., at 5.  Indeed, Rule 3 uses the uncompromising, declarative phrase “is commenced,” plainly indicating that Congress meant for the “filing [of] a complaint” to be both necessary &lt;em&gt;and sufficient&lt;/em&gt; to begin any civil case (including a malpractice action) in federal court.  Cf. &lt;em&gt;Walker&lt;/em&gt;, 446 U. S., at 750, n. 10 (“ ‘Rule 3 simply provides that an action is commenced by filing the complaint and has as its primary purpose the measuring of time periods that begin running from the date of commencement’ ” (quoting 4 C. Wright &amp;amp; A. Miller, Federal Practice and Procedure §1057, p. 191 (1969))); &lt;em&gt;Hallstrom &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Tillamook County&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/493/20"&gt;493 U. S. 20&lt;/a&gt;, 26 (1989) (reading Rule 3 to mean that “filing a complaint with the court” is synonymous with “fil[ing] suit”).&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Resisting this conclusion, defendants rely on three cases from 1949, arguing that “this Court has long found applicable in federal court” “state-law condition[s] on allowing suits to proceed.”  Brief for Respondent Beebe 26–27, and n. 11; see also Brief for Respondent Choy 36–37.  But that argument mischaracterizes our past rulings.  See &lt;em&gt;Cohen &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Beneficial Industrial Loan Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/337/541"&gt;337 U. S. 541 (1949)&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;em&gt;Woods&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Interstate Realty Co&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/337/535"&gt;337 U. S. 535 (1949)&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;em&gt;Walker &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Armco Steel Corp&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/446/740"&gt;446 U. S. 740&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The majority has already ably explained that defendants “substantially overread” &lt;em&gt;Cohen &lt;/em&gt;for the proposition that “all state ‘preconditions to proceeding’ are consistent with the Federal Rules.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 7.  I think &lt;em&gt;Walker &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Woods &lt;/em&gt;are also easily distinguishable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As with &lt;em&gt;Cohen&lt;/em&gt;, respondents overstate the effect of &lt;em&gt;Walker&lt;/em&gt;.  There, we held that a federal court sitting in diversity must apply an Oklahoma law that deemed an action “commenced” upon service of the summons &lt;em&gt;for purposes of the State’s statute of limitations&lt;/em&gt;.  446 U. S., at 742.  Rule 3, we explained, “governs the date from which various timing requirements of the Federal Rules begin to run, but does not affect state statutes of limitations.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 751.  Here, by contrast, §6853 and Rule 3 serve precisely the same function, in the same context: Both establish when a malpractice lawsuit is deemed initiated (&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;., filed and docketed) for purposes of determining “the date from which various timing requirements of the Federal Rules begin to run.”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  That is precisely the kind of conflict that bars the application of state law in federal court under our precedents.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Defendants’ reliance on &lt;em&gt;Woods&lt;/em&gt; is similarly unavailing.  There, we held that a federal court sitting in diversity must apply a Mississippi law prohibiting out-of-state corporations from bringing suit in the State unless they designated an agent for service of process.  337 U. S., at 536, n. 1.  Mississippi’s law was enacted to ensure that only those out-of-state corporations that consented to being sued in Mississippi had the privilege of accessing Mississippi’s courts.  See &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  In other words, Mississippi’s law had a broad substantive purpose and effect that went well beyond what the Federal Rules addressed.  That was why we had to wade through “&lt;em&gt;Erie&lt;/em&gt;’s murky waters” to decide the conflicts question that case presented.  See &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 398; see &lt;em&gt;Erie R. Co.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Tompkins&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/304/64"&gt;304 U. S. 64 (1938)&lt;/a&gt;.  Delaware’s affidavit requirement, by contrast, is plainly procedural in scope and well within the territory of the Federal Rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In short, our precedents establish that when a state law and a valid Federal Rule conflict—because they answer the same procedural question—the State’s requirement is inapplicable in federal court.  Because §6853 answers the same question about what is required to commence a medical malpractice action as the unquestionably valid Rule 3, Delaware’s law must give way.  See &lt;em&gt;Hanna&lt;/em&gt;, 380 U. S., at 469–474.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; If we accept, for the sake of argument, that the question Delaware’s law attempts to answer is “whether [a medical malpractice complaint] may be dismissed because [it] was not accompanied by an expert affidavit,” &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4, a problem arises: The Federal Rule the majority points to does not answer that same question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The majority discerns a conflict with Rule 8 by reasoning as follows.  With respect to the dismissal-related question quoted above, Delaware’s law says that such a complaint must be dismissed because the affidavit of merit is missing, whereas Rule 8 prescribes all “the information a plaintiff must present about the merits of his claim at the outset of litigation”—namely, “ ‘a short and plain statement of the claim showing that [he] is entitled to relief.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Ante&lt;/em&gt;, at 5 (quoting &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_8#rule_8_a_2"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 8(a)(2)&lt;/a&gt;).  “By requiring no more than a statement of the claim,” the majority continues, “Rule 8 establishes ‘implicitly, but with unmistakable clarity,’ . . . that evidence of the claim is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Ante&lt;/em&gt;, at 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The problem with this reasoning is not that it is based on “a negative inference” about Rule 8, &lt;em&gt;id.,&lt;/em&gt; at 7, n. 2, but rather the inattentively capacious scope of that negative inference.  I agree that Rule 8(a)’s finite list “preclude[s] courts” from imposing additional requirements.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.; see&lt;em&gt; Leatherman&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Tarrant County Narcotics Intelligence and Coordination Unit&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/507/163"&gt;507 U. S. 163&lt;/a&gt;, 168 (1993).  But context is critical: Rule 8 does not purport to establish &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; that a medical malpractice plaintiff can be required to say about the merits of his claims at the beginning of the case, much less that nothing more than the filing of a complaint can be mandated.  Rather, it (more narrowly) addresses what any “&lt;em&gt;pleading&lt;/em&gt;” stating a claim for relief must contain.  See Rule 8(a) (“A &lt;em&gt;pleading&lt;/em&gt; that states a claim for relief must contain . . .” (emphasis added)).  The majority neither holds nor suggests that §6853’s affidavit of merit is, itself, a “pleading”; to the contrary, the majority admits that the affidavit is not.  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 6.  So, as I see it, Delaware’s law—which prescribes what a plaintiff must submit &lt;em&gt;in addition to&lt;/em&gt; his pleadings in order for his complaint to be filed and his case docketed—does not actually conflict with Rule 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The majority acknowledges this “pleading” problem and offers, apparently as a solution, yet another formulation of the question that Rule 8 is answering: Rule 8, it says, tells us “what information a plaintiff must provide about the merits of his claim.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 6.  But, again, this description fails to acknowledge that Rule 8 operates entirely within a specific universe: the pleadings.  The majority’s unbounded characterization subtly frees Rule 8 from the constraint of its subject matter, allowing it to expand until it collides with Delaware’s law.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When properly construed, Rule 8 addresses a particular (and particularly important) procedural question: “What must a pleading that states a claim for relief contain?”&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  In my view, this narrower formulation of the question—the one tethered to the required contents of a “pleading”—keeps Rule 8 within the bounds of its plain meaning, consistent with &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt;’s command not to overread the Federal Rules at the expense of “important state interests and regulatory policies” in cases such as this one.  &lt;em&gt;Gasperini &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Center for Humanities, Inc.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/518/415"&gt;518 U. S. 415&lt;/a&gt;, 427, n. 7 (1996); see also n. 1, &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Accordingly, because §6853 does not address or govern the required contents of a pleading, Delaware’s law does not answer the same question as Rule 8.  Instead, the State’s affidavit requirement (which, incidentally, neither describes the affidavit of merit in relation to a plaintiff ’s obligation to state a claim for relief nor treats it as evidence) is an additional filing requirement for commencing any medical malpractice civil action under state law.  See §6853(a)(1) (“No health-care negligence lawsuit shall be filed in [Delaware] unless the complaint is accompanied by . . . [a]n affidavit of merit”).  Finding a Rule 8 conflict, as the majority does, thus requires contorting &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; Rule 8 and §6853.  There is no need to do so here, especially given the ready conflict with Rule 3 (discussed above) and Rule 12 (described below).&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The majority and I appear to agree that Delaware’s affidavit requirement—as interpreted by the Delaware Supreme Court—conflicts with Rule 12(d).  See &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 5.  That conflict suffices to displace §6853’s requirement.  But to the extent that the majority ties its Rule 12 analysis to the purported Rule 8 conflict, see &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;, I think the majority has gone further than it needs to, introducing incoherence in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; While the statute itself does not so specify, the Delaware Supreme Court has interpreted §6853 to mean that (assuming the clerk of court accepts an affidavit-free medical malpractice action and dockets the case notwithstanding the statute’s prohibition) “[t]he filing of a healthcare negligence action without the requisite affidavit of merit constitutes grounds of dismissal of medical negligence claims as a matter of law.”  &lt;em&gt;Hall&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Sorouri&lt;/em&gt;, 996 A. 2d 793 (Del. 2010) (Table).  That reading of Delaware law answers the question, “What can a court consider when dismissing a medical malpractice case?”  Because “[t]he highest state court is the final authority on state law,” &lt;em&gt;Fidelity Union Trust Co. &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Field&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/311/169"&gt;311 U. S. 169&lt;/a&gt;, 177 (1940), we must read this statute as that court does, &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;., as establishing dismissal requirements for medical malpractice cases.  Thus, if a valid Federal Rule answers that same dismissal question, §6853 cannot govern in federal court.  See &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, 559 U. S., at 398.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Enter Rule 12.  As the majority correctly explains, Rule 12(b)(6) provides the “only . . . ground for dismissal based on the merits,” and Rule 12(d) prohibits courts from considering “ ‘matters outside the pleadings’ ” in deciding motions to dismiss brought under Rule 12(b)(6).  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 5; see also &lt;em&gt;Stanley&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;City of Sanford&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/606/46"&gt;606 U. S. 46&lt;/a&gt;, 49 (2025) (explaining that, under Rule 12(d), a judge considering a motion to dismiss must “take as true the well-pleaded facts in the plaintiff ’s complaint, . . . and [must] not consider evidence beyond that pleading”).  Furthermore, by all accounts, the affidavit required by Delaware’s law is a “matte[r] outside the pleadings.”  Rule 12(d); see &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 6 (“It is true . . . that an affidavit of merit is a document separate from the ‘pleading’ ”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;We know the affidavit of merit qualifies as a “matter outside the pleadings” for several reasons.  For one thing, Delaware law provides that the affidavit is to “accompany” the complaint.  §6853(a)(1).  A thing cannot “accompany” that of which it is already a part.&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Indeed, Delaware’s Legislature apparently felt so strongly about the affidavit not being part of the complaint that it mandated &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; separation: By statute, the affidavit must be filed in its own sealed envelope, alongside (but apart from) the complaint.  See &lt;em&gt;ibid.&lt;/em&gt;  Nor do the Federal Rules suggest that affidavits of the nature specified by the Delaware law &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; qualify as “pleadings.”  Rule 7, which sets forth a list of “[p]leadings [a]llowed” in federal court, does not include an “affidavit” (or anything like it) on its list.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Pulling these threads together, Delaware’s law, as interpreted by the Delaware Supreme Court, requires judges to account for a matter &lt;em&gt;outside the pleadings&lt;/em&gt;—&lt;em&gt;i.e., &lt;/em&gt;the existence or sufficiency of an affidavit of merit (or lack thereof )—when deciding whether to dismiss a medical malpractice case.  Rule 12(d), however, forbids such extraneous considerations.  And Rule 12 is valid under the Rules Enabling Act (for similar reasons as the Court lays out in its opinion, see &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 10–11).  So Delaware’s law cannot be enforced in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As far as I can tell, then, there is no daylight between my view of the Rule 12 conflict and the majority’s assessment.  But far from “reinforc[ing]” a conflict with Rule 8, &lt;em&gt;ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 5, our shared evaluation of Rule 12 is, to me, yet another reason why Delaware’s law is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in conflict with Rule 8.  See Part II–B, &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt;.  The conflicts analysis concerning these two Rules is based on diametrically opposed characterizations of Delaware’s affidavit of merit: The affidavit must be &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; a “matter outside the pleadings” (and thus §6853 conflicts with Rule 12, per the Delaware Supreme Court’s decision in &lt;em&gt;Hall&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;or &lt;/em&gt;it is part of what the pleadings must contain (giving rise to the purported conflict with Rule 8).  A coherent conflicts analysis cannot have it both ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;*  *  *&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Read for what they are—by their “plain meaning,” sensitive to context yet without distortions created by the task of checking for a conflict, see &lt;em&gt;Walker&lt;/em&gt;, 446 U. S., at 750, n. 9; &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt;, 518 U. S., at 427, n. 7—Rules 3 and 12 answer the same questions as Delaware’s affidavit requirement.  That means that the majority and I share the same conclusion: There is a conflict between state law and valid Federal Rules, precluding application of Delaware’s affidavit requirement in federal court.  For the reasons discussed above, I think the majority is wrong to further maintain that §6853 answers the same question as Rule 8.  And I cannot see how the affidavit that the Delaware law requires can be a “matter outside the pleadings” (for Rule 12-conflict purposes) and also part of the “pleadings” (for Rule 8-conflict purposes).  Therefore, I concur only in the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-1ref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;   To the extent that the Court suggests that the Federal Rule’s plain text is all that matters when answering this question, that is not what our precedents hold.  In &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Center for Humanities, Inc&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/518/415"&gt;518 U. S. 415 (1996)&lt;/a&gt;, we explained that Federal Rules must be interpreted not solely based on their text—as the much earlier case of &lt;em&gt;Walker &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Armco Steel Corp.&lt;/em&gt; had suggested in a footnote—but also “with sensitivity to important state interests and regulatory policies,” 518 U. S., at 427, n. 7.  The majority opinion in &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove &lt;/em&gt;subsequently criticized &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt;’s “search for state interests and policies that are ‘important’ ” as “standardless.”  559 U. S., at 405, n. 7.  But five Justices in that case (&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;., a majority) agreed nevertheless with &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt;’s approach to interpreting the Federal Rules in this context.  See 559 U. S., at 437 (Ginsburg, J., dissenting) (writing for three other Justices that the Court should “continue to interpret Federal Rules with awareness of, and sensitivity to, important state regulatory policies”); &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;.,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;at 418 (Stevens, J., concurring in part and concurring in judgment) (explaining that the  Federal Rules “must be interpreted with some degree of ‘sensitivity to important state interests and regulatory policies’ ” (quoting &lt;em&gt;Gasperini&lt;/em&gt;, 518 U. S., at 427, n. 7)).  So, under our precedents, courts must be mindful of state interests and policies when determining whether a Federal Rule conflicts with state law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  The majority contends that its dismissal-focused formulation of the question is the right one because, in this case, “Berk’s lawsuit &lt;em&gt;has &lt;/em&gt;already been filed and docketed,” and “we granted certiorari” on the question “whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed.”  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4, n. 1.  That argument conflates the question presented with the “question” that, under &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt;, is supposed to serve as the linchpin of our conflict analysis.  559 U. S., at 401.  The latter comes not from the facts of the case, but rather from our interpretations of the potentially conflicting state law and Federal Rule.  So, while it may be that the &lt;em&gt;question presented&lt;/em&gt; is “whether Berk’s lawsuit may be dismissed,” the relevant question for our &lt;em&gt;Shady Grove&lt;/em&gt; analysis is “what is required to start a medical malpractice case,” because that is the question that §6853 and, as it happens, Rule 3, “attemp[t] to answer,” &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 399&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Nor is the majority correct that, regardless, I am “ultimately forced to grapple with the question whether Berk’s lawsuit may be ‘dismiss[ed].’ ”   &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 4, n. 1 (alteration in original).  As I stated above, §6853’s conflict with Rule 3 is enough to hold that the law cannot apply in federal court.  And, as I have shown, the Rule 3 analysis is about the commencement of the action, not its dismissal.  Once we determine that §6853 and Rule 3 answer the same commencement-related question, §6853 cannot apply in federal court, meaning that Berk’s lawsuit cannot be thwarted for failure to satisfy the requirements of that state law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  Proving this point, another provision of the Delaware law, §6853(a)(4), provides that a defendant is “not required to take any action with respect to the complaint . . . until 20 days after plaintiff has filed the affidavit.”  Under the Federal Rules, however, the deadline for a responsive act by the defendant is anchored to the filing of the complaint.  See &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_4#rule_4_m) "&gt;Fed. Rules Civ. Proc. 4(m) &lt;/a&gt;(a plaintiff must serve the complaint and summons “within 90 days after the complaint is filed”) and 12(a)(1)(A)(i) (a defendant “must serve an answer . . . within 21 days after being served with the summons and complaint”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-4ref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;  The majority’s description of Rule 8’s work is inaccurate even if confined to the universe of pleadings.  Rule 8 does not “addres[s] &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; information a plaintiff must provide about the merits of his claim” in the pleadings.  &lt;em&gt;Ante,&lt;/em&gt; at 6 (emphasis added).  Instead, with respect to a pleading that states a claim for relief (as opposed to one that does not, see Rule 7), Rule 8 governs &lt;em&gt;how much&lt;/em&gt; a plaintiff must say concerning his claim.  Rule 8’s primary purpose is to install a “simplified pleading system” that requires a complaint to include nothing more than “ ‘short and plain statement[s]’ ” of the claim, the grounds for jurisdiction, and the relief sought.  &lt;em&gt;Swierkiewicz&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Sorema N. A.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/534/506"&gt;534 U. S. 506&lt;/a&gt;, 512, 514 (2002).  In other words, Rule 8’s innovation is the “short and plain” bit, not the substance of what is required to be stated in that manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-5ref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;  The answer, under the Rule, is (1) “a short and plain statement of the grounds for . . . jurisdiction,” (2) “a short and plain statement of the claim showing that the pleader is entitled to relief,” and (3) “a demand for the relief sought.”  Rule 8(a).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-6ref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;  To be sure, many Courts of Appeals have also relied on a conflict with Rule 8 to hold that state affidavit-of-merit laws like Delaware’s do not apply in federal court.  See &lt;em&gt;Albright&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Christensen&lt;/em&gt;, 24 F. 4th 1039, 1048–1049 (CA6 2022); &lt;em&gt;Gallivan&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/943_F.3d_291"&gt;943 F. 3d 291&lt;/a&gt;, 293 (CA6 2019); &lt;em&gt;Pledger&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Lynch&lt;/em&gt;, 5 F. 4th 511, 519 (CA4 2021); &lt;em&gt;Young&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/942_F.3d_349"&gt;942 F. 3d 349&lt;/a&gt;, 351 (CA7 2019).  But a closer look at the relevant cases reveals that these courts, like the majority, got there by manipulating the relevant question.  In &lt;em&gt;Gallivan&lt;/em&gt;, for example, the Sixth Circuit posed as the pertinent question: “[D]oes someone need an affidavit of merit to state a claim for medical negligence?”  &lt;a href="/rio/citation/943_F.3d_293"&gt;943 F. 3d, at 293&lt;/a&gt;.  This leading question not only ignores (as the majority does) that Rule 8 is solely about “pleadings,” but, worse, also preordains a conflict by naming the very thing that the state law requires but the Federal Rule does not (&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;., an affidavit).  The Fourth and Seventh Circuits make the same error.  See &lt;em&gt;Pledger&lt;/em&gt;, 5 F. 4th, at 519 (asking “whether a medical malpractice plaintiff must provide pre-suit expert support for his claim”); &lt;em&gt;Young&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/942_F.3d_351"&gt;942 F. 3d, at 351&lt;/a&gt; (asking whether Rule 8 “require[s] attachments”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#CONCUR_5-7ref"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;  To be sure, plaintiffs can, in limited contexts, “incorporat[e]” certain documents “into the complaint by reference.”  &lt;em&gt;Tellabs, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;MakorIssues &amp;amp; Rights, Ltd.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/551/308"&gt;551 U. S. 308&lt;/a&gt;, 322 (2007).  But the affidavit of merit is not such a document because its content is neither discoverable nor admissible.  See §6853(d).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'notes' content area --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/main&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808"&gt;Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 24-808 argued date: November 4, 2025  decided date: January 20, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main class="container-fluid" id="main"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: center;"&gt; CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="#tab_default_1"&gt;
                        Supreme Court &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'text' content area --&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON&lt;br/&gt;109 F. 4th 438, affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syllabus&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-808_SYLLABUS"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Syllabus]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-808.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion&lt;/strong&gt;, Alito &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-808_OPINION_4"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Alito Opinion]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-808.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurrence&lt;/strong&gt;, Sotomayor &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-24-808_CONCUR_5"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[Sotomayor Concurrence]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="/supct/pdf/24-808.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; [PDF] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued. The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader. See &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Detroit Timber &amp;amp; Lumber Co.,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/200/321"&gt;200 U. S. 321&lt;/a&gt;, 337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center; text-align: justify;"&gt;Syllabus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; BURTON, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;chapter &lt;/span&gt;7&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; trustee for&lt;/span&gt; VISTA-PRO AUTOMOTIVE, LLC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the sixth circuit &lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;No. 24–808. Argued November 4, 2025—Decided January 20, 2026&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;The question in this case is whether &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60#rule_60_c_1"&gt;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1)&lt;/a&gt;’s requirement that parties make Rule 60(b) motions within a “reasonable time” applies to a motion seeking relief from an allegedly void judgment under Rule 60(b)(4).  Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, entered bankruptcy in 2014 and initiated adversarial proceedings against Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc., to collect $50,000 in allegedly unpaid invoices.  Vista-Pro attempted to serve process on Coney Island by mail but purportedly failed to comply with &lt;a href="/rules/frbp/rule_7004#rule_7004_b_3"&gt;Federal Rule of Bankruptcy Procedure 7004(b)(3)&lt;/a&gt;’s mail-service requirements.  Coney Island did not file an answer, and the Bankruptcy Court entered a default judgment.  Over the next six years, Vista-Pro’s bankruptcy trustee attempted to enforce the judgment.  These efforts bore fruit in 2021 when a marshal seized funds from Coney Island’s bank account in satisfaction of the judgment.  Coney Island filed a motion to vacate the judgment under &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60"&gt;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60&lt;/a&gt;, arguing that Vista-Pro’s failure to make proper service rendered the judgment void.  The Bankruptcy Court denied relief, holding that Coney Island failed to abide by Rule 60’s requirement that parties make motions for relief within a “reasonable time.”  The District Court and the Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Held&lt;/em&gt;: Rule 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).  Pp. 2–6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; (a) The plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) provides that a “motion under Rule 60(b) must be made within a reasonable time,” and because a motion  for relief from an allegedly void judgment is a “motion under Rule 60(b),” the reasonable-time limit applies.  The structure of Rule 60 confirms the plain-text interpretation.  Rule 60 expressly modifies the default reasonable-time limit, imposing a one-year limit on Rule 60(b) motions alleging mistakes, new evidence, or fraud.  Yet the Rule does not include an analogous unlimited-time principle for motions alleging voidness.  Pp. 2–3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; (b) The Court rejects the argument that because a “void judgment is a legal nullity,” &lt;em&gt;United Student Aid Funds, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Espinosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/260"&gt;559 U. S. 260&lt;/a&gt;, 270, no time limit should apply.  Even if the passage of time cannot cure voidness, the same principle holds true for most legal errors, yet statutes and rules routinely limit the time during which a party can seek relief from a judgment infected by error.  A party would need to show that some principle of law, such as the Due Process Clause, gives a party the right to allege voidness at any time, but Coney Island disclaims any such argument, and the Court cannot divine any such principle.  Allowing parties to allege voidness at any time would have extreme implications, such as allowing parties to ignore deadlines for filing notices of appeal or petitions for certiorari when subject-matter jurisdiction is contested.  The possibility that improper service is different from other legal errors because a party might not learn about proceedings until long after judgment issues does not help Coney Island.  Rule 60(c)(1) accommodates such a scenario by imposing a reasonable-time requirement rather than a fixed time limit.  In the context of a default judgment, it might be reasonable for a defendant not to seek relief before learning about a plaintiff’s attempted enforcement.  Pp. 3–5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; (c) The Court rejects Coney Island’s argument that courts have historically allowed litigants to seek relief from void judgments at any time.  No such historical consensus exists, and in any event, for Rule 60(b) motions, the Rule’s text and structure take priority over historical practice.  The Court also rejects Coney Island’s reliance on &lt;em&gt;Insurance Corp. of Ireland&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Compagnie des Bauxites de Guinee&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/456/694"&gt;456 U. S. 694&lt;/a&gt;, as that case undermines Coney Island’s plea for no time limits.  Lastly, the Court rejects Coney Island’s invocation of policy concerns, Rule 60’s drafting history, and the canon of constitutional avoidance.  To the extent that these interpretive tools carry any weight, they do so only when a Rule’s language is ambiguous.  Pp. 5–6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;109 F. 4th 438, affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Alito&lt;/span&gt;, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Roberts&lt;/span&gt;, C. J., and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Thomas&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Kagan&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Gorsuch&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Kavanaugh&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Barrett&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Jackson&lt;/span&gt;, JJ., joined.  &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Sotomayor&lt;/span&gt;, J., filed an opinion concurring in the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the United States Reports. Readers are requested to notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Washington, D. C. 20543, pio@supremecourt.gov, of any typographical or other formal errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–808&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC., PETITIONER &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; JEANNE ANN BURTON, CHAPTER 7 TRUSTEE FOR VISTA-PRO AUTOMOTIVE, LLC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the sixth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Alito&lt;/span&gt; delivered the opinion of the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; A party seeking relief from an allegedly void judgment may file a motion under &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60#rule_60_b_4"&gt;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(b)(4)&lt;/a&gt;.  Rule 60(c)(1) requires parties to make Rule 60(b) motions within a “reasonable time.”  We hold that this time limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, entered bankruptcy in 2014.  As part of its bankruptcy litigation, Vista-Pro initiated adversarial proceedings against Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc., to collect $50,000 in allegedly unpaid invoices.  Vista-Pro attempted to serve process on Coney Island by mail, but in doing so, it purportedly failed to comply with the mail-service requirements in &lt;a href="/rules/frbp/rule_7004#rule_7004_b_3"&gt;Federal Rule of Bankruptcy Procedure 7004(b)(3)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Coney Island did not file an answer in the adversarial proceedings, and the Bankruptcy Court entered a default judgment against the company in 2015.  Over the next six years, Vista-Pro’s bankruptcy trustee attempted to enforce  that judgment against Coney Island.  As part of these efforts, the trustee sent a demand letter to the company’s CEO in April 2016.  Lower courts concluded that this letter gave Coney Island notice of the judgment and the trustee’s enforcement efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; These efforts bore fruit in 2021 when a marshal seized funds from Coney Island’s bank account in satisfaction of the judgment.  In response, Coney Island filed a motion to vacate the judgment under &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60"&gt;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60&lt;/a&gt;.  According to Coney Island, Vista-Pro’s failure to make proper service rendered the judgment void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Bankruptcy Court denied relief.  It held that Coney Island failed to abide by Rule 60’s requirement that parties make motions for relief within a “reasonable time.”  The District Court and Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit affirmed.  We granted certiorari&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;to resolve a split of authority on whether Rule 60’s reasonable-time limit applies to motions seeking relief from allegedly void judgments.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  605 U. S. ___ (2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60"&gt;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60&lt;/a&gt; permits a court to “relieve a party . . . from a final judgment, order, or proceeding,” and subdivision (b)(4) specifically authorizes a court to  grant relief from a “void” judgment.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Parties may seek relief under Rule 60 by filing a motion with the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Rule 60 also imposes a time limit for such motions.  Rule 60(c)(1) provides that a “motion under Rule 60(b) must be made within a reasonable time.”  Because a motion for relief from an allegedly void judgment is a “motion under Rule 60(b),” the reasonable-time limit applies.  Accord, &lt;em&gt;Kemp&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/596/528"&gt;596 U. S. 528&lt;/a&gt;, 533 (2022) (“All [Rule 60(b) motions] must be filed ‘within a reasonable time’ ”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The structure of Rule 60 confirms what the plain text of subdivision (c)(1) provides.  When Rule 60 modifies the default reasonable-time limit, it does so expressly.  For example, Rule 60(c)(1) imposes a 1-year limit on Rule 60(b) motions alleging mistakes, new evidence, or fraud.  Thus, one would expect Rule 60 to include an analogous provision if a special, unlimited-time principle applied to motions alleging voidness.  Cf.&lt;em&gt; Kemp&lt;/em&gt;, 596 U. S., at 534–535.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;But the Rule does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Coney Island, several Courts of Appeals, and a promi- nent treatise nonetheless maintain that Rule 60(c)(1)’s  reasonable-time limit does not apply to motions alleging voidness.  See n. 1, &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt;; 11 C. Wright, A. Miller, &amp;amp; M. Kane, Federal Practice and Procedure §2862, pp. 431–433 (3d ed. 2012).  These authorities acknowledge that their interpretation clashes with Rule 60’s text.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Sea-Land Serv.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Ceramica Europa II&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="/rio/citation/160_F.3d_849"&gt;160 F. 3d 849&lt;/a&gt;, 852 (CA1 1998).  But relying on the generally accepted maxim that a “void judgment is a legal nullity,” &lt;em&gt;United Student Aid Funds, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Espinosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/559/260"&gt;559 U. S. 260&lt;/a&gt;, 270 (2010), they argue that the passage of time cannot turn such a nullity into an enforceable judgment.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Austin &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Smith&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/312_F.2d_337"&gt;312 F. 2d 337&lt;/a&gt;, 343 (CADC 1962).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  This argument cannot bear the weight that Coney Island and others have placed on it.  Even if the passage of time cannot cure voidness, the same principle holds true for most legal errors.  Nevertheless, statutes and rules routinely limit the time during which a party can seek relief from a judgment infected by error.  Therefore, a party in Coney Island’s position would need to show that some principle of law, such as the Due Process Clause, gives a party the right to allege voidness at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Coney Island disclaims any such argument, and we cannot divine any principle requiring courts to keep their doors perpetually open to allegations of voidness.  Giving a party a “reasonable” time to seek relief from an allegedly void judgment may well be all that due process demands.  By contrast, the argument that a party may allege voidness at any time, if taken to its logical conclusion, would have extreme implications.  For example, if a federal district court erroneously concluded that it possessed subject-matter jurisdiction and proceeded to enter a judgment, the adversely affected party could wait as long as it wanted before filing a notice of appeal.  But see &lt;a href="/rules/frap/rule_4#rule_4_a_1"&gt;Fed. Rule App. Proc. 4(a)(1)&lt;/a&gt;.  Similarly, if a federal court of appeals erroneously asserted subject-matter jurisdiction, the adversely affected party would not be required to comply with the deadline for filing a petition for a writ of certiorari imposed by this Court’s Rule 13.  It is hard to accept the proposition that due process requires such a regime.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  Coney Island maintains that the alleged defect in this&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;case—failure to perform proper service—is different from other legal errors that might render a judgment void.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Coney Island emphasizes that when a party does not receive proper service, it might not learn about the proceedings until long after the judgment issues.  But this possibility does not help Coney Island’s position.  Rule 60(c)(1) accommodates such a scenario by imposing a reasonable-time requirement, rather than a fixed time limit.  And in the context of a default judgment, it might be reasonable for a defendant not to seek relief before learning about a plaintiff ’s attempted enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Coney Island separately contends that courts have historically allowed litigants to seek relief from void judgments at any time.  But the historical record is not so clear.  To be sure, courts have granted relief from void judgments long after their entry, especially when the issuing court lacked jurisdiction over the defendant.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Harris&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hardeman&lt;/em&gt;, 14 How. 334, 338, 344–346 (1853) (affirming a lower court order that set aside a judgment 11 years after its issuance where the plaintiff did not make proper service and the defendant did not appear).  But there was no historical consensus that a party could request such relief at &lt;em&gt;any &lt;/em&gt;time.  Some courts, for instance, concluded that laches or other time limits could bar relief, even when a litigant alleged voidness.  &lt;em&gt;E.g&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Stocking &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Hanson&lt;/em&gt;, 35 Minn. 207, 211–212, 28 N. W. 507, 507–508 (1886); &lt;em&gt;Smith &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Jones&lt;/em&gt;, 174 Cal. 513, 515–517, 163 P. 890, 890–892 (1917).  In any event, for Rule 60(b) motions, the Rule’s “text and structure” take priority over historical practice.&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  See &lt;em&gt;Honeycutt&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/581/443"&gt;581 U. S. 443&lt;/a&gt;, 453 (2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  Coney Island turns next to this Court’s decision in &lt;em&gt;Insurance Corp. of Ireland&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Compagnie des Bauxites de Guinee&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/456/694"&gt;456 U. S. 694 (1982)&lt;/a&gt;.  There, we explained that a defendant seeking to dispute personal jurisdiction is “always free to ignore the judicial proceedings, risk a default judgment, and then challenge that judgment . . . in a collateral proceeding.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 706.  Citing this sentence, Coney Island argues that defendants need not comply with time limits when alleging a lack of personal jurisdiction.  But &lt;em&gt;Insurance Corp&lt;/em&gt;. also recognized that the “expression of legal rights is often subject to certain procedural rules,” and “the failure to enter a timely objection” may result in the loss of a legal right.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 705.  Thus, &lt;em&gt;Insurance Corp.&lt;/em&gt; undermines Coney Island’s plea for no time limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Coney Island lastly invokes policy concerns, Rule 60’s drafting history, and the canon of constitutional avoidance.  To the extent that these interpretive tools carry any weight, they do so only when a Rule’s language is ambiguous.  See &lt;em&gt;BP p.l.c.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Mayor and City Council of Baltimore&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/593/230"&gt;593 U. S. 230&lt;/a&gt;, 245 (2021); &lt;em&gt;Milner&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Department of Navy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/562/562"&gt;562 U. S. 562&lt;/a&gt;, 572 (2011); &lt;em&gt;Van Buren&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/593/374"&gt;593 U. S. 374&lt;/a&gt;, 393–394 (2021).  Here, the operative language clearly requires parties to make Rule 60(b) motions within a reasonable time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Litigants seeking relief under Rule 60(b)(4) must comply with Rule 60(c)(1) and file a motion within a reasonable time.  Coney Island does not contend that it complied with this requirement.  Therefore, we need not expound on whether Coney Island’s timing was reasonable.  The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit is affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt; It is so ordered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;  Compare &lt;em&gt;In re Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC&lt;/em&gt;, 109 F. 4th 438, 444 (CA6 2024) (case below), with &lt;em&gt;Austin &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Smith&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/312_F.2d_337"&gt;312 F. 2d 337&lt;/a&gt;, 343 (CADC 1962); &lt;em&gt;V. T. A.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Airco&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;a href="/rio/citation/597_F.2d_220"&gt;597 F. 2d 220&lt;/a&gt;, 224, and n. 9 (CA10 1979); &lt;em&gt;Rodd &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Region Constr. Co.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/783_F.2d_89"&gt;783 F. 2d 89&lt;/a&gt;, 91 (CA7 1986);&lt;em&gt; Hertz Corp. &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Alamo Rent-A-Car, Inc.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/16_F.3d_1126"&gt;16 F. 3d 1126&lt;/a&gt;, 1130 (CA11 1994);&lt;em&gt; Sea-Land Serv.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc.&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Ceramica Europa II&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Inc.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/160_F.3d_849"&gt;160 F. 3d 849&lt;/a&gt;, 852 (CA1 1998); &lt;em&gt;United States &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;One Toshiba Color Television&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/213_F.3d_147"&gt;213 F. 3d 147&lt;/a&gt;, 157–158 (CA3 2000) (en banc);&lt;em&gt; Jackson &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;FIE Corp.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="/rio/citation/302_F.3d_515"&gt;302 F. 3d 515&lt;/a&gt;, 523 (CA5 2002).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-3ref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;  Rule 60 governs motions to set aside default judgments, &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_55#rule_55_c"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 55(c)&lt;/a&gt;, including those issued in bankruptcy proceedings, Fed. Rules Bkrtcy. Proc. 7055 and 9024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-4ref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Justice Sotomayor&lt;/span&gt; contends that we should abstain from addressing any potential due-process considerations.  &lt;em&gt;Post&lt;/em&gt;, at 1 (opinion concurring in judgment).  Although Coney Island disclaims any constitutional argument, it cites a longstanding consensus of authority holding that a party may allege voidness at any time despite the contrary language in Rule 60.  And the only possible basis for such a holding is a rule of constitutional law that prevents the imposition of the Rule’s reasonable-time requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-5ref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;  We express no view on whether the allegedly defective service in this case would render the judgment void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#OPINION_4-6ref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;  Rule 60(d) preserves parties’ ability to obtain relief from a judgment in limited ways other than through a Rule 60(b) motion.  We express no view regarding the limits applicable to obtaining relief through one of those methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;&lt;a href="#writing-ZS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Concurrence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;No. 24–808&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;_________________&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC., PETITIONER &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt; JEANNE ANN BURTON, CHAPTER 7 TRUSTEE FOR VISTA-PRO AUTOMOTIVE, LLC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the sixth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;[January 20, 2026]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Justice Sotomayor&lt;/span&gt;, concurring in the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The Court today rightly holds that a Rule 60(b)(4) motion to set aside a default judgment that is void for lack of personal jurisdiction must be made “within a reasonable time.”  &lt;a href="/rules/frcp/rule_60#rule_60_c_1"&gt;Fed. Rule Civ. Proc. 60(c)(1)&lt;/a&gt;.  Rule 60’s text and structure require that conclusion, as the majority explains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; I concur in the judgment because the majority unnecessarily opines on the potential validity of a constitutional challenge to the “reasonable time” limit under the Due Process Clause.  &lt;em&gt;Ante&lt;/em&gt;, at 4.  Coney Island did not make this argument below and the Sixth Circuit did not pass upon it.  See &lt;em&gt;In re Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC&lt;/em&gt;, 109 F. 4th 438, 443 (2024) (“Coney Island does not mount a constitutional attack on Rule 60”).  In this Court, Coney Island expressly disclaimed any due process argument.  See Brief for Petitioner 22 (“To be clear, Coney Island does not contend that Rule 60 or Rule 60(c)(1) [is] unconstitutional”).  This Court does “not generally entertain arguments that were not raised below and are not advanced in this Court by any party.”  &lt;em&gt;Burwell&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hobby Lobby Stores, Inc.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/573/682"&gt;573 U. S. 682&lt;/a&gt;, 721 (2014).  There is no reason to depart from that practice absent unusual circumstances, which certainly are not present here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'notes' content area --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/main&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KLEIN v. MARTIN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51"&gt;Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 25-51 argued date:   decided date: January 26, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main class="container-fluid" id="main"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: center;"&gt; KLEIN v. MARTIN &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="#tab_default_1"&gt;
                        Supreme Court &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'text' content area --&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;hr/&gt;TOP
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Per Curiam&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;CHRISTOPHER KLEIN, SUPERINTENDENT, DEPARTMENT OF DETENTION FACILITIES  FOR ANNE ARUNDEL COUNTY, &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;et al.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;v.&lt;/em&gt;  CHARLES BRANDON MARTIN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;on petition for writ of certiorari to the united states court of appeals for the fourth circuit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;div&gt;No. 25–51. Decided January 26, 2026&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt; Per Curiam&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (AEDPA), strict standards govern the grant of federal habeas relief to prisoners convicted in state court.  Faithful application of those standards sometimes puts federal district courts and courts of appeals in the disagreeable position of having to deny relief in cases they would have analyzed differently if they had been in the shoes of the relevant state court.  But federal courts are dutybound to comply with AEDPA, and we have granted summary relief when the lower courts have departed from the role AEDPA assigns.  See, &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;., &lt;em&gt;Clark&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Sweeney&lt;/em&gt;, 607 U. S. ___ (2025) (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;); &lt;em&gt;Dunn&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Reeves&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/594/731"&gt;594 U. S. 731 (2021)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;); &lt;em&gt;Mays&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Hines&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/592/385"&gt;592 U. S. 385 (2021)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;); &lt;em&gt;Virginia&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;LeBlanc&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/582/91"&gt;582 U. S. 91 (2017)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;); &lt;em&gt;White&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Wheeler&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/577/73"&gt;577 U. S. 73 (2015)&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This is such a case.  Respondent Charles Brandon Martin was convicted in a Maryland court for the attempted murder of one of his girlfriends, Jodi Torok.  The evidence against him was strong, his conviction was affirmed on appeal, and an appellate court held in a state postconviction proceeding that the State’s failure to disclose certain impeachment evidence that was favorable under &lt;em&gt;Brady &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Maryland&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/373/83"&gt;373 U. S. 83 (1963)&lt;/a&gt;, did not warrant a new trial because there was no “reasonable probability that the result of [the] trial would have been different” had the  evidence been turned over.  App. to Pet. for Cert. 115a (App.); see &lt;em&gt;Kyles &lt;/em&gt;v.&lt;em&gt; Whitley&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/514/419"&gt;514 U. S. 419&lt;/a&gt;, 434 (1995) (the “touchstone of materiality is a ‘reasonable probability’ of a different result”).  Because that decision neither was “contrary to” nor “involved an unreasonable application” of “clearly established Federal law,” AEDPA required the denial of Martin’s federal habeas petition.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2254#d_1"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2254(d)(1)&lt;/a&gt;.  Yet the Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit affirmed the award of a new trial based on reasoning that departed from what AEDPA prescribes.  We therefore grant the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: justify; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Torok, the victim of the attempted murder, had been dating Martin for about a year when she told him she was pregnant with a baby she thought was his.  Angered by this news, Martin demanded that Torok have an abortion.  She refused and informed him that she intended to go to court to compel him to provide child support.  She also threatened to tell his “wife or baby mama” about the child.  App. 254a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; A few weeks later, Martin sent Torok a text message asking: “ ‘What time do u work[?]’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;State&lt;/em&gt;, 218 Md. App. 1, 14, 96 A. 3d 765, 773 (2014) (alteration in original).  Torok replied, “ ‘I’m off [today],’ ” thus verifying that she would likely be home.  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;.  Later that day, just before 3 p.m., Torok was alone in her apartment in Crofton, Maryland, speaking on the phone with a close friend, Blair Wolfe, who lived in Pittsburgh.  During their call, a man purporting to be a salesman knocked on Torok’s front door.  Torok hung up to speak to the man but promised to call Wolfe back.  When she did not, Wolfe called her several times, but no one answered.  Growing increasingly concerned, Wolfe called Torok’s housemate, Jessica Higgs, and asked her to return home to see if Torok was safe.  Higgs found Torok unconscious on the floor, bleeding from a gunshot wound to  her head.  Torok survived, but her unborn baby did not, and Torok suffered serious permanent injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; When the police examined the scene of the shooting, they found no sign of forced entry and recovered several items of evidentiary value from the floor near where Torok lay: a shell casing and bullet from a .380-caliber cartridge and a peculiarly modified Gatorade bottle.  (Photos of this bottle appear in the appendix to this opinion.)  The upper part of the bottle was covered with two layers of tape, white medical tape underneath and silver duct tape on top.  There was a rectangular hole in the tape over the mouth of the bottle and a jagged hole at the bottom of the bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Circumstantial evidence strongly suggested that this object was likely brought to the apartment and left there by Torok’s assailant.  Higgs testified that the bottle was not on the floor when she left for work that morning.  Both Torok and Higgs testified that they did not drink Gatorade or keep it at home, and both said that they would not have left a bottle on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The three items found at the crime scene played a part in the State’s case.  Federal firearms records showed that Martin owned a .380-caliber semiautomatic handgun that could have fired the bullet and ejected the casing.  One of Martin’s girlfriends testified that she had seen him with a “small” “semiautomatic” gun in the weeks before the shooting.  App&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; 379a.  Michael Bradley, the brother of still another of Martin’s girlfriends, Maggie McFadden, added that on several occasions he had seen Martin with a “small” “semi-automatic gun.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 331a–333a, 371a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As for the bottle, the State offered evidence suggesting that it was a homemade silencer.  A police sergeant said that the tape on the mouth of the bottle bore a “rectangular impression” that likely resulted from something being “stuck in there.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 292a.  The bottle was available for examination by the jury, and the State argued that the opening in the tape was shaped like the muzzle of a  semiautomatic handgun.  The State also noted that the edges of the hole at the bottom of the bottle were bent outward, suggesting that the hole had been created by a force emanating from inside the bottle.  The police sergeant testified that the bottle resembled homemade silencing devices he had seen in a film and in online videos.  A detective testified that he found “black soot” inside the bottle, &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 310a–311a, but that he did not smell burnt or burning marijuana in the bottle, &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 314a–315a, and another witness testified that he found no “signs or evidence of controlled dangerous substances” in the bottle, &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 309.  Based on this evidence and the fact that none of Torok’s neighbors had heard a gunshot at the apartment on the afternoon of the shooting, the State argued that the bottle had been used as a silencer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Testing of the bottle revealed DNA evidence that strongly implicated Martin.  A hair was found on the tape on the bottle, and one of the State’s expert witnesses, a forensic scientist, determined that although the hair could not have come from 99.94 percent of the population of North America, she could not rule out Martin as the source of hair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Besides the DNA taken from the hair, trace DNA from at least three persons, including at least one male, was found on the mouth of the bottle.  A forensic chemist testified that she could rule out 96 percent of the black population as potential sources of this DNA but could not rule out Martin (who is black).&lt;a href="#PERCURIAM_2-2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; This DNA evidence linking Martin to the bottle was bolstered by the testimony of Michael Bradley.  Bradley testified that on the afternoon of the shooting, he, his brother Frank, Martin, and an acquaintance named Jerry Burks smoked marijuana at McFadden’s home.  At one point, according to Michael, Frank went upstairs and came back with white “medical tape.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 337a.  Martin and Frank  then went upstairs together.  Frank came downstairs, grabbed a Gatorade bottle, and headed back up the stairs with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Based on this testimony, the State suggested that Martin helped to make the bottle into the silencing device that the shooter used.  This theory was supported by the discovery in the McFadden home of the same kind of white medical tape that was affixed to the bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Michael Bradley further testified that Martin acted suspiciously at the time of and shortly after the shooting.  According to his testimony, Martin and Burks left the house together before 2 p.m. and were still out when he returned from picking up his niece at around 3 p.m.  Martin and Burks eventually reappeared together some time before 6:30 p.m.  Martin then handed Frank Bradley a “brown paper bag” and told him to “get rid of this.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 353a.  The State suggested that this bag contained the hit weapon, which was never found.  Neither did police ever find the .380-caliber pistol that, according to federal firearms records and witness testimony, Martin owned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In addition to all this evidence, Sheri Carter, another of Martin’s girlfriends, testified for the State.  Carter said that Martin had kept at her home a laptop that he said he had obtained from a former employer.  She testified that she had seen Martin “looking up gun silencers” on this laptop not long before the shooting.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 377a.  Martin, she asserted, took the laptop from her apartment after the shooting and “got rid of it” “in case [the] apartment got searched,” because he “didn’t want it found there.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 378a–379a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The trial judge instructed the jury that Martin could be found guilty if he had “ ‘aided’ ” or “ ‘encouraged’ ” the attempted murder and assault with the intent that the crime succeed.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 79a.  The jury found him guilty as an accessory before the fact.  The court sentenced him to life in prison, and his conviction and sentence were affirmed on direct appeal.  &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt;, 218 Md. App. 1, 96 A. 3d 765.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt; B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Martin then sought postconviction relief in state court.  He argued that the State had violated his right to due process by failing to disclose a forensic report that had analyzed five computers found at his home.  One of these machines, a laptop, had been issued to Martin by a former employer.  The report found no evidence that this laptop had been used since 2005, and it noted that a keyword search for words such as “ ‘Handgun,’ ” “ ‘Gatorade,’ ” “ ‘silencer,’ ” and “ ‘Homemade silencer’ ” had yielded no hits.  App. 103a–104a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Martin argued that this computer was the one to which Carter had referred in her testimony and that the report tended to discredit her claim that he had used the laptop at her home to research silencers.  The postconviction court agreed and ordered a new trial, but a unanimous panel of the Maryland Court of Special Appeals reversed on the ground that the report was not material.  Based on its review of the whole record, the court concluded that even if the report had “totally discredit[ed]” Carter, the other evidence linking Martin to the crime was so “strong” that there was no “reasonable probability that the result of his trial would have been different.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 112a, 115a.  The State’s high court denied review, &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;State&lt;/em&gt;, 466 Md. 554, 222 A. 3d 1075 (2020) (table), as did this Court, see &lt;em&gt;Martin&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Maryland&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/590/973"&gt;590 U. S. 973 (2020)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;C&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Martin sought habeas relief in federal court, and the District Court granted his petition based on the State’s failure to disclose the forensic report.  A sharply divided panel of the Fourth Circuit affirmed.  The majority acknowledged that the state appellate court had correctly stated the rule on materiality set out in our decisions and had claimed to apply that rule.  Yet the majority concluded that the state court had not actually done what it said it did—had not held  that there was no “reasonable probability” that the disclosure of the forensic report would have changed the verdict—but instead had applied the sufficiency-of-the-evidence rule that we condemned in &lt;em&gt;Kyles&lt;/em&gt;.  App. 21a–22a; see 514 U. S., at 434–435&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(a &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; claimant need not show that, “after discounting the inculpatory evidence in light of the undisclosed evidence, there would not have been enough left to convict”).  According to the majority, the state court “never engaged” with some evidence, “disregarded or misconstrued” other evidence, and failed to assess in a “nuanced” way the evidence it did discuss.  App. 24a–26a.  The majority then ruled that no fairminded jurist could agree with the state court’s decision.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 27a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Judge Niemeyer dissented, contending that the majority had defied AEDPA’s standard of review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: justify; text-align: center;"&gt;A&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; As we have noted many times, AEDPA sharply limits federal review of habeas claims raised by state prisoners.  A federal court may grant habeas relief on a claim that a state court resolved on the merits only when the state court’s “decision” was “contrary to, or involved an unreasonable application of, clearly established Federal law,” or “was based on an unreasonable determination of the facts in light of the evidence presented” in state court.  &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/28/2254#d"&gt;28 U. S. C. §2254(d)&lt;/a&gt;.  These standards require federal courts to give the “benefit of the doubt” to merits decisions issued by the courts of the sovereign States.  &lt;em&gt;Woodford&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Visciotti&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/537/19"&gt;537 U. S. 19&lt;/a&gt;, 24 (2002) (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;).  AEDPA review provides an important but limited safeguard: It protects against “ ‘extreme malfunctions’ ” in the state courts’ adjudication of constitutional claims.  &lt;em&gt;Harrington&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Richter&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/562/86"&gt;562 U. S. 86&lt;/a&gt;, 102 (2011).  So in order to obtain federal habeas relief, a state prisoner must “show far more” than “ ‘clear error.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Shinn&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Kayer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/592/111"&gt;592 U. S. 111&lt;/a&gt;, 118 (2020) (&lt;em&gt;per curiam&lt;/em&gt;) (quoting &lt;em&gt;LeBlanc&lt;/em&gt;,  582 U. S., at 94).  The habeas claimant must instead establish that the state court “blunder[ed] so badly that every fairminded jurist would disagree” with the decision.  &lt;em&gt;Mays&lt;/em&gt;, 592 U. S., at 392.  Only then is a decision “so lacking in justification” that its error precludes even the “possibility for fairminded” dispute.  &lt;em&gt;Richter&lt;/em&gt;, 562 U. S., at 103.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; “If this rule means anything,” we have said, it means that a federal court must “carefully consider all the reasons and evidence supporting the state court’s decision.”  &lt;em&gt;Mays&lt;/em&gt;, 592 U. S., at 391.  That requirement is pivotal because federal courts have “no authority to impose mandatory opinion-writing standards on state courts.”  &lt;em&gt;Johnson&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Williams&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/568/289"&gt;568 U. S. 289&lt;/a&gt;, 300 (2013).  And a state court “need not make detailed findings addressing all the evidence before it.”  &lt;em&gt;Miller-El&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Cockrell&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/537/322"&gt;537 U. S. 322&lt;/a&gt;, 347 (2003).  Indeed, AEDPA requires deference even if the state court does not discuss the evidence at all.  &lt;em&gt;Richter&lt;/em&gt;, 562 U. S., at 99.  What matters under §2254(d)(1)—the standard relevant here—is whether a decision is contrary to, or involves an unreasonable application of, this Court’s holdings, not whether the state court’s opinion satisfies the federal court’s opinion-writing standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority contravened these well-settled principles in two ways.  First, it grounded its holding that the state appellate court applied the wrong legal rule on its conclusion that the state court had not actually applied the materiality test that it clearly invoked.  Second, it erred in holding that no fairminded jurist could find the forensic report on the computer to be immaterial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority first erred in holding that the state appellate court failed to apply the right rule for &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; materiality.  Undisclosed evidence is material if it could  reasonably have “ ‘put the whole case in such a different light as to undermine confidence in the verdict.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Strickler &lt;/em&gt;v. &lt;em&gt;Greene&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/527/263"&gt;527 U. S. 263&lt;/a&gt;, 290 (1999).  But when the evidence could not have reasonably had such an effect, it is not material, and its erroneous nondisclosure does not justify relief.  Under this rule, even if undisclosed evidence “entirely discredit[s]” a prosecution witness, the failure to turn over the evidence is not material if “considerable” other evidence “link[s]” the defendant to the crime and the record provides “strong support” that the defendant would have been convicted anyway.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 292–294.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The state appellate court applied these rules instead of a sufficiency-of-the-evidence test.  The state court accurately summarized our &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; precedents, correctly stated the governing rule on materiality, and stated unequivocally that its decision was based on that rule.  It recounted salient trial evidence, acknowledged where the State’s theory of the case was “attenuated,” and said that the disclosure of the forensic report would likely have eliminated any adverse inference based on the concealment of evidence.  App. 114a–115a, and n. 14.  It also assumed that the jury would have “totally discredit[ed]” Carter’s testimony had the State disclosed the report.  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 112a.  Yet based on its review of the “ ‘entire record,’ ” the court found that the evidence “linking” Martin to the crime was so “strong” that there was no “reasonable probability that the result of his trial would have been different.”  &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;., at 109a–110a, 112a, 115a.  That standard was legally correct.  And except when it was quoting our precedent, the state court did not use words like “sufficient,” “insufficient,” “adequate,” or “inadequate” in analyzing the &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority nonetheless held that the state appellate court applied the wrong rule because that court failed to discuss certain evidence that tended to undermine the State’s case and because its analysis was not sufficiently “nuanced.”  App. 24a–26a.  That holding was a basic  misapplication of AEDPA, which bars federal courts from imposing opinion-writing standards on state courts and demands that the relevant state-court decision be given the “benefit of the doubt.”  &lt;em&gt;Woodford&lt;/em&gt;, 537 U. S., at 24.  The majority’s “readiness to attribute error” to the state appellate court despite that court’s correct citation and synthesis of our precedent was both “inconsistent with the presumption that state courts know and follow the law” and “incompatible with §2254(d)’s ‘highly deferential standard for evaluating state-court rulings.’ ”  &lt;em&gt;Ibid&lt;/em&gt;. (quoting &lt;em&gt;Lindh&lt;/em&gt; v. &lt;em&gt;Murphy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/521/320"&gt;521 U. S. 320&lt;/a&gt;, 333, n. 7 (1997)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 style="text-align: justify; text-align: center;"&gt;a&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority also went astray in holding that every fairminded jurist would find that the undisclosed forensic report about Martin’s laptop was material.  On the contrary, the record contains “strong support” for the state court’s conclusion that Martin “would have been convicted” even if the forensic report “severely impeached” Carter.  &lt;em&gt;Strickler&lt;/em&gt;, 527 U. S., at 294.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; DNA evidence tied Martin tightly to the modified Gatorade bottled that resembled a homemade silencer and that had apparently been used in the shooting.  Evidence also suggested that Martin was present when the bottle was modified.  Michael Bradley testified that shortly before the shooting Martin was in the room to which Frank Bradley brought both a Gatorade bottle and tape that matched the white medical tape on the mouth of the bottle found at the crime scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Martin had a strong motive for aiding the attempted murder of Torok: She had refused to get an abortion, had expressed her intent to take him to court to obtain child support, and had threatened to tell his wife about the baby.  On the day of the shooting, Martin had texted Torok in  what a reasonable jury could think was an effort to find a time when she would be home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Martin owned the kind of gun that seemed to have been used to shoot Torok, and multiple witnesses testified that they had seen him with such a weapon.  Michael Bradley also testified that Martin left McFadden’s house not long before the hit and that, upon returning, Martin told Frank Bradley to get rid of a brown paper bag that Martin had been holding.  Because the police never found Martin’s handgun or the weapon used in the shooting, a reasonable jury might well have concluded that Martin allowed his gun to be used and then ensured its disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; In light of all this evidence, a fairminded jurist could easily conclude that the disclosure of the forensic report on the computer would not have “undercut” the relevance or force of these “item[s] of the State’s case,” &lt;em&gt;Kyles&lt;/em&gt;, 514 U. S., at 451, or “ ‘put the whole case in such a different light as to undermine confidence in the verdict,’ ” &lt;em&gt;Strickler&lt;/em&gt;, 527 U. S., at 290.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;b&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority’s reasons for concluding otherwise were not consistent with the deference that AEDPA requires.  First, the majority argued that the disclosure of the report would have bolstered the defense’s primary theory of the case: that the bottle was a device used to smoke marijuana, not a silencer.  But a fairminded jurist could find that theory farfetched.  Among other things, the mouth of the bottle was covered in tape that looked like it had nestled the muzzle of a semiautomatic firearm.  The bottle did not smell like burnt marijuana and bore no trace of controlled substances.  The outward-punched puncture at the bottom of the bottle also looked like a bullet hole, and the defense never explained why anyone wanting to construct a bong would have poked a hole in the bottom of the bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority ventured that Carter’s testimony was the “only evidence connecting Martin to his potential  construction of the Gatorade bottle for use as a silencer.”  App. 21a.  A fairminded jurist could easily disagree based on both the bottle itself and Michael Bradley’s eyewitness testimony about what had occurred upstairs in the McFadden house shortly before the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; The panel majority discounted the strength of the evidence against Martin because it thought that strong evidence linked McFadden to the commission of the crime.  Yet that theory was inconsistent with the undisputed testimony that Torok ended her phone call with Wolfe to speak with a man who was at the door.  Nor did any evidence tie McFadden to the Gatorade bottle or the disposal of the firearm.  And even if McFadden were somehow involved in the crime, Martin could have been an accessory anyway.  After all, a fairminded jurist could decide that no evidence suggests that McFadden knew about Torok, or had any reason to want her killed, except through and because of Martin.  See &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;., at 439a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Last, the panel majority voiced serious doubt about Michael Bradley’s credibility, and the defense certainly had material to use in its effort to convince the jury that he should not be believed.  But his testimony about Martin’s role in the creation of the makeshift silencer was supported by the DNA evidence, and the jury was able to assess his credibility firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; Based on all the evidence, a fairminded jurist could easily conclude that disclosure of the forensic report on the laptop would not have made a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt;*  *  *&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt; We grant the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari, reverse the judgment of the Fourth Circuit, and remand the case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;It is so ordered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;"&gt;  &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps;"&gt;Justice Jackson&lt;/span&gt; would deny the petition for a writ of certiorari. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center; text-align: center;"&gt; APPENDIX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center; text-align: justify;"&gt;App. 442a &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center; text-align: justify;"&gt; App. 445a  App. 444a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#PERCURIAM_2-2ref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; *Nor could she rule out Torok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- 'notes' content area --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/main&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
