<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court of the United States - Recent Decisions — Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text</link>
    <description>Model-written summaries corresponding to the main feed items.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 21:52:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</guid>
      <title>ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Holsey Ellingburg, Jr., who was sentenced under the Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996 (MVRA) and ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution. Ellingburg committed his crime before the MVRA’s enactment. He challenged his restitution obligation, arguing it violated the Ex Post Facto Clause. The Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment and therefore not subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause. The Court granted certiorari to answer the question of whether restitution under the MVRA constitutes criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court applied principles of statutory construction, examining the text and structure of the MVRA. The Act labels restitution as a “penalty” for a criminal “offense,” restricts it to convicted criminal defendants, imposes it at sentencing alongside other criminal punishments, and is codified within Title 18 of the U.S. Code, which governs “Crimes and Criminal Procedure.” The Court also noted that victims do not initiate or settle the restitution process as they would in a civil proceeding. The Court’s prior precedents have also understood MVRA restitution to be criminal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion. The Court of Appeals may consider the Government’s arguments for affirmance of the District Court’s judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</guid>
      <title>HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari and a motion for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; to the Supreme Court of Indiana. The Court considered whether to dismiss the petition and whether to impose restrictions on the petitioner's ability to file future petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;. The question before the Court was whether to grant the petitioner's motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court dismissed the petition for a writ of certiorari and denied the motion for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;. The Clerk is directed not to accept further petitions in noncriminal matters from the petitioner unless the docketing fee is paid and the petition complies with specific rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court has previously imposed filing bars on litigants who have repeatedly abused the Court's process by submitting frivolous petitions. The Court reasoned that such bars are necessary to curb serious abuses of its docket and ensure resources are allocated effectively. The petitioner, Danny Howell, had previously submitted petitions deemed "frivolous," and the Court applied a precedent established in &lt;em&gt;Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;, which allows for prospective filing bars. Justice Jackson, dissenting, argued that a categorical, forward-looking filing bar, particularly for indigent incarcerated individuals, is a questionable restriction and that the Court should err on the side of keeping courthouse doors open to ensure equal justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition was dismissed, and the motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; was denied. The Clerk is directed to refuse future &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; petitions from the petitioner unless the required fee is paid and the petition complies with rules.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</guid>
      <title>BERK v. CHOY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Harold Berk’s lawsuit against Dr. Wilson Choy and Beebe Medical Center for medical malpractice under Delaware law. Berk sued in federal court but failed to provide an affidavit of merit, as required by Delaware Code Title 18, §6853. The District Court dismissed the lawsuit, and the Third Circuit affirmed. The question before the Supreme Court was whether Delaware’s affidavit law applies in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a plaintiff brings a state-law claim in federal court, the court must determine whether to apply state or federal law. The Rules of Decision Act directs federal courts to apply state substantive law unless otherwise required by the Constitution, a treaty, or a statute. The Rules Enabling Act authorizes the Supreme Court to adopt uniform rules of procedure, which displace contrary state law when a valid Federal Rule of Civil Procedure is on point. Here, Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 8 governs, as it prescribes the information a plaintiff must present in a complaint. Rule 8 requires only a "short and plain statement of the claim," implicitly rejecting the need for additional evidence like an affidavit. The Court rejected the defendants' argument that Delaware's law could be reinterpreted to avoid conflict with the Federal Rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Court of Appeals was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</guid>
      <title>CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a dispute arising from a bankruptcy proceeding. Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, initiated adversarial proceedings against Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc., to collect unpaid invoices. Vista-Pro attempted service by mail, which Coney Island contends was improper. Coney Island failed to answer, resulting in a default judgment. After six years and attempts to enforce the judgment, Coney Island filed a motion to vacate, arguing the judgment was void due to improper service. The Bankruptcy Court and Sixth Circuit affirmed the denial of relief, finding Coney Island failed to file the motion within a "reasonable time" as required by Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1). The question before the Court was whether this "reasonable time" requirement applies to motions alleging a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that the plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) explicitly states that motions under Rule 60(b) must be made within a reasonable time.  Since a motion to vacate a void judgment falls under Rule 60(b), the time limit applies. The Court rejected the argument that void judgments are inherently unenforceable and thus exempt from time limits, noting that other legal errors also have time limits for seeking relief. The Court also dismissed Coney Island’s arguments regarding historical practice, policy concerns, and constitutional avoidance, finding them unpersuasive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court affirmed the judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit. Coney Island’s motion to vacate the judgment was denied, and the bankruptcy trustee can proceed with enforcing the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</guid>
      <title>KLEIN v. MARTIN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of the United States concerning Charles Brandon Martin’s federal habeas petition. Martin was convicted in a Maryland court for the attempted murder of his girlfriend, Jodi Torok. He sought federal habeas relief, arguing that the State failed to disclose favorable impeachment evidence (a forensic report regarding a laptop) in violation of &lt;em&gt;Brady v. Maryland&lt;/em&gt;. The Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals reversed the district court’s denial of the petition and awarded Martin a new trial, reasoning that the state court’s decision was not consistent with AEDPA. The central question before the Supreme Court was whether the Fourth Circuit correctly interpreted and applied the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (AEDPA) in reviewing the state court’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment. The Court held that the Fourth Circuit departed from the role AEDPA assigns to federal courts in reviewing state court decisions on habeas petitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court emphasized the strict standards governing federal habeas relief under AEDPA, requiring deference to state court decisions. It explained that federal courts must only grant relief when a state court’s decision is “contrary to” or “involved an unreasonable application of” “clearly established Federal law.” The Court found that the Fourth Circuit erred in concluding the state appellate court applied the wrong legal rule and in holding that every fairminded jurist would find the undisclosed forensic report material. The Court reasoned that the state court correctly applied &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; precedent, stating that the evidence linking Martin to the crime was strong enough that the disclosure of the report would not have changed the outcome of the trial. The Court also criticized the Fourth Circuit for imposing opinion-writing standards on the state court and for failing to give the state court’s decision the “benefit of the doubt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment and remanded the case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion. This means the lower court’s decision is overturned, and the case will be sent back to the Fourth Circuit to be reconsidered in light of the Supreme Court’s ruling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</guid>
      <title>BOYD v. HAMM</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is an application for a stay of execution and a petition for a writ of certiorari. Anthony Boyd challenged Alabama’s use of nitrogen hypoxia as a method of execution, arguing it violated the Eighth Amendment. He sought to be executed by firing squad instead. The District Court denied his request, and the Eleventh Circuit denied a stay, finding the District Court did not abuse its discretion. The Court considered whether Alabama’s nitrogen hypoxia method of execution violated the Eighth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay of execution is denied, and the petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority declined to grant a stay or certiorari. Justice Sotomayor, joined by Justices Kagan and Jackson, dissented, arguing that Boyd demonstrated he was likely to succeed on his Eighth Amendment claim. The dissent highlighted evidence showing nitrogen hypoxia inflicts prolonged psychological terror and conscious suffocation, significantly exceeding the pain inherent in other execution methods. The dissent criticized the lower courts for failing to recognize the substantial differences between nitrogen hypoxia and a firing squad, particularly regarding the duration of conscious suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari and the application for a stay were denied. Boyd was executed using nitrogen hypoxia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ORR</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns an Executive Branch policy requiring all new passports to display an individual’s biological sex at birth. A United States District Court preliminarily enjoined the Government from enforcing this policy, and the First Circuit declined to stay the injunction pending appeal. The Government subsequently filed a stay application with the Supreme Court. The Court considered whether to grant the application, addressing the question of whether a stay should be issued pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the Government’s application for a stay. The June 17, 2025 order of the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts is stayed pending the disposition of the appeal in the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit and disposition of a petition for a writ of certiorari, if such a writ is timely sought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that the Government is likely to succeed on the merits, citing the Government’s ability to attest to historical facts without subjecting anyone to differential treatment and the lack of evidence that the policy was motivated by a desire to harm a politically unpopular group. Additionally, the Court noted that the District Court’s class-wide relief enjoins enforcement of an Executive Branch policy with foreign affairs implications, and that the Government would suffer irreparable injury absent a stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay was granted. The District Court’s order is stayed pending the First Circuit’s disposition of the appeal and any subsequent petition for a writ of certiorari. The stay will terminate automatically if certiorari is denied and upon the sending down of the judgment of the Supreme Court if certiorari is granted. Justices Jackson, Sotomayor, and Kagan dissented from the grant of the application for a stay.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</guid>
      <title>VENENO v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. Petitioner, Veneno, seeks review to reconsider &lt;em&gt;United States v. Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, which established the theory of “plenary power” over Native American tribal affairs. The question presented is whether the Court should reconsider &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority declined to grant certiorari. Justice Gorsuch, joined by Justice Thomas, dissented from the denial, arguing that &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; lacks constitutional foundation and should be overturned. He contends that Native American Tribes are sovereign entities with inherent powers, and the Major Crimes Act, upheld in &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, represents an overreach of federal authority. The dissent criticizes the Court’s reliance on outdated doctrines like the European doctrine of discovery and the notion of Tribes as “wards” of the nation, arguing these concepts are inconsistent with the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The Court declined to reconsider &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, leaving the existing precedent in place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</guid>
      <title>HUTSON v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari denied by the Supreme Court. The central question presented, as viewed by the dissenting justices, is whether a District Court order mandating the construction of a prison facility violates the Prison Litigation Reform Act of 1995 (PLRA), and whether lower courts erred in failing to terminate an injunction that potentially violated the PLRA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari. Justice Gorsuch would have granted the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting justices argue that the District Court’s order to construct a new facility for inmates with mental-health needs violated the PLRA, which explicitly prohibits courts from ordering prison construction as a remedial measure. They further contend that the lower courts erred in not terminating the injunction after four years, as required by the PLRA, and in improperly shifting the burden of proof to the party seeking termination. The Fifth Circuit’s resolution of this issue created a circuit split, warranting Supreme Court review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The decision of the Fifth Circuit stands, leaving New Orleans to continue paying for the allegedly erroneous legal rulings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</guid>
      <title>PITTS v. MISSISSIPPI</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Jeffrey Clyde Pitts, was convicted of sexual abuse following a report made by his daughter, A.G.C., after a weekend visit. At trial, the State sought to place a screen between Pitts and his daughter during her testimony, citing a Mississippi statute granting child witnesses the right to a screen. Pitts objected, arguing the State had not met the Sixth Amendment's burden of demonstrating necessity for such screening. The Mississippi Supreme Court upheld the trial court's decision, distinguishing prior Supreme Court cases (&lt;em&gt;Coy v. Iowa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Maryland v. Craig&lt;/em&gt;) and relying on the state statute. The central question before the Supreme Court was whether the Mississippi Supreme Court correctly applied the Sixth Amendment's Confrontation Clause in allowing the screening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court reversed the Mississippi Supreme Court's judgment, holding that the trial court erred in authorizing the screening without making a case-specific finding of necessity based on evidence, as required by the Sixth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reiterated that the Sixth Amendment guarantees a defendant the right to a face-to-face meeting with witnesses, and that this right is only an exception in child-abuse cases when a court determines screening is necessary to protect the child from trauma. The Court found that the Mississippi Supreme Court’s attempts to distinguish &lt;em&gt;Coy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Craig&lt;/em&gt; were unpersuasive, and that the trial court’s reliance on a mandatory state statute, rather than a case-specific finding of necessity based on evidence, violated the Sixth Amendment. The Court rejected the State’s argument that the trial court had made such a finding, noting the trial court’s express concerns about following the statute and the prosecution’s reliance on the statute itself rather than presenting evidence of necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Mississippi Supreme Court was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. The State may argue, and the Mississippi Supreme Court may consider, whether the error warrants a new trial under the harmless-error standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</guid>
      <title>BECK v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was filed following a denial of relief to Kari Beck, personal representative of the Estate of Cameron Gayle Beck, against the United States. The Eighth Circuit affirmed a lower court's dismissal of Beck’s wrongful death suit, relying on the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine, which provides an exception to the Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA). The central question presented was whether the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine should be applied to a case where the servicemember was killed in a car accident while off-duty and away from military activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari, declining to review the Eighth Circuit’s decision. Justice Gorsuch would have granted the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Sotomayor, writing separately, acknowledged the criticisms of the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine and its expansive interpretation of the FTCA. However, she argued that &lt;em&gt;stare decisis&lt;/em&gt;—respect for precedent—and Congress’s repeated consideration of legislation to overrule or limit &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; without action, warranted denying the petition. She emphasized that Congress holds primary authority over statutory interpretation and that courts should defer to Congress’s decision not to intervene. Justice Thomas, dissenting from the denial, argued that the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine should be overruled and that, even without overruling it, the doctrine should not have been applied in this case because the servicemember’s death did not arise out of activities incident to military service. He highlighted the circuit split and confusion surrounding the application of &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The Eighth Circuit’s decision affirming the dismissal of Beck’s wrongful death suit stands. Mrs. Beck will not recover in tort for her husband’s wrongful death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</guid>
      <title>CLARK v. SWEENEY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
Jeremiah Sweeney was convicted of second-degree murder and other crimes in Maryland state court, and his appeals were unsuccessful. He subsequently sought habeas relief in Federal District Court, which was denied. The Fourth Circuit reversed the District Court's decision and ordered a new trial, relying on a claim Sweeney did not raise. The Supreme Court granted certiorari to address whether the Fourth Circuit properly departed from the principle of party presentation. The question before the Court was whether the Fourth Circuit erred in granting Sweeney relief on a claim he never asserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Fourth Circuit’s decision to grant Sweeney a new trial was reversed because the court departed from the principle of party presentation by ruling on a claim Sweeney never asserted. The Court held that courts should follow the principle of party presentation, where the parties frame the issues for decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Supreme Court emphasized the principle of party presentation in the adversarial legal system, where courts act as neutral arbiters of issues raised by the parties. The Fourth Circuit violated this principle by creating a new claim—based on “extraordinary failures from juror to judge to attorney”—rather than addressing the ineffective-assistance claim Sweeney actually presented. The Court found this action constituted an abuse of discretion, citing &lt;em&gt;United States v. Sineneng-Smith&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Fourth Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. On remand, the Fourth Circuit must analyze the ineffective-assistance claim Sweeney asserted, applying a “doubly deferential” standard under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</guid>
      <title>ABBOTT v. LEAGUE OF UNITED LATIN AMERICAN CITIZENS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a challenge to a new congressional map drawn by Texas. A three-judge District Court found the map was drawn with a predominantly racial motive and enjoined its use in the 2026 elections. The State of Texas and its officials sought a stay of the District Court’s order pending appeal, initiating this application for stay before the Supreme Court. The Court was asked to determine whether Texas satisfied the criteria for interim relief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted Texas’s application for a stay of the District Court’s order. The order enjoining the use of the new map in the 2026 elections is stayed pending the filing of an appeal in the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that Texas met the traditional criteria for interim relief. Specifically, the Court found the District Court made at least two serious errors: failing to honor the presumption of legislative good faith by construing ambiguous evidence against the challengers, and failing to draw an adverse inference against the challengers for not producing a viable alternative map that met the State’s partisan goals. The Court also emphasized that lower federal courts should ordinarily not alter election rules on the eve of an election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for stay was granted. The November 18, 2025 order entered by the United States District Court for the Western District of Texas is stayed pending the timely filing of an appeal. The stay will remain in effect pending the Court’s action on the appeal, or until the judgment is affirmed or dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</guid>
      <title>JOHN DOE v. DYNAMIC PHYSICAL  THERAPY, LLC, et al.</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari before the Supreme Court of the United States. The Louisiana Court of Appeal held that a state statute immunizing healthcare providers from civil liability during a public health emergency barred the plaintiff’s federal claims. The central question before the Supreme Court was whether a state law can confer immunity from federal causes of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holding:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court held that a state does not have the power to confer immunity from federal causes of action. Defining the scope of liability under state law remains the State’s prerogative, but this does not extend to shielding parties from federal claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that defining liability under state law is within a state’s authority. However, a state’s power does not extend to preventing federal causes of action. The Supremacy Clause of the United States Constitution dictates that federal law prevails over conflicting state laws. The Court cited precedent supporting this principle, emphasizing that state courts are bound to follow federal law regardless of any contrary state statutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Louisiana Court of Appeal was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings not inconsistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion. The lower court must now reconsider the plaintiff’s federal claims without applying the state immunity statute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</guid>
      <title>DAVENPORT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner sought a writ of certiorari following a denial by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. The procedural posture was a petition for review of a lower court decision. The central question addressed was whether the District Court erred in refusing to provide a jury instruction defining "reasonable doubt" for the underlying state-law murder charge in a federal murder in aid of racketeering case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari. Justice Sotomayor, writing separately, stated that the District Court was mistaken in its understanding that federal courts are prohibited from defining reasonable doubt for a jury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
Justice Sotomayor reasoned that &lt;em&gt;Victor v. Nebraska&lt;/em&gt; established that the Constitution does not prohibit trial courts from defining reasonable doubt, and that most Courts of Appeals recognize this discretion. While acknowledging that defining reasonable doubt may not always be advisable, and that the District Court had concerns about potential jury confusion, Justice Sotomayor emphasized that district courts should weigh the circumstances of each case to determine whether providing a definition is appropriate, particularly when there is potential for juror confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The Court did not revisit the Fourth Circuit’s decision, but Justice Sotomayor’s concurring opinion clarifies the proper role of district courts in defining reasonable doubt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ILLINOIS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves an application for a stay pending review of a District Court order. The core question presented, as initially framed by the parties, concerned whether the District Court correctly interpreted the phrase "regular forces" in 10 U.S.C. §12406(3), which allows the President to call the National Guard into federal service when unable to execute the laws with "regular forces." The District Court held that civilian federal law enforcement officers were the "regular forces."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court departed from standard practice by raising and ruling on an argument waived below by the respondents, finding that "regular forces" means the military. The Court also expressed tentative views on other issues, including the scope of "execute the laws" under §12406(3) and whether the President's inherent constitutional authority is sufficient to justify using the National Guard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting Justice Alito argues the Court improperly considered an argument the respondents had waived below. He contends the Court should have decided the case based on the issues the parties presented, assuming the parties' interpretation of "regular forces" was correct. He further criticizes the Court's tentative views on other issues, arguing they lack sufficient briefing and consideration. Alito argues the President's determination that he was unable to execute federal law with civilian law enforcement should be given deference, and that the Court's interpretation of "unable" and "execute the laws" is implausible and inconsistent with established precedent and ordinary usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court did not explicitly state an outcome regarding the stay application itself. However, the dissenting Justice expresses disagreement with the manner in which the Court disposed of the application. The dissent suggests the Court should have granted the stay based on the original arguments presented.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</guid>
      <title>BOWE v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Michael S. Bowe, who is serving a 24-year federal sentence for conspiracy to commit robbery, attempted robbery, and using a firearm in relation to a crime of violence. Bowe is seeking postconviction relief from a mandatory consecutive 10-year sentence imposed under 18 U.S.C. §924(c). The question before the Court is whether §2244(b)(3)(E) bars this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion, and whether §2244(b)(1) applies to second or successive motions filed by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Court has jurisdiction because §2244(b)(3)(E) does not bar this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;§2244(b)(1) does not apply to second or successive motions filed under §2255(h) by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that §2244(b)(3)(E), which restricts certiorari review of authorization denials, is intended for state prisoners and their §2254 applications, not federal prisoners and their §2255 motions. The cross-reference in §2255(h) to §2244 does not provide the "clear indication" of congressional intent needed to strip this Court of jurisdiction. Similarly, §2244(b)(1)’s old-claim bar, which applies to state prisoners’ habeas applications, is not applicable to federal prisoners’ motions under §2255 because the statute explicitly distinguishes between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case was vacated and remanded to the Eleventh Circuit to determine whether Bowe should receive authorization to file a second or successive motion under the correct standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</guid>
      <title>CASE v. MONTANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a challenge to a warrantless entry into a home by Montana police officers responding to a 911 call reporting that William Case was threatening suicide and may have shot himself. The procedural posture is an appeal to the Supreme Court on a writ of certiorari to the Montana Supreme Court, which upheld the officers’ entry as lawful under Montana’s caretaker doctrine. The central question before the Court was whether the Fourth Amendment allows police officers to enter a home without a warrant if they have an “objectively reasonable basis for believing” that someone inside needs emergency assistance, or whether they must have “probable cause.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court held that the “objectively reasonable basis” standard for warrantless home entries to render emergency aid, established in &lt;em&gt;Brigham City v. Stuart&lt;/em&gt;, applies without further gloss and was satisfied in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that the Fourth Amendment presumptively requires warrants for searches and seizures within a home, but this requirement is subject to exceptions, including the need to render emergency assistance. &lt;em&gt;Brigham City&lt;/em&gt; established the “objectively reasonable basis” standard, which the Montana Supreme Court deviated from by applying a standard akin to “reasonable suspicion.” The Court rejected Case’s argument that the standard should be interpreted as requiring “probable cause,” noting that probable cause is “peculiarly related to criminal investigations” and would not fit the non-criminal, non-investigatory context of emergency aid. The officers had an objectively reasonable basis to believe Case needed emergency aid based on the 911 call and their observations at the scene, including an empty holster and a possible suicide note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court affirmed the judgment of the Montana Supreme Court. The case is remanded to the lower courts for further proceedings consistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</guid>
      <title>BOST v. ILLINOIS STATE BD. OF ELECTIONS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a challenge to Illinois law, which requires election officials to count mail-in ballots postmarked or certified no later than election day and received within two weeks of election day. Congressman Michael Bost and two other political candidates sued, alleging that this practice violates federal law (2 U.S.C. §7 and 3 U.S.C. §1), which sets election day as the Tuesday following the first Monday in November. The district court dismissed the case, and the Seventh Circuit affirmed, finding the plaintiffs lacked standing. The Supreme Court granted certiorari to answer the question of whether Congressman Bost, as a candidate, has standing to challenge the rules governing the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a candidate for office, Congressman Bost has standing to challenge the rules that govern the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that candidates have a “personal stake” in the rules governing their elections, extending beyond simply winning. They have an interest in a fair process, as candidates seek to represent the people and suffer when the process deviates from the law. Unlawful vote counting or discarding of lawful votes undermines the integrity of the electoral process and erodes public confidence in election results, causing reputational harm to candidates. The Court rejected the Seventh Circuit’s requirement that candidates demonstrate a substantial risk of losing the election or failing to achieve a specific vote threshold to establish standing, arguing that such a requirement would delay challenges and potentially undermine the democratic process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</guid>
      <title>BARRETT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns the interplay between two provisions of 18 U.S.C. §924: subsection (c)(1)(A)(i), which criminalizes using a firearm in connection with a federal crime, and subsection (j), which prescribes enhanced penalties when a violation of subsection (c) causes death. The procedural posture is an appeal from the Second Circuit following a grant of certiorari by this Court. The question presented is whether a single act violating both provisions can result in two convictions, or only one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress did not clearly authorize convictions under both §§924(c)(1)(A)(i) and (j) for a single act violating both provisions. Therefore, one such act may spawn only one conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court applied the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; test, which presumes Congress does not intend to punish the same offense twice. While the offenses are considered the same under &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt;, the Court found no “plainly expressed” congressional intent to overcome this presumption. Congress used specific language in subsection (c) to authorize dual convictions for the predicate crime, but not for subsection (j). The Court rejected arguments that the differing focuses of the two subsections justified multiple convictions, noting that Congress did not explicitly authorize such a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part of the Second Circuit’s judgment holding otherwise is reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>