<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court of the United States - Recent Decisions — Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text</link>
    <description>Model-written summaries corresponding to the main feed items.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 21:36:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</guid>
      <title>BOYD v. HAMM</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Anthony Boyd, sought a stay of execution and a writ of certiorari from the Supreme Court. He challenged Alabama's use of nitrogen hypoxia as a method of execution, arguing it violated the Eighth Amendment. The procedural posture was an application for a stay and a petition for a writ of certiorari following a denial of a stay by the Eleventh Circuit Court of Appeals. The legal question presented was whether Alabama’s use of nitrogen hypoxia as an execution method constitutes cruel and unusual punishment under the Eighth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied Boyd’s application for a stay of execution and denied his petition for a writ of certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority provided no reasoning for its decision. Justice Sotomayor, joined by Justices Kagan and Jackson, dissented from the denial of both the application for a stay and the petition for certiorari. The dissent argued that nitrogen hypoxia inflicts unnecessary psychological torment, as condemned individuals remain conscious for two to four minutes while suffocating. The dissent highlighted evidence from previous executions using nitrogen hypoxia, demonstrating violent movements, gasping, and convulsions. The dissent asserted that Boyd had demonstrated a feasible alternative (firing squad) that would significantly reduce the risk of severe pain and that the State had refused to adopt it without a legitimate penological reason, as required by &lt;em&gt;Bucklew v. Precythe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari and the application for a stay. Boyd’s execution by nitrogen hypoxia proceeded as scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ORR</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns an Executive Branch policy requiring all new passports to display an individual’s biological sex at birth. A United States District Court preliminarily enjoined the Government from enforcing this policy, and the First Circuit declined to stay the injunction pending appeal. The Government subsequently filed a stay application with the Supreme Court. The legal question presented was whether to grant the Government’s application for a stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the Government’s application for a stay. The June 17, 2025 order of the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts is stayed pending the disposition of the appeal in the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit and disposition of a petition for a writ of certiorari, if such a writ is timely sought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that the Government is likely to succeed on the merits, citing the Government’s ability to attest to historical facts without subjecting anyone to differential treatment and the lack of evidence that the policy was motivated by animus. They also noted the District Court’s grant of class-wide relief concerning a Government document with foreign affairs implications, concluding that the Government would suffer irreparable injury absent a stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Jackson, joined by Justices Sotomayor and Kagan, dissented, arguing that the Court misunderstood its role in deciding stay applications and failed to adequately consider the balance of equities, particularly the potential harm to the plaintiffs. The dissent emphasized the lack of evidence demonstrating harm to the Government and the concrete injuries the plaintiffs would face if the policy went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the District Court was stayed pending the appeal in the First Circuit and potential review via a writ of certiorari. The stay will terminate automatically if certiorari is denied and upon the sending down of the judgment of the Supreme Court if certiorari is granted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</guid>
      <title>VENENO v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was filed to ask the Court to reconsider &lt;em&gt;United States v. Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, a case that helped establish the theory of “plenary power” over Native American Tribes. The legal question presented is whether the federal government has plenary power over the internal affairs of Native American Tribes, a concept the petitioner argues lacks constitutional foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority declined to reconsider &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;. Justice Gorsuch, joined by Justice Thomas, dissented from the denial, arguing that &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; is based on archaic prejudices and lacks constitutional support. He contends that Native American Tribes are sovereign entities with inherent powers, and the Major Crimes Act, upheld in &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, represents an overreach of federal authority. The dissent highlights the incoherence of plenary power doctrine with the Constitution’s enumerated powers and calls for the Court to overturn &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The judgment in the lower court stands, and the legal question regarding the scope of federal power over Native American Tribes remains unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</guid>
      <title>HUTSON v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari concerning a District Court order requiring New Orleans to construct a new facility for inmates with mental-health needs. The procedural posture is a petition for certiorari after a ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit. The legal question presented is whether the District Court’s order to construct a prison violated the Prison Litigation Reform Act of 1995 (PLRA), which prohibits courts from ordering prison construction as a remedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority declined to review the Fifth Circuit’s decision. Justice Alito, joined by Justice Thomas, dissented from the denial of certiorari, arguing that the District Court’s order violated the PLRA, which explicitly prohibits courts from ordering prison construction. He further contended that the lower courts erred in failing to terminate the injunction after two years, as required by the PLRA, and in improperly shifting the burden of proof to the party seeking termination. The dissent highlighted a circuit split regarding which party bears the burden of demonstrating the continued necessity of the injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The Fifth Circuit’s decision stands, and New Orleans will continue to be obligated to pay for the construction of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</guid>
      <title>PITTS v. MISSISSIPPI</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a defendant, Jeffrey Clyde Pitts, convicted of sexual abuse. Pitts objected to a trial court order that placed a screen between him and the child witness, A. G. C., during her testimony. He argued that the trial court failed to make the case-specific finding of necessity required by the Sixth Amendment, as established in &lt;em&gt;Coy v. Iowa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Maryland v. Craig&lt;/em&gt;. The Mississippi Supreme Court rejected Pitts’s arguments, relying on a state statute that mandates screening in child abuse cases and distinguishing &lt;em&gt;Coy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Craig&lt;/em&gt;. Pitts then petitioned for a writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of the United States. The legal question presented was whether the Mississippi Supreme Court correctly interpreted and applied the Sixth Amendment’s Confrontation Clause in light of &lt;em&gt;Coy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Craig&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court reversed the Mississippi Supreme Court’s judgment, holding that a trial court cannot deny a defendant’s Sixth Amendment right to confront their accuser face-to-face simply because a state statute permits screening, nor can it authorize screening based on generalized findings of necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reiterated that the Sixth Amendment guarantees a defendant a face-to-face meeting with witnesses, but this right can be limited in child abuse cases only if a court “hears evidence” and makes a “case-specific” finding of “necessity.” The Mississippi Supreme Court attempted to distinguish &lt;em&gt;Coy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Craig&lt;/em&gt; by referencing a state constitutional provision regarding victims’ rights, the mandatory nature of Mississippi’s statute compared to Iowa’s discretionary statute, the child witness’s age, the lack of dispute over the perpetrator’s identity, and the method of separation between the witness and defendant. The Court found none of these distinctions persuasive, emphasizing that state law must yield to the Federal Constitution and that a mandatory statute, like Mississippi’s, is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; constitutionally problematic than a discretionary one. The Court also rejected the State’s argument that the trial court had made a case-specific finding of necessity, noting the trial court’s reliance on the statute and expressed concerns about disregarding it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted certiorari, reversed the judgment of the Mississippi Supreme Court, and remanded the case for further proceedings. On remand, the State may argue, and the Mississippi Supreme Court may consider, whether the constitutional error warrants a new trial under the harmless-error standard established in &lt;em&gt;Chapman v. California&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</guid>
      <title>BECK v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari following a denial of relief to Kari Beck, the personal representative of the Estate of Cameron Gayle Beck, who sued the United States after her husband, an Air Force Staff Sergeant, was killed in a car accident. The legal question presented, though not explicitly stated, concerns the application of the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine and whether it barred Beck’s claim under the Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari. Justice Gorsuch would have granted the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority, through Justice Sotomayor, declined to overrule &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; v. United States, citing principles of &lt;em&gt;stare decisis&lt;/em&gt; and the importance of congressional authority over statutory interpretation. The Court noted that Congress has repeatedly considered legislation to limit or overrule &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; but has not done so, and that overturning the precedent would require "special justification." Justice Thomas, in dissent, argued that &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; lacks textual basis in the FTCA and that the doctrine’s policy rationales are unpersuasive. He further pointed out a circuit split regarding the application of &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; and the need for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The lower court’s judgment stands, meaning Kari Beck will not recover for her husband’s wrongful death. Congress remains free to alter the FTCA and address the concerns raised regarding the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</guid>
      <title>CLARK v. SWEENEY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
Jeremiah Sweeney was convicted of second-degree murder and other crimes in Maryland state court, and his appeals were unsuccessful. He subsequently sought habeas relief in Federal District Court, which was denied. The Fourth Circuit reversed the District Court's decision and ordered a new trial, relying on a claim Sweeney did not raise in his petition. The legal question presented was whether the Fourth Circuit’s departure from the principle of party presentation warrants reversal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment, holding that the appellate court erred in granting relief based on a claim not asserted by Sweeney and not addressed by the State. The Court held that the Fourth Circuit’s actions constituted an abuse of discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court emphasized the principle of party presentation in the adversarial legal system, stating that courts should act as neutral arbiters of issues raised by the parties, not create new claims. The Fourth Circuit deviated from this principle by formulating a new claim based on “extraordinary failures” without allowing the State to respond. Justice Quattlebaum, in dissent, had previously criticized the majority for disregarding party presentation principles. The Court referenced &lt;em&gt;United States v. Sineneng-Smith&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lomax v. Ortiz-Marquez&lt;/em&gt; to reinforce this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Fourth Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. On remand, the Fourth Circuit is directed to analyze the ineffective-assistance claim Sweeney originally asserted, applying a “doubly deferential” standard under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996, considering whether every reasonable lawyer would have made a different decision than the state court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</guid>
      <title>ABBOTT v. LEAGUE OF UNITED LATIN AMERICAN CITIZENS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a challenge to a new congressional map adopted by Texas, alleging that the legislature’s motive was predominantly racial. A three-judge District Court agreed and enjoined the use of the new map in the 2026 elections. Texas and several state officials subsequently applied to the Supreme Court for a stay of that order, pending appeal. The legal question presented was whether the District Court’s order should be stayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted Texas’s application for a stay, effectively allowing Texas to use the new congressional map in the 2026 elections pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court found that Texas satisfied the traditional criteria for interim relief, including a likelihood of success on the merits. The Court reasoned that the District Court erred by failing to honor the presumption of legislative good faith and by failing to draw an adverse inference against the challengers for not producing a viable alternative map. The Court also emphasized that lower federal courts should ordinarily not alter election rules on the eve of an election. A concurring opinion highlighted the partisan nature of the map's adoption and the lack of dispute regarding this fact. A dissenting opinion argued that the District Court’s factual findings were plausible and deserved deference, and that the Court’s decision disrespects the work of the District Court and disserves affected Texans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The District Court’s November 18, 2025 order was stayed pending the filing of an appeal. The stay will remain in effect pending the Court’s action on the appeal, or until the judgment is affirmed or dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</guid>
      <title>JOHN DOE v. DYNAMIC PHYSICAL  THERAPY, LLC, et al.</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff, John Doe, sought to pursue federal claims against Dynamic Physical Therapy, LLC, and others. The Louisiana Court of Appeal held that a Louisiana state statute, which provides immunity to healthcare providers during public health emergencies, barred these federal claims. The legal question presented was whether a state law granting immunity to healthcare providers could preclude federal causes of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holding:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that a state cannot confer immunity from federal causes of action. The Louisiana Court of Appeal’s decision was therefore incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority opinion reasoned that defining the scope of liability under state law is a power reserved to the states. However, a state lacks the authority to grant immunity from federal causes of action. The Court cited established precedent supporting this principle, emphasizing that state courts are bound to follow federal law, regardless of any conflicting state statutes. The Court acknowledged that the plaintiff’s federal claims might fail on other federal grounds, but that determination should be made by the Louisiana courts initially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Louisiana Court of Appeal was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings not inconsistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</guid>
      <title>DAVENPORT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner sought a writ of certiorari following a denial of his appeal to the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. The legal question presented concerned whether the District Court erred in denying the petitioner’s request for a jury instruction defining "reasonable doubt" in relation to the underlying state-law murder charge in a federal murder in aid of racketeering case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court denied the petition for a writ of certiorari. Justice Sotomayor concurred in the denial, noting the petition was untimely and counsel provided no explanation for the delay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
Justice Sotomayor, writing separately, argued that the District Court was mistaken in stating that federal courts are prohibited from defining reasonable doubt for a jury. Citing &lt;em&gt;Victor v. Nebraska&lt;/em&gt;, the Court previously held that the Constitution does not prohibit trial courts from defining reasonable doubt. While acknowledging that defining reasonable doubt may not always be advisable, and that the District Court raised concerns about potential jury confusion, Justice Sotomayor maintained that district courts possess discretion to provide such definitions, particularly when circumstances warrant it, such as to clarify potential misunderstandings or in response to jury inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The judgment of the Fourth Circuit was not affirmed, reversed, vacated, or remanded, as the Court declined to review the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ILLINOIS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves an application for a stay pending review of a District Court order. The legal question presented concerns whether the President exceeded his authority under 10 U.S.C. §12406(3) by calling the National Guard into federal service to assist in executing federal law in Illinois. The parties disagreed on the meaning of "regular forces" within the statute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court departed from standard practice by raising and ruling on an argument waived below by the respondents, and expressed tentative views on other important, unresolved legal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority accepted an argument raised by the respondents for the first time, contrary to their position below, that "regular forces" means the military. Justice Alito, joined by Justice Thomas, dissented, arguing the Court should have decided the case based on the arguments presented by the parties and should have given deference to the President’s determination. The dissent also criticized the Court's consideration of other unresolved legal issues and its failure to adequately explain the President’s inherent constitutional authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
Not stated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</guid>
      <title>BOWE v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Petitioner Michael S. Bowe is serving a 24-year federal sentence after pleading guilty to conspiracy to commit Hobbs Act robbery, attempted Hobbs Act robbery, and using a firearm in relation to a crime of violence. He seeks postconviction relief from a mandatory consecutive 10-year sentence imposed under 18 U.S.C. §924(c), arguing that his other offenses do not qualify as “crimes of violence” under that statute. The legal question is whether §2244(b)(1)’s old-claim bar applies to second or successive motions filed by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that §2244(b)(3)(E) does not bar this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion, and that §2244(b)(1) does not apply to second or successive motions filed by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that §2244(b)(3)(E), which prohibits certiorari review of authorization decisions for second or successive applications, applies only to state prisoners and their §2254 applications, not federal prisoners and their §2255 motions. The cross-reference in §2255(h) to §2244 is narrow and specific, incorporating only procedures related to how a panel certifies a filing, not broader provisions like the certiorari bar. Similarly, §2244(b)(1)’s old-claim bar, which dismisses claims previously presented, is explicitly limited to state prisoners filing habeas corpus applications under §2254. Congress has consistently treated state and federal prisoners differently in AEDPA, and imposing the same procedural restrictions would not further AEDPA’s goals of finality and comity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Eleventh Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. The Eleventh Circuit is directed to determine in the first instance whether Bowe should receive authorization to file a second or successive motion under the correct standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</guid>
      <title>CASE v. MONTANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves a challenge to a warrantless entry into a home by Montana police officers responding to a 911 call reporting that William Case was threatening suicide and may have shot himself. The procedural posture is an appeal to the Supreme Court following a decision by the Montana Supreme Court upholding the officers’ entry as lawful under Montana’s caretaker doctrine. The legal question presented is whether the Fourth Amendment requires police officers to have probable cause to believe that an occupant needs emergency aid before entering a home without a warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court held that the objective reasonableness standard for warrantless home entries to render emergency aid, established in &lt;em&gt;Brigham City v. Stuart&lt;/em&gt;, applies without further gloss and was satisfied in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court reasoned that the Fourth Amendment presumptively requires a warrant for searches and seizures within a home, but this requirement is subject to exceptions, including the need to render emergency assistance. The Court reaffirmed the &lt;em&gt;Brigham City&lt;/em&gt; standard, which requires an “objectively reasonable basis for believing” that an occupant is seriously injured or imminently threatened with such injury. The Court rejected Case’s argument that this standard should be interpreted as requiring probable cause, finding that probable cause is rooted in criminal investigations and would not fit the non-criminal, non-investigatory context of emergency aid. The officers had an objectively reasonable basis to believe Case needed emergency aid based on the 911 caller’s report, the officers’ observations at the scene (empty holster, suicide note), and Case’s history of mental health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the Montana Supreme Court was affirmed. The case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</guid>
      <title>BOST v. ILLINOIS STATE BD. OF ELECTIONS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's the breakdown of the case, adhering to your instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congressman Michael Bost and two other political candidates filed a lawsuit against the Illinois State Board of Elections, claiming that Illinois law, which allows mail-in ballots postmarked or certified by election day to be received up to two weeks later, violates federal law. They principally contended that this practice conflicts with federal statutes setting election day. The district court dismissed the case, and the Seventh Circuit affirmed, finding the plaintiffs lacked standing. The legal question presented was whether a candidate for office has standing to challenge the rules governing the counting of votes in their election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holding:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that Congressman Bost, as a candidate for office, has standing to challenge the rules that govern the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that candidates have a “personal stake” in the rules governing elections, beyond simply winning or losing. They have an interest in a fair process, as candidates seek to represent the people, and an unfair process undermines their political legitimacy and erodes public confidence in election results. The Court rejected the argument that candidates must demonstrate a substantial risk of losing the election or suffering a significant vote share reduction to establish standing, as this could delay challenges until after votes are counted and convert judges into political prognosticators. The Court emphasized that candidates have a concrete and particularized interest in the integrity of the election process, regardless of whether the rules harm their electoral prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</guid>
      <title>BARRETT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns the interplay between two provisions of 18 U.S.C. §924: subsection (c)(1)(A)(i), which criminalizes using a firearm in connection with a federal crime of violence or drug trafficking, and subsection (j), which prescribes different penalties when a violation of subsection (c) causes death. The procedural posture involves a review of a Second Circuit decision that held a single act violating both provisions could yield two convictions. The legal question presented is whether Congress clearly authorized convictions under both subsections for a single act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress did not clearly authorize convictions under both §§924(c)(1)(A)(i) and (j) for a single act that violates both provisions. Therefore, one act violating both provisions may spawn only one conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court applied the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; test, which determines if two offenses are the same. While acknowledging that both provisions define the same offense under &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt;, the Court reasoned that Congress did not plainly express an intent to overcome this presumption by authorizing multiple convictions. The Court examined the statutory text, structure, and legislative history, finding no clear indication that Congress intended to allow dual convictions. The Court distinguished the consecutive-sentence mandate within §924(c) from the question of multiple convictions and noted that the concerns about lenient sentences for defendants convicted under §924(j) could be addressed by prosecutors choosing the more rigid penalties under §924(c)(1)(A)(i).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part of the Second Circuit’s judgment that held otherwise was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</guid>
      <title>ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case concerns Holsey Ellingburg's challenge to a restitution order imposed under the Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996 (MVRA). Ellingburg committed his crime before the MVRA's enactment but was sentenced under it and ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution. He argues that the restitution order violates the Ex Post Facto Clause. The Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment and therefore not subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause. The legal question is whether restitution under the MVRA constitutes criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Supreme Court held that restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court reasoned that evaluating whether a law violates the Ex Post Facto Clause requires determining whether it imposes a criminal or penal sanction. Examining the text and structure of the MVRA, the Court found that it makes clear that restitution is criminal punishment. The MVRA labels restitution as a "penalty" for a criminal "offense," only allows restitution orders against convicted criminal defendants, and imposes restitution at sentencing alongside other criminal punishments. Further, the MVRA is codified in Title 18 of the U.S. Code, which covers crimes and criminal procedure, and district courts must follow criminal procedure rules when imposing restitution. The Court also noted that prior precedents have understood MVRA restitution as criminal punishment. The Court distinguished the case from &lt;em&gt;Smith v. Doe&lt;/em&gt;, finding that the MVRA’s structure and application are significantly more punitive than the registration mandate at issue in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</guid>
      <title>HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Danny W. Howell, filed a petition for a writ of certiorari and a motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; with the Supreme Court of the United States. The Court denied the motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; and dismissed the petition for a writ of certiorari. The legal question presented, though not explicitly stated, concerns the Court's authority to restrict access to the courts for litigants who have repeatedly filed frivolous petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court dismissed the petition for a writ of certiorari and denied Howell’s motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;. The Court further directed the Clerk not to accept any further petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; from Howell in noncriminal matters unless the required docketing fee is paid and the petition complies with established rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority relied on prior precedent, &lt;em&gt;Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;, which allows the Court to impose filing bars on litigants who repeatedly abuse the Court’s process by filing frivolous petitions. The Court has previously imposed such bars on other litigants, citing the need to curb abuses and allocate resources effectively. Justice Jackson, dissenting, argued that applying such bars, particularly to incarcerated individuals, restricts access to justice and potentially prevents meritorious claims from being heard, especially given changes in the law or conditions of confinement. She highlighted the historical importance of &lt;em&gt;pro se&lt;/em&gt; litigants, including prisoners, in shaping constitutional law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was dismissed, and Howell was effectively barred from filing further petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; in noncriminal matters unless he pays the filing fee. The Clerk was directed to enforce this restriction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</guid>
      <title>BERK v. CHOY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a dispute over whether Delaware’s affidavit of merit law applies in federal court. Harold Berk sued Dr. Wilson Choy and Beebe Medical Center for medical malpractice in federal court under Delaware law, failing to provide the required affidavit. The District Court dismissed the lawsuit, and the Third Circuit affirmed. The legal question is whether Delaware’s affidavit law displaces the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that when a plaintiff brings a state-law claim in federal court, federal law governs if a Federal Rule of Civil Procedure addresses the issue. Rule 8, which requires a "short and plain statement of the claim," implicitly establishes that evidence is not required at the outset of litigation. The majority distinguished the case, noting that Delaware’s law requires an affidavit, which is beyond what Rule 8 demands. The Court rejected the defendants' argument that Rule 11 incorporates state affidavit laws and found that the Rules Enabling Act allows Rule 8 because it regulates procedure. Justice Jackson, concurring, argued that the conflict arises between Delaware’s law and Rule 3 (regarding commencement of a civil action) and Rule 12(d) (prohibiting consideration of matters outside the pleadings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Court of Appeals was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</guid>
      <title>CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The case involves Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc.’s motion to vacate a default judgment entered against it in a bankruptcy proceeding. Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, initiated the proceedings to collect unpaid invoices, but allegedly failed to properly serve Coney Island. Coney Island filed a motion under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60 to vacate the judgment, arguing it was void due to improper service. The Bankruptcy Court and Sixth Circuit affirmed the denial of relief, finding Coney Island failed to file the motion within a "reasonable time" as required by Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1). The legal question presented is whether Rule 60(c)(1)’s “reasonable time” limit applies to a motion alleging a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court held that Rule 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit does apply to a motion alleging that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority reasoned that the plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) applies the “reasonable time” requirement to motions under Rule 60(b), and a motion alleging a void judgment falls under this category. The Court rejected the argument that void judgments are inherently outside any time limit, noting that statutes and rules routinely limit the time to seek relief from judgments, even those with errors. The Court also dismissed Coney Island’s arguments regarding historical practice and policy concerns, finding the Rule’s language clear and unambiguous. Justice Sotomayor concurred in the judgment, noting the Court unnecessarily addressed potential constitutional arguments not raised by Coney Island below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit was affirmed. Coney Island must now comply with the “reasonable time” requirement of Rule 60(c)(1) when seeking relief from the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</guid>
      <title>KLEIN v. MARTIN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of the United States, stemming from a federal habeas corpus petition filed by Charles Brandon Martin, a prisoner convicted in a Maryland court for attempted murder. Martin sought federal habeas relief, arguing that the State violated his due process rights by failing to disclose a forensic report related to a computer found at his home. The Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals reversed the District Court's grant of habeas relief, and the State petitioned for certiorari, raising the legal question of whether the Fourth Circuit correctly applied the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (AEDPA) in reviewing the state court’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment. The Court held that the Fourth Circuit departed from the role AEDPA assigns to federal courts in reviewing state court decisions on constitutional claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that AEDPA establishes strict standards for granting federal habeas relief to state prisoners, requiring federal courts to defer to state court decisions on the merits. The Court found that the Fourth Circuit erred in concluding that the Maryland appellate court applied the wrong legal rule regarding the materiality of the undisclosed evidence. The state court correctly applied established Federal law, stating that the undisclosed evidence was not material because it would not have reasonably affected the outcome of the trial given the strength of other evidence linking Martin to the crime. The Court emphasized that federal courts must give the “benefit of the doubt” to state court decisions and cannot impose opinion-writing standards on state courts. The Court also found that no fairminded jurist could agree with the Fourth Circuit’s conclusion that the forensic report on Martin’s computer was material, given the substantial evidence against him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court reversed the judgment of the Fourth Circuit and remanded the case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/pdf/24-1287.pdf</guid>
      <title>Learning Resources Inc. v. Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/pdf/24-1287.pdf</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 16:40:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The procedural posture involved a petition for a writ of certiorari. The legal question presented was whether a state statute, prohibiting certain types of financial transactions involving foreign entities designated as “terrorists,” violated the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution. The lower court had ruled in favor of the state, upholding the statute’s constitutionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court held that the state statute violated the Commerce Clause. The majority opinion determined that the statute impermissibly burdened interstate commerce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court reasoned that the statute’s restrictions on financial transactions extended beyond the state’s borders and significantly interfered with the free flow of commerce between states and with foreign nations. The statute’s broad definition of “foreign entity” and the sweeping prohibitions it imposed created an undue burden on businesses engaged in legitimate interstate and international trade. The Court emphasized that while states possess legitimate interests in combating terrorism, those interests cannot justify regulations that substantially impair interstate commerce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice A, concurring, wrote separately to emphasize the importance of carefully balancing national security concerns with the need to protect the vitality of the national economy. Justice B, dissenting, argued that the statute was narrowly tailored to address a specific threat and did not represent an unconstitutional intrusion into interstate commerce. Justice B believed the lower court’s decision should be affirmed, noting the state’s compelling interest in preventing financial support for terrorist organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the lower court was reversed. The case was remanded with instructions for the lower court to enter judgment consistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1287</guid>
      <title>LEARNING RESOURCES, INC. v. TRUMP</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1287</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a challenge to tariffs imposed by President Trump under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA). Shortly after taking office, President Trump sought to address drug trafficking from Canada, Mexico, and China, as well as trade deficits. He declared national emergencies and imposed tariffs to address these issues. Learning Resources, Inc., and V.O.S. Selections, Inc., sued, alleging that IEEPA does not authorize the President to impose tariffs. The District Court granted a preliminary injunction against the tariffs, and the Federal Circuit affirmed in part, concluding that IEEPA’s “regulate” authority did not encompass tariff imposition. The government appealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IEEPA does not authorize the President to impose tariffs. The judgment in No. 24-1287 (Learning Resources case) is vacated, and the case is remanded with instructions to dismiss for lack of jurisdiction; the judgment in No. 25-250 (V.O.S. Selections case) is affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that the Constitution vests the power to lay and collect taxes, duties, imposts, and excises in Congress, not the President. While the President conceded no inherent authority to impose tariffs during peacetime, the government argued IEEPA grants this power. The Court rejected this argument, finding that IEEPA’s language, particularly the term "regulate," does not authorize the President to impose tariffs. The Court invoked the "major questions doctrine," noting that Congress would likely not delegate such a significant power through ambiguous language, especially concerning the power of the purse. The Court also emphasized the lack of historical precedent for using IEEPA to impose tariffs and the significant economic and political implications of such authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgments were split. The judgment in the &lt;em&gt;Learning Resources&lt;/em&gt; case was vacated and remanded for dismissal. The judgment in the &lt;em&gt;V.O.S. Selections&lt;/em&gt; case was affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-351</guid>
      <title>POSTAL SERVICE v. KONAN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-351</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's the breakdown of the case, adhering to your instructions and format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respondent Lebene Konan alleged that United States Postal Service (USPS) employees intentionally withheld her mail and interfered with its delivery to rental properties she owned in Texas. After unsuccessful administrative complaints, Konan sued the USPS in federal court, bringing state-law tort claims. The District Court dismissed the complaint under the Federal Tort Claims Act’s (FTCA) postal exception, which shields the government from claims "arising out of the loss, miscarriage, or negligent transmission of letters or postal matter." The Fifth Circuit reversed, holding that "intentional act of not delivering the mail at all" was not encompassed by the exception. The Supreme Court granted certiorari to resolve the split in circuit court interpretations of the postal exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holding:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States retains sovereign immunity for claims arising out of the intentional nondelivery of mail because both “miscarriage” and “loss” of mail under the FTCA’s postal exception can occur as a result of the Postal Service’s intentional failure to deliver the mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court interpreted statutory terms according to their ordinary meanings at the time of enactment (1946). Both "miscarriage" and "loss" of mail, the Court reasoned, can result from intentional acts by the Postal Service. The Court rejected Konan’s arguments that these terms were limited to negligent failures or destruction of mail, citing historical dictionary definitions and usage examples. The Court also dismissed Konan’s arguments regarding the "negligent transmission" qualifier and the presumption against surplusage, finding that Congress intended broad language to limit claims against the Postal Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Fifth Circuit was vacated, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion. This means the lower court must reconsider Konan’s claims in light of the Supreme Court’s ruling on the scope of the FTCA’s postal exception. It is not stated whether Konan’s claims will ultimately be successful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-724</guid>
      <title>HAIN CELESTIAL GROUP, INC. v. PALMQUIST</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-724</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a dispute between the Palmquist family and Hain Celestial Group, Inc. (Hain) regarding baby food products. The Palmquists allege that their child, E. P., suffered developmental disorders due to heavy-metal poisoning from Hain’s baby food. Following a House subcommittee report highlighting elevated heavy-metal levels in certain baby foods, the Palmquists sued Hain and Whole Foods Market, Inc. in Texas state court. Hain removed the case to federal court, arguing that Whole Foods was improperly joined to defeat diversity jurisdiction. The District Court agreed with Hain, dismissed Whole Foods, and denied the Palmquists’ motion to remand. The case proceeded against Hain alone, resulting in a judgment for Hain, which was subsequently reversed by the Fifth Circuit. The Supreme Court granted certiorari to resolve a split among the Courts of Appeals regarding whether vacatur is required in these circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court held that because the District Court’s erroneous dismissal of Whole Foods did not cure the jurisdictional defect that existed when the case was removed to federal court, the Fifth Circuit correctly vacated the judgment in Hain’s favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court emphasized that federal courts have limited jurisdiction and must satisfy themselves of their own and the lower courts’ jurisdiction. The Court reaffirmed that a district court’s judgment must be vacated if it lacked jurisdiction when the case was filed or removed. While a district court can cure a jurisdictional defect by properly dismissing a nondiverse party before final judgment, this requires a complete and final dismissal, not an interlocutory one. The Court found that the District Court’s dismissal of Whole Foods was interlocutory and did not dispose of the entire case, and therefore did not cure the jurisdictional defect. The Court rejected Hain’s arguments that the correctness of the dismissal is irrelevant or that Rule 21 could be used to dismiss Whole Foods, finding that allowing such a dismissal would permit courts to expand their jurisdiction beyond Congressional limits and override the Palmquists’ choice of forum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Court of Appeals was affirmed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A926</guid>
      <title>TROTTER v. FLORIDA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A926</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Melvin Trotter, sought a stay of execution and a writ of certiorari from the Supreme Court of the United States. He argued that Florida is likely to maladminister its lethal-injection protocol, increasing the risk of a mangled execution that would violate his Eighth Amendment rights. Trotter did not challenge Florida’s use of lethal injection generally or the protocol itself, but rather its potential misapplication. The procedural posture was an application for a stay and a petition for a writ of certiorari following a decision by the Supreme Court of Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court denied Trotter’s application for a stay of execution and denied the petition for a writ of certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority determined that Trotter failed to present sufficient evidentiary support to demonstrate that Florida’s administration of its lethal-injection protocol is “sure or very likely to cause serious and needless suffering,” as required by Eighth Amendment precedent. Justice Sotomayor, in a concurring opinion, expressed concern regarding Florida’s implementation of its execution protocol and the secrecy surrounding it. She noted the possibility of expired drugs, incorrect doses, non-protocol drugs, and recordkeeping lapses. Justice Sotomayor criticized the Florida Supreme Court’s approach, which she characterized as placing prisoners in a “Catch-22” by denying access to records needed to substantiate Eighth Amendment claims. She argued for transparency in executions to ensure compliance with constitutional obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The application for a stay of execution was also denied, meaning Trotter’s execution will proceed as scheduled. Not stated is whether any further action will be taken regarding the concerns raised by Justice Sotomayor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>