<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court of the United States - Recent Decisions — Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text</link>
    <description>Model-written summaries corresponding to the main feed items.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 23:34:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</guid>
      <title>BOYD v. HAMM</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case involves an application for a stay of execution and a petition for a writ of certiorari regarding Anthony Boyd's impending execution in Alabama. Boyd was sentenced to death and challenges the state's use of nitrogen hypoxia as a method of execution, arguing it violates the Eighth Amendment. He requests execution by firing squad instead. The procedural posture is an appeal from the Eleventh Circuit, which denied a stay. The central question presented is whether Alabama’s use of nitrogen hypoxia as an execution method constitutes cruel and unusual punishment under the Eighth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay of execution is denied. The petition for a writ of certiorari is also denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Sotomayor, Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court declined to intervene in the execution, effectively upholding Alabama’s right to use nitrogen hypoxia. The majority refused to grant a stay or review the case, allowing the execution to proceed as scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting justices, led by Justice Sotomayor, argued that the Court erred in denying the stay and certiorari. They contended that nitrogen hypoxia, as implemented in Alabama, poses a substantial risk of conscious terror and psychological pain, exceeding what is inherent in any constitutional method of execution. The dissent highlighted firsthand accounts of executions using nitrogen hypoxia, noting violent movements, gasping for air, and prolonged suffering lasting several minutes. They distinguished between the ordinary distress of facing execution and the additional, unnecessary psychological torment inflicted by nitrogen hypoxia. The dissent also criticized the District Court’s flawed comparison between the pain of nitrogen hypoxia and the pain of a firing squad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied, and the application for a stay was also denied. As a result, Anthony Boyd’s execution by nitrogen hypoxia proceeded as scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ORR</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves an application for a stay of a preliminary injunction issued by the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts. The District Court preliminarily enjoined the Government from enforcing a policy requiring all new passports to display an individual’s biological sex at birth. The First Circuit declined to stay the injunction pending appeal, prompting the Government to file this stay application with the Supreme Court. The Court considered the familiar stay factors to determine whether to grant the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay was granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas, Justice Alito, Justice Gorsuch, Justice Kavanaugh, and Chief Justice Roberts.
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson, Justice Sotomayor, and Justice Kagan.
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; None.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court granted the application for a stay, meaning the District Court’s order is temporarily suspended. The stay will remain in effect pending the disposition of the appeal in the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit and the resolution of a petition for a writ of certiorari, if filed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that the Government was likely to succeed on the merits of its appeal, as displaying an individual’s sex at birth does not violate equal protection principles and the State Department did not act arbitrarily and capriciously in declining to depart from Presidential rules. They also found that the District Court’s class-wide injunction concerning a Government document with foreign affairs implications caused an “irreparable injury” to the Government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting justices argued that the Court misunderstood its role in deciding stay applications and failed to adequately consider the balance of equities. They contended that the Government had not demonstrated any harm from the injunction and that the plaintiffs would suffer concrete injuries if the policy were enforced, including increased risk of harassment and discrimination. They criticized the Court for intervening in favor of the Government without sufficient justification and for disregarding the potential harm to vulnerable individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay was granted. The June 17, 2025 order of the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts is stayed pending the disposition of the appeal in the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit and disposition of a petition for a writ of certiorari, if such a writ is timely sought. Should certiorari be denied, this stay shall terminate automatically. In the event certiorari is granted, the stay shall terminate upon the sending down of the judgment of this Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</guid>
      <title>VENENO v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The petitioner, Veneno, sought review to reconsider &lt;em&gt;United States v. Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, a case establishing the federal government's "plenary power" over Native American tribal affairs. The question presented, if review had been granted, was whether &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; should be overturned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied.
- Concurred: Justice Thomas
- Dissented from the denial of certiorari: Justice Gorsuch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court declined to reconsider &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, a decision that upheld the Major Crimes Act of 1885 and established the federal government's broad authority over Native American tribal affairs. The dissenting justices argued that this decision lacked constitutional basis and should be overturned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The dissenting opinion, authored by Justice Gorsuch, argued that &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; was based on flawed reasoning and archaic prejudices, lacking any foundation in the Constitution. It criticized the Court's reliance on the Territories Clause and the doctrine of discovery, asserting that these doctrines do not grant Congress plenary power over tribal affairs. The dissent emphasized the Tribes' inherent sovereignty and the principle of limited federal powers, citing &lt;em&gt;Worcester v. Georgia&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;McCulloch v. Maryland&lt;/em&gt;. Justice Gorsuch also criticized the Court's historical reliance on paternalistic views of Native American tribes as "weak and helpless," arguing that such views are inconsistent with constitutional principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
Petition for writ of certiorari denied. The decision in &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; remains in effect, but the dissenting justices expressed hope that the Court will eventually reconsider the decision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</guid>
      <title>HUTSON v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari after a ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit. The central question presented was whether the lower courts erred in upholding a District Court order requiring New Orleans to construct a new facility for inmates with mental-health needs, particularly in light of the Prison Litigation Reform Act of 1995 (PLRA), which appears to prohibit courts from ordering prison construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: Justice Gorsuch, Justice Alito (joined by Justice Thomas).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court declined to review the Fifth Circuit’s decision, effectively allowing the lower court’s order requiring the construction of the facility to stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting justices argued that the lower courts erred in multiple ways. First, they contended that the District Court’s order to construct a new facility violated the PLRA, which explicitly prohibits courts from ordering prison construction. Second, they asserted that the injunction should have been terminated automatically after two years, as required by the PLRA, and that the lower courts improperly shifted the burden of proof to the party seeking termination. The dissent highlighted a Circuit split regarding which party bears the burden of demonstrating the continued necessity of the injunction, noting that Fifth Circuit precedent places the burden on the party supporting the injunction. The dissent believed the case presented an important issue of federal law warranting Supreme Court review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was denied. The Fifth Circuit’s decision upholding the injunction remains in effect, and New Orleans is required to continue construction of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</guid>
      <title>PITTS v. MISSISSIPPI</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of Mississippi. The central question before the Court was whether the Mississippi Supreme Court correctly applied the Sixth Amendment’s Confrontation Clause when it upheld the trial court’s decision to screen a child witness from the defendant in a child abuse case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mississippi Supreme Court’s judgment is reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice King.
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that the Mississippi Supreme Court erred in upholding the trial court’s decision to screen the child witness without making the required case-specific finding of necessity, as mandated by the Sixth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reiterated that the Sixth Amendment guarantees a defendant the right to a face-to-face meeting with witnesses, but this right can be limited in child abuse cases if a court makes a case-specific finding of necessity based on evidence of trauma. The Mississippi Supreme Court attempted to distinguish prior Supreme Court cases (&lt;em&gt;Coy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Craig&lt;/em&gt;) by arguing that Mississippi’s statute was mandatory, involved a victim’s rights provision, the child’s age, the lack of dispute over the perpetrator’s identity, and the method of separation between the witness and defendant. The Court found these distinctions unpersuasive, emphasizing that state law must yield to the Federal Constitution and that a mandatory statute, like Mississippi’s, is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; constitutionally problematic, not less, because it eliminates the need for a case-specific finding. The Court also rejected the State’s argument that the trial court had made a sufficient finding of necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari is granted, the judgment of the Mississippi Supreme Court is reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings. The State may argue, and the Mississippi Supreme Court may consider, whether the error warrants a new trial under the harmless-error standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</guid>
      <title>BECK v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari before the Supreme Court. The issue presented is whether the Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA) should be interpreted to bar recovery for a wrongful death claim arising from a car accident involving a civilian government employee and a servicemember who was off-duty and going home for lunch. The Court denied the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that, out of respect for &lt;em&gt;stare decisis&lt;/em&gt; and recognizing reliance interests generated by the precedent, it would deny the petition for certiorari, even though the case presented an opportunity to reconsider the application of the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Sotomayor, writing separately, acknowledged the difficulties in justifying the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine, which has been widely criticized and has caused confusion. However, she argued that &lt;em&gt;stare decisis&lt;/em&gt; has “enhanced force” in questions of statutory interpretation, particularly when Congress has repeatedly considered but declined to overrule the Court’s interpretation of a statute. Justice Thomas, dissenting from the denial of certiorari, argued that the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine lacks textual basis in the FTCA and that the lower courts are deeply divided on its application. He contended that the case did not involve sensitive military affairs and that the Court should have granted certiorari to resolve the circuit split and clarify the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The lower court’s decision stands, and Mrs. Beck will not recover for her husband’s wrongful death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</guid>
      <title>CLARK v. SWEENEY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Jeremiah Sweeney, was convicted of second-degree murder and other crimes in Maryland state court. His convictions were affirmed on appeal, and his postconviction relief bid was unsuccessful. He then sought habeas relief in Federal District Court, which was denied. The Fourth Circuit reversed the District Court's decision and ordered a new trial, relying on a claim Sweeney never asserted. The question before the Supreme Court was whether the Fourth Circuit’s departure from the principle of party presentation warrants reversal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: None stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: Judge Quattlebaum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: None stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that the Fourth Circuit erred in granting relief based on a claim not raised by Sweeney and not addressed by the State, thereby violating the principle of party presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court emphasized the principle of party presentation in the adversarial legal system, where courts act as neutral arbiters of issues raised by the parties. The Fourth Circuit’s action of creating a new claim based on “extraordinary failures” deviated significantly from this principle. Justice Quattlebaum, in dissent, criticized the majority for “flout[ing]” traditional principles of party presentation. The Court referenced &lt;em&gt;United States v. Sineneng-Smith&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lomax v. Ortiz-Marquez&lt;/em&gt; to reinforce the importance of adhering to the party-presentation principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Fourth Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. On remand, the Fourth Circuit must analyze the ineffective-assistance claim Sweeney originally asserted, applying a “doubly deferential” standard under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</guid>
      <title>ABBOTT v. LEAGUE OF UNITED LATIN AMERICAN CITIZENS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a challenge to a new congressional map drawn by the State of Texas, alleging that the legislature's motive was predominantly racial. A three-judge District Court agreed and enjoined the use of the new map in the 2026 elections. The State of Texas and several officials applied to the Supreme Court for a stay of the District Court's order pending appeal. The Court considered whether Texas satisfied the traditional criteria for interim relief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay was granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts, Justice Sotomayor, Justice Jackson
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Alito, Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court granted the stay of the District Court's order, allowing Texas to use the new congressional map in the 2026 elections pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court found that Texas likely would succeed on the merits of its claim, citing the District Court's failure to honor the presumption of legislative good faith and its failure to draw an adverse inference against the respondents. The Court also emphasized that lower federal courts should ordinarily not alter election rules on the eve of an election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissenting justices argued that the Court disregarded the District Court’s thorough factual findings and that the Court’s decision disrespects the work of the District Court. They contended that the District Court’s findings indicated that Texas largely divided its citizens along racial lines to create a pro-Republican map, violating the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments. They also criticized the Court’s failure to apply the clear-error standard of review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The District Court’s November 18, 2025 order was stayed pending the filing of an appeal in this Court. The stay will remain in effect pending the Court’s action on the appeal, or until the judgment is affirmed or dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</guid>
      <title>JOHN DOE v. DYNAMIC PHYSICAL  THERAPY, LLC, et al.</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari before the Supreme Court of the United States. The Louisiana Court of Appeal held that a state statute immunizing healthcare providers from civil liability during a public health emergency barred the plaintiff’s federal claims. The Court addressed the question of whether a state can confer immunity from federal causes of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holding:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Louisiana Court of Appeal’s decision is incorrect. States do not have the power to confer immunity from federal causes of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that defining the scope of liability under state law is within the State’s prerogative. However, a State’s power does not extend to conferring immunity from federal causes of action. The Court cited precedent supporting this principle and emphasized the Supremacy Clause of the U.S. Constitution, which dictates that federal law prevails over conflicting state laws. The Court acknowledged that the plaintiff’s federal claims might fail on other federal grounds, but that determination should be made by the Louisiana courts initially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari is granted, the judgment of the Louisiana Court of Appeal is reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings not inconsistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</guid>
      <title>DAVENPORT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Antonio Nathaniel Davenport, Jr., sought a writ of certiorari after losing in the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. The central question addressed, though not explicitly framed as such, concerns whether the District Court erred in denying Davenport’s request for a jury instruction defining "reasonable doubt" in relation to the state-law element of murder within a federal murder-in-aid-of-racketeering charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court declined to review the case, finding the petition untimely. Justice Sotomayor, writing separately, addressed the District Court’s error in stating that federal courts are prohibited from defining reasonable doubt for a jury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Sotomayor’s separate opinion argues that the District Court misconstrued existing precedent. &lt;em&gt;Victor v. Nebraska&lt;/em&gt; established that the Constitution does not prohibit trial courts from defining reasonable doubt, and most Courts of Appeals allow such definitions at the discretion of the court. While acknowledging that defining reasonable doubt can sometimes be unhelpful or confusing, Justice Sotomayor emphasized that it is not always the case and that district courts should weigh the circumstances of each case to determine whether a definition is appropriate. She noted that jurors often struggle to understand the term without explanation and that a definition can be particularly useful to clarify potential confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The lower court’s decision stands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ILLINOIS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves an application for a stay pending appeal. The central question before the Court concerned whether the President exceeded his authority under 10 U.S.C. §12406(3) by calling the National Guard into federal service to assist in executing federal law in Illinois. The procedural posture involved a challenge to a District Court’s holding regarding the President’s determination of his inability to execute federal law using civilian federal law enforcement officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Alito&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court ruled in favor of the respondents, accepting an argument they raised for the first time, contrary to their position below, that "regular forces" means the military. The Court effectively added language to the statutory text and expressed tentative views on other important, unresolved legal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Alito, joined by Justice Thomas, strongly dissented, arguing the Court departed from standard practice by raising and ruling on an argument waived by the respondents. He criticized the Court's expansion of the statutory text and its tentative views on other complex legal issues lacking sufficient briefing or oral argument. The dissent emphasized the importance of adhering to the "party-presented controversy" and suggested the Court should have granted the application based on the arguments initially presented. Justice Gorsuch, in a separate dissent, expressed caution regarding the unresolved questions surrounding the use of the National Guard and the military in domestic law enforcement, advocating for a narrower decision based solely on the preserved arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay was denied. The District Court’s decision was not affirmed, reversed, or vacated, but the Court’s ruling effectively supported the District Court’s interpretation of the law. The next steps are not stated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</guid>
      <title>BOWE v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Michael S. Bowe, who is serving a 24-year federal sentence after pleading guilty to conspiracy to commit robbery, attempted robbery, and using a firearm in relation to a crime of violence. Bowe is seeking postconviction relief from a mandatory consecutive 10-year sentence imposed under 18 U.S.C. §924(c), arguing that his underlying offenses do not qualify as "crimes of violence" under that statute. The Court granted certiorari to resolve a circuit split regarding the applicability of 28 U.S.C. §2244(b)(1) to second or successive motions filed by federal prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Gorsuch, Justice Thomas, Justice Alito, Justice Barrett&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that 28 U.S.C. §2244(b)(3)(E) does not bar this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion, and that 28 U.S.C. §2244(b)(1) does not apply to second or successive motions filed by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that §2244(b)(3)(E), which restricts certiorari review of authorization decisions for state prisoners, does not clearly apply to federal prisoners due to the distinct statutory framework governing federal prisoners under §2255. The cross-reference in §2255(h) to §2244 is narrow and specific, incorporating only procedures related to certification, not the certiorari bar itself. The Court also found that applying §2244(b)(1) to federal prisoners would disregard the differences in statutory language and purpose between §2254 (for state prisoners) and §2255 (for federal prisoners). The dissenting opinion argued that the Court's interpretation creates an illogical distinction and misinterprets the statutory scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vacated and remanded. The case is sent back to the Eleventh Circuit to determine whether Bowe should receive authorization to file a second or successive motion under the correct standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</guid>
      <title>CASE v. MONTANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves a challenge to a warrantless entry into William Case's home by Montana police officers responding to a 911 call reporting a suicide threat and a possible gunshot. The procedural posture is an appeal to the Supreme Court following a decision by the Montana Supreme Court upholding the officers’ entry as lawful under Montana’s caretaker doctrine. The question presented was whether the “objectively reasonable basis” standard for warrantless home entries to render emergency aid, established in &lt;em&gt;Brigham City v. Stuart&lt;/em&gt;, applies without further gloss, or whether officers must have probable cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court held that the &lt;em&gt;Brigham City&lt;/em&gt; standard applies without further gloss and was satisfied in this case.
Concurred: Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts
Concurred: Justice Sotomayor
Concurred: Justice Gorsuch
The holding affirms the judgment of the Montana Supreme Court, finding that the officers had an objectively reasonable basis to believe emergency aid was needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court reasoned that the &lt;em&gt;Brigham City&lt;/em&gt; standard, requiring an "objectively reasonable basis for believing" that an occupant needs emergency assistance, should not be interpreted as requiring probable cause, which is typically required for criminal investigations. The Court distinguished the emergency aid context from criminal investigations, noting that applying a probable cause standard would be awkward and inappropriate. Justice Sotomayor, concurring, emphasized the importance of considering the unique circumstances of mental health crises and the potential for escalation when law enforcement is involved. Justice Gorsuch, concurring, highlighted the historical basis of the emergency aid exception in common law principles regarding property rights and the need to protect human safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
Affirmed. The judgment of the Montana Supreme Court is affirmed, meaning the lower court’s decision is upheld. The case is concluded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</guid>
      <title>BOST v. ILLINOIS STATE BD. OF ELECTIONS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's the breakdown of the case, formatted as requested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a challenge to Illinois law, which requires election officials to count mail-in ballots postmarked or certified no later than election day but received within two weeks of election day. Congressman Michael Bost and two other political candidates (petitioners) sued the Illinois State Board of Elections, alleging that this procedure violates federal law (2 U.S.C. §7 and 3 U.S.C. §1), which sets election day as the Tuesday following the first Monday in November. The district court dismissed the case, and the Seventh Circuit affirmed, finding the petitioners lacked standing. The central question before the Supreme Court was whether Congressman Bost, as a candidate, had standing to challenge the rules governing the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holding:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a candidate for office, Congressman Bost has standing to challenge the rules that govern the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Barrett, Justice Kagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson, Justice Sotomayor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that candidates have a particularized interest in the rules governing vote counting, extending beyond merely winning the election to include a fair process and the integrity of the electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that unlawful election rules can injure a candidate in several ways, including causing them to lose the election, requiring additional resources, or damaging their reputation. They emphasized that candidates have an interest in a fair process and that rules undermining the integrity of the electoral process also undermine the winner’s political legitimacy. The Court rejected the Seventh Circuit’s requirement that candidates demonstrate a substantial risk of losing the election or failing to achieve a specific vote threshold to establish standing, arguing that such a requirement could delay challenges and undermine confidence in election results. Justice Barrett, concurring, argued that Bost had standing based on a traditional "pocketbook injury" due to the costs of monitoring ballot counting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Jackson, dissenting, argued that the majority’s holding improperly expands standing by disregarding the requirement of a particularized injury. She contended that the asserted harm—a fair electoral process—is not unique to candidates but is shared by all voters and that the Court’s reasoning undermines the separation of powers by allowing the judiciary to resolve questions of broad public significance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</guid>
      <title>BARRETT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns the relationship between two provisions of 18 U.S.C. §924: subsection (c)(1)(A)(i), which criminalizes using a firearm in connection with a federal crime of violence or drug trafficking crime, and subsection (j), which prescribes different penalties when a violation of subsection (c) causes death. The Second Circuit held that a single act violating both provisions could yield two convictions. The Court granted certiorari to resolve a split among the Courts of Appeals regarding whether a single act violating both provisions could yield two convictions or only one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress did not clearly authorize convictions under both §§924(c)(1)(A)(i) and (j) for a single act that violates both provisions. Therefore, one act violating both provisions may spawn only one conviction. The Second Circuit’s judgment holding otherwise is reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court applied the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; test, which asks whether each statute requires proof of a fact the other does not. The Court found that both §924(c)(1)(A)(i) and §924(j) define the same offense. While the Government argued that Congress intended to authorize multiple convictions, the Court found no “plainly expressed” intent to overcome the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; presumption. The Court distinguished the case from &lt;em&gt;Garrett&lt;/em&gt;, noting the absence of a continuing criminal enterprise and the classic relationship of a lesser included offense to a greater offense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court affirmed the principle that Congress must clearly express an intent to overcome the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; presumption to authorize multiple convictions for the same offense. The judgment of the Second Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</guid>
      <title>ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Holsey Ellingburg's challenge to a restitution order imposed under the Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996 (MVRA). Ellingburg committed his crime before the MVRA's enactment but was sentenced under it and ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution. He argues that the restitution order violates the Ex Post Facto Clause. The Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment and therefore not subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause. The central question before the Supreme Court was whether restitution under the MVRA constitutes criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; None
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; None&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court analyzed the MVRA's text and structure, finding that it labels restitution as a "penalty" for a criminal "offense" and is imposed at sentencing alongside other criminal punishments. The government, not the victim, is the adverse party at sentencing, and the MVRA is codified in Title 18, "Crimes and Criminal Procedure." The Court emphasized that prior precedents have understood MVRA restitution as criminal punishment. The Court rejected the argument that the government's intent or the procedural aspects of the law negated its punitive nature, finding that the MVRA's text and structure clearly demonstrate an intent to impose criminal punishment. The concurring opinion emphasized a return to the original understanding of the Ex Post Facto Clause, focusing on whether the law imposed a coercive penalty for a public wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court's opinion. The Court of Appeals may consider the government's separate arguments for affirmance of the District Court’s judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</guid>
      <title>HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedural posture is a petition for a writ of certiorari and a motion for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; to the Supreme Court of Indiana. The Court considered whether to dismiss the petition and whether to impose restrictions on the petitioner's ability to file future petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;. The question before the Court was whether to grant the petitioner leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was dismissed, and the motion for leave to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; was denied. The Clerk was directed not to accept further petitions in noncriminal matters from the petitioner unless the docketing fee is paid and the petition complies with specific rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The holding essentially bars the petitioner from filing future petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; in noncriminal matters unless he pays the required filing fee and adheres to specific procedural rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that the petitioner had repeatedly abused the Court's process by filing frivolous petitions, justifying the imposition of a filing bar, similar to those previously applied in &lt;em&gt;Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;. Justice Jackson, dissenting, argued that a categorical, forward-looking filing bar is a questionable restriction, particularly for incarcerated individuals. She highlighted that the petitioner has only filed a handful of petitions over 14 years and that barring him from challenging his conviction or conditions of confinement without requiring payment of the filing fee is unduly restrictive. She emphasized the importance of maintaining access to the courts for indigent litigants, especially those incarcerated, and expressed concern that the Court is routinely imposing such bars, even in cases where meritorious claims might arise in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition was dismissed, and the motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; was denied. The Clerk was directed to restrict the petitioner's ability to file future petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; unless certain conditions are met.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</guid>
      <title>BERK v. CHOY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a challenge to Delaware law requiring a medical professional's affidavit attesting to the merit of a medical malpractice suit to accompany the plaintiff's complaint. Harold Berk sued Dr. Wilson Choy and Beebe Medical Center in federal court for medical malpractice under Delaware law, failing to provide the required affidavit. The District Court dismissed Berk’s lawsuit, and the Third Circuit affirmed, leading Berk to petition the Supreme Court. The Court granted certiorari to answer the question of whether Delaware’s affidavit law applies in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; None
&lt;strong&gt;Abstained:&lt;/strong&gt; None&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure displace contrary state law, even if the state law would qualify as substantive under Erie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 8 governs the information a plaintiff must present about the merits of a claim at the outset of litigation, requiring only a "short and plain statement of the claim." This implicitly establishes that evidence of the claim is not required. Rule 12 reinforces this point, providing grounds for dismissal only for failure to state a claim and prohibiting courts from considering matters outside the pleadings. The Court rejected the defendants' argument that Rule 11 incorporates state affidavit laws, finding it inapplicable to affidavits from third parties. The Court also found that the Rules Enabling Act allows for the application of Federal Rules, as they regulate procedure rather than substance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Jackson, concurring in the judgment, argued that the relevant conflict arises between Delaware’s law and Federal Rule 3, which governs the commencement of a civil action. She disagreed with the majority’s framing of the question as whether the lawsuit may be dismissed, asserting that the statute addresses the requirements for filing a complaint. She also highlighted a conflict with Rule 12(d), which prohibits courts from considering matters outside the pleadings when dismissing a case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Court of Appeals was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</guid>
      <title>CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a dispute arising from a bankruptcy proceeding. Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, initiated adversarial proceedings against Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc., to collect unpaid invoices. Vista-Pro attempted service by mail, which Coney Island contends was improper. Coney Island failed to answer, resulting in a default judgment. After six years and attempts to enforce the judgment, Coney Island filed a motion to vacate the judgment under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60, arguing the judgment was void due to improper service. The Bankruptcy Court denied relief, finding Coney Island failed to file the motion within a "reasonable time" as required by Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1). This decision was affirmed by the District Court and the Sixth Circuit. The question before the Court was whether Rule 60(c)(1)’s “reasonable time” requirement applies to a motion alleging a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurred: Justice Kagan, Chief Justice Roberts, Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch, Justice Kavanaugh, Justice Barrett, and Justice Jackson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissented: Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstained: Not stated.
The Court held that a motion alleging a judgment is void must be brought within a reasonable time, as dictated by Rule 60(c)(1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that the plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) clearly states that motions under Rule 60(b) must be made within a reasonable time. The Court rejected the argument that void judgments are inherently unenforceable and thus exempt from time limits, noting that other legal errors are routinely subject to time constraints. The Court also dismissed Coney Island’s argument that courts have historically allowed voidness challenges at any time, emphasizing that Rule 60’s text and structure take precedence. The Court further rejected Coney Island’s policy arguments and concerns about constitutional avoidance, finding them unpersuasive. Justice Sotomayor, concurring in the judgment, argued that the Court unnecessarily addressed potential due process considerations, as Coney Island had not raised such an argument below or before this Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Affirmed. The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit was affirmed, meaning Coney Island’s motion to vacate the judgment was denied, and the default judgment against Coney Island remains in effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</guid>
      <title>KLEIN v. MARTIN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari to review a decision by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Charles Brandon Martin was convicted in a Maryland court for the attempted murder of his girlfriend, Jodi Torok. Martin sought federal habeas relief, arguing that the State violated his right to due process by failing to disclose a forensic report related to a computer found at his home. The Fourth Circuit affirmed the award of a new trial based on this failure, reasoning that the lower courts had departed from the role AEDPA assigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment. The Court held that the Fourth Circuit’s decision departed from the standards prescribed by the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (AEDPA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.
&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson
&lt;strong&gt;Concurred in the Judgment:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.
&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.
&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority opinion emphasized the strict standards governing federal habeas relief under AEDPA, requiring deference to state court decisions. The Court found that the Fourth Circuit erred in two ways: first, by concluding the state appellate court applied the wrong legal rule regarding &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; material, and second, by holding that every fairminded jurist would find the undisclosed forensic report material. The Court noted that the state appellate court correctly cited and synthesized relevant precedent, stating that the evidence linking Martin to the crime was so strong that the disclosure of the report would not have changed the outcome. The Court rejected the Fourth Circuit’s focus on the report’s potential to undermine the State’s case, highlighting the substantial evidence supporting Martin’s conviction, including DNA evidence, witness testimony, and circumstantial evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari, reversed the judgment of the Fourth Circuit, and remanded the case for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>