<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court of the United States - Recent Decisions — Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text</link>
    <description>Model-written summaries corresponding to the main feed items.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 23:59:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</guid>
      <title>BOYD v. HAMM</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A457</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitioner, Anthony Boyd, sought a stay of execution and a writ of certiorari. He challenged Alabama’s use of nitrogen hypoxia as a method of execution, arguing it violated the Eighth Amendment. The District Court denied his request for a preliminary injunction, and the Eleventh Circuit denied a stay, finding no abuse of discretion in the District Court’s ruling. The legal question presented was whether Alabama’s use of nitrogen hypoxia as an execution method constitutes cruel and unusual punishment under the Eighth Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay of execution is denied, and the petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred in the Judgement:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Sotomayor, Justice Kagan, Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice E&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority declined to grant a stay or certiorari. Justice Sotomayor, joined by Justices Kagan and Jackson, dissented, arguing that Boyd demonstrated a substantial risk of conscious terror and psychological pain with nitrogen hypoxia, and that a firing squad presented a feasible alternative. The dissent highlighted evidence from previous executions using nitrogen hypoxia, noting prolonged periods of conscious suffering, convulsions, and gasping for air. The dissent criticized the District Court and Eleventh Circuit for failing to adequately consider the differences between nitrogen hypoxia and a firing squad, particularly the extended duration of conscious suffering with the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied, and the application for a stay was denied. As a result, Anthony Boyd’s execution by nitrogen hypoxia proceeded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ORR</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A319</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves an application for a stay of a preliminary injunction issued by the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts. The District Court preliminarily enjoined the Government from enforcing a policy requiring all new passports to display an individual’s biological sex at birth. The First Circuit declined to stay the injunction pending appeal, prompting the Government to file this stay application with the Supreme Court. The legal question presented is whether to grant the Government’s application for a stay pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application for a stay is granted. The June 17, 2025 order of the United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts is stayed pending the disposition of the appeal in the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit and disposition of a petition for a writ of certiorari, if such a writ is timely sought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred in the Judgement:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson, Justice Sotomayor, Justice Kagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that the Government is likely to succeed on the merits, as displaying passport holders’ sex at birth does not offend equal protection principles and the State Department did not act arbitrarily and capriciously in declining to depart from Presidential rules. Furthermore, the District Court’s class-wide injunction concerns an Executive Branch policy with foreign affairs implications, and the Government will suffer irreparable injury absent a stay. The dissenting Justices argued that the Court misunderstood the assignment in deciding stay applications and failed to adequately consider the balance of equities, particularly the harm to individuals subjected to the policy. They asserted the Government offered no evidence of harm from the injunction while plaintiffs would suffer imminent, concrete injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the District Court was stayed pending the disposition of the appeal in the First Circuit and a potential petition for a writ of certiorari. The stay will terminate automatically if certiorari is denied and upon the sending down of the judgment of this Court if certiorari is granted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</guid>
      <title>VENENO v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5191</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The petitioner, Veneno, sought review to reconsider &lt;em&gt;United States v. Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, which established the theory of “plenary power” over Native American tribal affairs. The legal question presented was whether the federal government’s authority over Native American tribes extends to plenary power, or is limited by the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority denied certiorari, leaving &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; intact. Justice Gorsuch, joined by Justice Thomas, dissented from the denial, arguing that &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt; lacked constitutional foundation and should be overturned. The dissent asserted that Native American tribes are sovereign entities with inherent powers, and the Major Crimes Act, upheld in &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;, represented an overreach of federal authority. The dissent criticized &lt;em&gt;Kagama&lt;/em&gt;'s reliance on outdated legal doctrines and its assertion that tribes are "weak and helpless," requiring federal protection. The dissent argued that Congress’s power is limited and enumerated, and that the Court should reconsider decisions upholding plenary power over tribal affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The judgment in &lt;em&gt;United States v. Kagama&lt;/em&gt; remains in effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</guid>
      <title>HUTSON v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1022</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner, Hutson, filed a petition for a writ of certiorari. The procedural posture is a petition for review of a lower court decision. The legal question presented, as articulated by the dissenting justices, concerns the legality of a District Court order mandating the construction of a prison facility and the subsequent termination of that order under the Prison Litigation Reform Act of 1995 (PLRA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.
Per Curiam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority declined to review the case. The dissenting justices argued that the lower courts erred in failing to terminate the prison-building injunction. They contended that the PLRA explicitly prohibits courts from ordering prison construction and that the injunction should have been terminated immediately upon the filing of a motion to terminate. Further, they asserted that even if the injunction initially complied with the PLRA, it should have been terminable two years after its issuance. The dissent highlighted a Circuit split regarding which party bears the burden of demonstrating the continued necessity of the injunction, noting that Fifth Circuit precedent places the burden on the party supporting the injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied, leaving the Fifth Circuit’s decision in place. New Orleans will continue to be obligated to pay for the construction of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</guid>
      <title>PITTS v. MISSISSIPPI</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1159</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner, Jeffrey Clyde Pitts, was convicted of sexual abuse following a report from his daughter, A.G.C., to her mother. At trial, the State sought to place a screen between Pitts and his daughter during her testimony, citing a Mississippi statute granting child witnesses the right to a screen. Pitts objected, arguing the State had not met the Sixth Amendment's burden of demonstrating necessity for such screening. The Mississippi Supreme Court upheld the trial court's decision, distinguishing prior Supreme Court cases. The legal question presented was whether the Mississippi Supreme Court correctly applied Sixth Amendment principles regarding the Confrontation Clause in child abuse cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Mississippi Supreme Court erred in upholding the trial court's decision to screen the child witness without making a case-specific finding of necessity. The petition for certiorari is granted, the judgment of the Mississippi Supreme Court is reversed, and the case is remanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court reiterated that the Sixth Amendment guarantees a defendant the right to confront their accusers face-to-face, but this right can be limited in child abuse cases only if a court hears evidence and makes a case-specific finding of necessity, as established in &lt;em&gt;Coy v. Iowa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Maryland v. Craig&lt;/em&gt;. The Mississippi Supreme Court attempted to distinguish these precedents, citing a state constitutional provision regarding victims' rights, the mandatory nature of the state statute, the child witness's age, the lack of dispute over the perpetrator's identity, and the screening method used. The Court found these distinctions unpersuasive, emphasizing that state law cannot override the Federal Constitution and that a mandatory statute undermines the necessity requirement. The State argued the trial court had made a case-specific finding, but the Court rejected this, noting the trial court’s reliance on the statute’s mandatory nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the Mississippi Supreme Court was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings not inconsistent with this opinion. The State may argue, and the Mississippi Supreme Court may consider, whether the error warrants a new trial under the harmless-error standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</guid>
      <title>BECK v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-1078</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari following a denial of relief to Kari Beck, personal representative of the Estate of Cameron Gayle Beck, whose husband was killed in a car accident involving a civilian government employee on an Air Force base. The legal question presented, though not explicitly stated, concerns the application of the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine and whether it should bar recovery for injuries sustained in circumstances not directly related to military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.
- &lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Sotomayor
- &lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas
- &lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority, through Justice Sotomayor, declined to grant certiorari, citing the principle of &lt;em&gt;stare decisis&lt;/em&gt; and Congress’s repeated consideration of legislation to overrule or limit the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine without action. The Court reasoned that Congress retains the power to alter the interpretation of the Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA) and that judicial intervention would improperly encroach on Congress’s legislative authority. Justice Thomas, dissenting, argued that the &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt; doctrine lacks textual basis in the FTCA and that the circumstances of the husband’s death—occurring off-duty, away from military activities—did not warrant application of the doctrine. He further noted the widespread criticism and circuit splits regarding the application of &lt;em&gt;Feres&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment was affirmed. Kari Beck’s claim was denied, and she will not recover for her husband’s wrongful death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</guid>
      <title>CLARK v. SWEENEY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-52</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
Jeremiah Sweeney was convicted of second-degree murder and other crimes in Maryland state court, and his appeals were unsuccessful. He subsequently sought habeas relief in Federal District Court, which was denied. The Fourth Circuit reversed the District Court's decision and ordered a new trial, relying on a claim Sweeney did not raise in his petition. The legal question presented was whether the Fourth Circuit’s departure from the principle of party presentation warrants reversal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment. The Fourth Circuit erred in granting relief based on a claim Sweeney never asserted, thereby violating the principle of party presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court emphasized the principle of party presentation, which dictates that courts act as neutral arbiters of issues raised by the parties, not as independent investigators. The Fourth Circuit disregarded this principle by creating a new claim based on “extraordinary failures” not presented by Sweeney. Justice Quattlebaum’s dissent in the Fourth Circuit correctly criticized this approach as “flout[ing]” traditional principles. The Court noted that under the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996, review of state court decisions is highly deferential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the Fourth Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings. On remand, the Fourth Circuit must analyze the ineffective-assistance claim Sweeney originally asserted, applying a deferential standard of review to the state court’s prior decision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</guid>
      <title>ABBOTT v. LEAGUE OF UNITED LATIN AMERICAN CITIZENS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A608</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The State of Texas redrew its congressional districts, prompting a challenge from the League of United Latin American Citizens (LULAC), alleging the legislature’s motive was predominantly racial. A three-judge District Court agreed and enjoined the use of the new map in the 2026 elections. Texas and its officials sought a stay from the Supreme Court pending appeal. The legal question presented was whether the District Court’s order should be stayed pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The application for a stay is granted. The District Court’s November 18, 2025 order is stayed pending the filing of an appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Alito&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority found Texas satisfied the traditional criteria for interim relief, citing a preliminary evaluation of the case. The Court reasoned the District Court erred by failing to honor the presumption of legislative good faith and by failing to draw an adverse inference against the respondents. The Court also found Texas demonstrated irreparable harm and that the equities and public interest favored a stay, noting lower federal courts should ordinarily not alter election rules on the eve of an election. Justice Alito, concurring, emphasized the partisan motive behind the map and the lack of a viable alternative map from the respondents, arguing this supported an inference of non-racial intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the District Court was stayed pending appeal. The stay will remain in effect pending the Court’s action on the appeal, or until the judgment is affirmed or dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</guid>
      <title>JOHN DOE v. DYNAMIC PHYSICAL  THERAPY, LLC, et al.</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-180</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff, John Doe, sought to pursue federal claims against Dynamic Physical Therapy, LLC, and others. Louisiana law, specifically La. Rev. Stat. Ann. §29:771(B)(2)(c)(i), provides immunity to healthcare providers during public health emergencies. The Louisiana Court of Appeal held that this state statute barred Doe’s federal claims. The petition for a writ of certiorari was filed to challenge that decision. The legal question presented was whether a state law granting immunity to healthcare providers during a public health emergency could bar federal causes of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holding:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court held that a state cannot confer immunity from federal causes of action. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Per Curiam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court reasoned that defining the scope of liability under state law is within the State’s prerogative. However, a State lacks the power to grant immunity from federal causes of action. The Court cited established precedent affirming the Supremacy Clause of the U.S. Constitution, which dictates that federal law prevails over conflicting state laws. While the plaintiff’s federal claims might fail on other federal grounds, the Louisiana courts should initially address those issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petition for certiorari was granted, the judgment of the Louisiana Court of Appeal was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings not inconsistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</guid>
      <title>DAVENPORT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-7435</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner sought a writ of certiorari following a denial of relief by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. The legal question presented concerned whether the District Court erred in denying the petitioner’s request for a jury instruction defining "reasonable doubt" in relation to the underlying state-law murder charge in a murder in aid of racketeering case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Sotomayor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority denied certiorari without explanation. Justice Sotomayor concurred in the denial, noting the petition was untimely and counsel provided no explanation for the delay. Justice Sotomayor’s separate concurrence addressed the District Court’s error in stating that federal courts are prohibited from defining reasonable doubt. Citing &lt;em&gt;Victor v. Nebraska&lt;/em&gt;, she explained that the Constitution does not prohibit such definitions and that courts of appeals generally allow district judges discretion to define reasonable doubt. While acknowledging potential pitfalls in defining the term, Justice Sotomayor argued that district courts should carefully weigh the circumstances of each case to determine whether providing a definition is appropriate, particularly to address potential jury confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The petition for a writ of certiorari was denied. The judgment of the Fourth Circuit remains in effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</guid>
      <title>TRUMP v. ILLINOIS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25A443</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves an application for a stay pending review of a District Court order. The legal question presented concerns whether the President exceeded his authority under 10 U.S.C. §12406(3) by calling the National Guard into federal service to assist in executing federal law in Illinois. The parties disagreed on the meaning of "regular forces" within the statute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court granted the application for a stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Alito, Justice Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority determined that the District Court erred in refusing to credit the Government’s declarations regarding violence and threats to federal law enforcement officers. The Court also expressed concerns about the District Court’s interpretation of “unable” and its failure to afford deference to the President’s determination. Justice Alito, in a dissenting opinion, criticized the Court for raising and ruling on arguments not presented by the parties below and for expressing tentative views on other important issues without adequate briefing or oral argument. Justice Gorsuch, in a separate dissent, argued that the Court should have decided the application narrowly, based only on the arguments the parties preserved, and refrained from venturing into complex and unresolved legal questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment was stayed. The application for a stay was granted, effectively halting the District Court’s order pending further review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</guid>
      <title>BOWE v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5438</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns Michael S. Bowe, who is serving a 24-year federal sentence after pleading guilty to conspiracy to commit robbery, attempted robbery, and using a firearm in relation to a crime of violence. Bowe seeks postconviction relief from a mandatory consecutive 10-year sentence imposed under 18 U.S.C. §924(c), arguing that his underlying offenses do not qualify as "crimes of violence" under that statute. The legal question is whether §2244(b)(3)(E) bars this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion, and whether §2244(b)(1) applies to second or successive motions filed under §2255(h) by federal prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Court has jurisdiction because §2244(b)(3)(E) does not bar this Court’s review of a federal prisoner’s request to file a second or successive §2255 motion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;§2244(b)(1) does not apply to second or successive motions filed under §2255(h) by federal prisoners challenging their convictions or sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Roberts, C.J., Kagan, Kavanaugh, Jackson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Sotomayor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Thomas, Alito, Barrett (as to Part I)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that §2244(b)(3)(E), which prohibits certiorari review of authorization decisions for state prisoners, does not apply to federal prisoners because the cross-reference in §2255(h) is narrow and specific, incorporating only procedures related to how a panel certifies a filing, not broader provisions like the certiorari bar. The Court found no "clear indication" that Congress intended to strip this Court of jurisdiction over federal prisoner cases. Regarding §2244(b)(1), the Court held that it applies only to state prisoners’ habeas applications under §2254, not to federal prisoners’ motions under §2255, due to the statute's plain language and Congressional intent to treat state and federal prisoners differently. The dissent argued that the Court’s interpretation creates inconsistencies and misreads statutory language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Eleventh Circuit was vacated and remanded for further proceedings. The Eleventh Circuit is directed to determine in the first instance whether Bowe should receive authorization to file a second or successive motion under the correct standard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</guid>
      <title>CASE v. MONTANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-624</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
This case involves a challenge to a warrantless entry into a home by Montana police officers responding to a 911 call reporting that William Case was threatening suicide and may have shot himself. The procedural posture is an appeal from a decision of the Montana Supreme Court upholding the officers’ entry as lawful under Montana’s caretaker doctrine. The legal question presented is whether the Fourth Amendment requires police officers to have probable cause to believe that an occupant needs emergency aid before entering a home without a warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court held that the objective reasonableness standard for warrantless home entries to render emergency aid, established in &lt;em&gt;Brigham City v. Stuart&lt;/em&gt;, applies without further gloss and was satisfied in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kagan, Justice Sotomayor, Justice Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Thomas, Justice Alito, Justice Barrett&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority reasoned that the Fourth Amendment presumptively considers searches and seizures inside a home unreasonable without a warrant, but this is subject to exceptions, including the need to render emergency assistance. Citing &lt;em&gt;Brigham City v. Stuart&lt;/em&gt;, the Court reiterated that officers may enter when they have an “objectively reasonable basis for believing” that an occupant is seriously injured or imminently threatened with such injury. The Montana Supreme Court’s application of a “reasonable suspicion” standard deviated from this rule. The Court rejected Case’s argument that the standard should be “probable cause,” finding that standard is “peculiarly related to criminal investigations” and not appropriate for non-criminal, emergency situations. The officers’ actions were deemed objectively reasonable given the information from Case’s ex-girlfriend and their observations at the scene, suggesting a potential suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the Montana Supreme Court was affirmed. The case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</guid>
      <title>BOST v. ILLINOIS STATE BD. OF ELECTIONS</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-568</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's the breakdown of the case, adhering to your instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congressman Michael Bost and two other political candidates sued the Illinois State Board of Elections, challenging Illinois law that allows mail-in ballots postmarked or certified no later than election day to be counted if received within two weeks of election day. The plaintiffs contended that this practice conflicts with federal law establishing election day. The District Court dismissed the case, and the Seventh Circuit affirmed, finding the plaintiffs lacked standing. The legal question presented was whether a candidate for office has standing to challenge rules governing the counting of votes in their election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holding:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a candidate for office, Congressman Bost has standing to challenge the rules that govern the counting of votes in his election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Roberts, Justice Alito, Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch, Justice Kavanaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Barrett, Justice Kagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissented:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson, Justice Sotomayor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that candidates have a personal stake in the rules governing their elections, beyond simply winning. They have an interest in a fair process, as candidates seek to represent the people, and an unfair process undermines their political legitimacy and erodes public confidence. The Court rejected the argument that candidates must demonstrate a substantial risk of losing the election or suffering a significant vote share reduction to establish standing, as this could delay challenges until after the election and improperly transform judges into political prognosticators. The Court held that candidates have a concrete and particularized interest in the integrity of the election process, regardless of whether the rules harm their electoral prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Barrett, concurring, argued that Bost had standing based on a traditional "pocketbook injury" – the costs incurred to monitor the vote counting process and mitigate potential harm. Justice Jackson, dissenting, argued that the plaintiffs failed to allege a particularized injury, as the harm of an unfair election process is shared by all voters, not just candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</guid>
      <title>BARRETT v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-5774</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case concerns the relationship between two provisions of 18 U.S.C. §924: subsection (c)(1)(A)(i), which criminalizes using a firearm in connection with a federal crime of violence or drug trafficking crime, and subsection (j), which prescribes different penalties when a violation of subsection (c) causes death. The legal question presented is whether a single act violating both provisions can yield two convictions, one under each provision, or only one. The Second Circuit held that it could, but this Court granted certiorari to resolve a split among the Courts of Appeals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress did not clearly authorize convictions under both §§924(c)(1)(A)(i) and (j) for a single act violating both provisions. Therefore, one act violating both provisions may spawn only one conviction. The Second Circuit’s judgment holding otherwise is reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Roberts, Justice Sotomayor, Justice Kagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that Congress ordinarily does not intend to punish the same offense under two different statutes (the &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; presumption). While Congress can overcome this presumption with plainly expressed intent, the Court found no such clear intent in the statutory text regarding §924(c)(1)(A)(i) and §924(j). The Court noted that Congress used “in addition to” language in other parts of §924 to authorize multiple convictions, but not in relation to subsections (c)(1)(A)(i) and (j). The Court also rejected arguments that the different focuses of the two subsections justified multiple convictions. Justice Gorsuch, concurring separately, questioned the assumption that &lt;em&gt;Blockburger&lt;/em&gt; applies differently in concurrent versus successive prosecutions, suggesting a historical context where overlapping charges were less common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Second Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</guid>
      <title>ELLINGBURG v. UNITED STATES</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-482</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The Mandatory Victims Restitution Act of 1996 (MVRA) requires defendants convicted of certain federal crimes to pay monetary restitution to victims. Petitioner Ellingburg committed a crime before the MVRA’s enactment but was sentenced under the MVRA and ordered to pay $7,567.25 in restitution. He challenged his restitution obligation, arguing it violated the Ex Post Facto Clause. The Eighth Circuit concluded that restitution under the MVRA is not criminal punishment subject to the Ex Post Facto Clause. The legal question presented was whether restitution under the MVRA constitutes criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
Restitution under the MVRA is plainly criminal punishment for purposes of the Ex Post Facto Clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Kavanaugh, Justice Thomas, Justice Gorsuch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The Court determined that evaluating whether a law violates the Ex Post Facto Clause requires assessing whether it imposes a criminal or penal sanction. Examining the MVRA’s text and structure, the Court found that it clearly designates restitution as a “penalty” for a criminal “offense.” Restitution is imposed at sentencing alongside other criminal punishments, and the Government, not the victim, is the adverse party. The MVRA is codified in Title 18, “Crimes and Criminal Procedure,” and its provisions are contained within a chapter on “Miscellaneous Sentencing Provisions.” Prior Court precedents have also understood MVRA restitution as criminal punishment. The Court distinguished the case from &lt;em&gt;Smith v. Doe&lt;/em&gt;, noting that the MVRA’s structure and language demonstrate an intent to impose criminal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit was reversed and remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</guid>
      <title>HOWELL v. CIRCUIT COURT OF INDIANA</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-5557</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The petitioner, Danny W. Howell, filed a petition for a writ of certiorari and a motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; to the Supreme Court of Indiana. The legal question presented, though not explicitly stated, concerns the Court's authority to restrict access to the Court for indigent litigants who have repeatedly filed frivolous petitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
The Court dismissed the petition for a writ of certiorari and denied the motion to proceed &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt;. The Clerk is directed not to accept further petitions from Howell in noncriminal matters unless the docketing fee is paid and the petition complies with Rule 33.1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority’s reasoning relies on precedent established in &lt;em&gt;Martin v. District of Columbia Court of Appeals&lt;/em&gt;, allowing the Court to impose filing bars on litigants who have repeatedly abused the Court’s process. Justice Jackson, dissenting, argues that applying such bars, particularly to incarcerated individuals, is overly restrictive and potentially prevents meritorious claims from being heard. She highlights the potential for changes in law and prison conditions to give rise to valid claims, and notes that the administrative burden of reviewing petitions is minimal compared to the importance of ensuring access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment was dismissed. As a result of the ruling, Danny W. Howell is barred from filing further petitions &lt;em&gt;in forma pauperis&lt;/em&gt; in noncriminal matters unless he pays the required filing fee and complies with procedural rules.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</guid>
      <title>BERK v. CHOY</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-440</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's the edited output, adhering to all your instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a challenge to Delaware law requiring a medical professional's affidavit attesting to the merit of a medical malpractice suit to accompany the plaintiff's complaint. Harold Berk sued Dr. Wilson Choy and Beebe Medical Center in federal court for medical malpractice under Delaware law, failing to provide the required affidavit. The District Court dismissed the lawsuit, and the Third Circuit affirmed. The legal question presented is whether Delaware’s affidavit law applies in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holding:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaware’s affidavit law does not apply in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Roberts, Justice Thomas, Justice Alito, Justice Sotomayor, Justice Kagan, Justice Gorsuch, Justice Kavanaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority reasoned that when a plaintiff brings a state-law claim in federal court, a choice-of-law problem arises. The Rules of Decision Act directs federal courts to apply state substantive law unless otherwise required, but Federal Rules of Civil Procedure displace contrary state law when on point. Rule 8, which prescribes the information a plaintiff must present at the outset of litigation, establishes that a short and plain statement of the claim is sufficient, implicitly rejecting the need for additional evidence like an affidavit. The majority rejected the defendants’ argument that the affidavit requirement was a permissible precondition to filing, finding it inconsistent with the Federal Rules. Justice Jackson concurred in the judgment, arguing that the conflict arises between Delaware’s law and Federal Rule 3 regarding the requirements to commence a lawsuit, and also with Rule 12(d) regarding what a court can consider when dismissing a case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Court of Appeals was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</guid>
      <title>CONEY ISLAND AUTO PARTS UNLIMITED, INC. v. BURTON</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/24-808</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background:
The case involves Coney Island Auto Parts Unlimited, Inc.’s motion to vacate a default judgment entered against it in a bankruptcy proceeding. Vista-Pro Automotive, LLC, initiated the proceedings to collect unpaid invoices. Coney Island argues the judgment is void due to improper service. The Bankruptcy Court and Sixth Circuit denied relief, finding Coney Island failed to file the motion within a "reasonable time" as required by Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(c)(1). The legal question is whether this "reasonable time" limit applies to motions alleging a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding:
Rule 60(c)(1)’s reasonable-time limit applies to a motion alleging that a judgment is void under Rule 60(b)(4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Roberts, Justice Thomas, Justice Kagan, Justice Gorsuch, Justice Kavanaugh, Justice Barrett, and Justice Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurred (separately):&lt;/strong&gt; Justice Sotomayor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoning:
The majority reasoned that the plain text of Rule 60(c)(1) applies the “reasonable time” requirement to motions under Rule 60(b), and a motion alleging a void judgment falls under this category. The Court rejected the argument that void judgments are exempt from time limits, noting that other legal errors are routinely subject to time restrictions. The Court also dismissed Coney Island’s arguments regarding historical practice and policy concerns, finding the Rule’s language clear and unambiguous. Justice Sotomayor concurred in the judgment but expressed reservations about the Court’s discussion of potential due process concerns, noting Coney Island did not raise such an argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome:
The judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit was affirmed. Coney Island must comply with Rule 60(c)(1) and file a motion within a reasonable time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</guid>
      <title>KLEIN v. MARTIN</title>
      <link>https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/25-51</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case involves a petition for a writ of certiorari to review a decision by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Charles Brandon Martin was convicted in a Maryland court for the attempted murder of his girlfriend, Jodi Torok. Martin sought federal habeas relief, arguing that the State violated his right to due process by failing to disclose a forensic report related to a computer found at his home. The Fourth Circuit affirmed the award of a new trial based on this failure, reasoning that the lower courts had departed from the role AEDPA assigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holding:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari and reversed the Fourth Circuit’s judgment. The Court held that the Fourth Circuit’s decision departed from the standards prescribed by the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (AEDPA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joined the Majority:&lt;/strong&gt; Per Curiam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did Not Participate:&lt;/strong&gt; Not stated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasoning:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority opinion emphasized the strict standards governing federal habeas relief under AEDPA, requiring deference to state court decisions. The Court found that the Fourth Circuit erred in concluding the state appellate court applied the wrong legal rule, as the state court correctly cited and synthesized relevant precedent regarding &lt;em&gt;Brady&lt;/em&gt; material. The Court also rejected the Fourth Circuit’s assessment that every fairminded jurist would find the undisclosed forensic report material, noting the strong evidence linking Martin to the crime, including DNA evidence, witness testimony, and a motive for the attempted murder. The Court underscored that AEDPA requires federal courts to give the “benefit of the doubt” to state court decisions and to avoid imposing opinion-writing standards on state courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outcome:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment of the Fourth Circuit was reversed, and the case was remanded for further proceedings consistent with the Supreme Court’s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>